<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Artificiall embellishments, or Arts best directions how to preserve beauty or procure it.</title>
            <author>Jeamson, Thomas, d. 1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 241 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 105 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17155</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11931312</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11931312</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51143</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46696)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51143)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 816:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Artificiall embellishments, or Arts best directions how to preserve beauty or procure it.</title>
                  <author>Jeamson, Thomas, d. 1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 192 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: M.S.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Jeamson. cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Table of contents: p. [13]-[16]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Beauty, Personal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51143:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51143:1"/>
            <p>ARTIFICIALL Embelliſhments.</p>
            <p>OR <hi>ARTS BEST DIRECTIONS</hi> How to Preſerve Beauty or Procure it.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Anacr.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed by <hi>William Hall, Ann.</hi> D. 1665.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51143:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51143:2"/>
            <head>To The HONOURABLE <hi>And Truly Vertuous</hi> A. E.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Trifles ſhould be made Preſents to perſons of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, or that theſe worthleſs lines, ſhould court the Eye of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, are faults that ſcarce any will pardon but <hi>Your Ladiſhip,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:51143:3"/>whoſe <hi>Goodnes</hi> is as <hi>Great</hi> as your <hi>Beauty</hi> is <hi>Glorious.</hi> 'Twas <hi>That</hi> animated my preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in preſenting this piece to <hi>Your Honour:</hi> for being ſo much divine in every thing elſe, <hi>You</hi> muſt be ſo in Goodnes, and accept a Mite from him, who is unable to make a more ſtately offering. The deſign <hi>Lady</hi> of the Book is not to make any addition to <hi>Your</hi> ſpotles fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but to borrow that from <hi>You</hi> which it promiſeth to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Beauty and Splendour.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours</hi> Moſt Humble Servant <hi>M. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51143:3"/>
            <head>To the Ladies.</head>
            <p>DEformity (faireſt Ladies) is a <hi>ſingle</hi> name, yet a <hi>complicated</hi> miſery; for a young Algebraiſt in this only word, knows how to read a whole <hi>Iliad</hi> of evills. Poets fancy the creature to be hatcht in <hi>Hell;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do they greatly injure it, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as it brings with it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient matter for a whole <hi>Hell</hi> of miſery to thoſe, whoſe darkned ſoules are clouded with it's fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full adumbrations: and as it comes from thence, ſo would it willingly
<pb facs="tcp:51143:4"/>thither againe, as appears from it's ſhunning the light, and only ſolacing it ſelfe in duskie ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes. For thoſe whoſe bodyes are diſmiſt natures <hi>preſſe</hi> with ſome <hi>errata's,</hi> and have not the <hi>royall ſtamp</hi> of Beauty to make them <hi>currant coyne</hi> for humane ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, make choice of obſcurity; judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing death leſſe inſufferable, then that ignominy which too often at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends deformity. It is a diſeaſe uſually looked upon as infectious, and hath one <hi>ſymptome</hi> of dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conſequence, it <hi>breeds obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> and that chiefly to Ladies preferment; ſince none ſave <hi>Grooms</hi> or <hi>Oaſtlers</hi> think thoſe worth their courtſhip, who are ruſted
<pb facs="tcp:51143:4"/>over with ill-inticing looks.</p>
            <p>Now to quit you Ladies from the loathſome embraces of this hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous Hagge, (which might there be ſo many Furies in Hell, would make a fourth) I have publiſhed theſe <hi>Coſmeticks;</hi> ſo Beautify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that thoſe who uſe them ſhall <hi>Diana</hi> it in company, and with a radiant luſtre outſhine their thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skind companions, as ſo many <hi>browner Nymphs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though you may look ſo <hi>pallid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> ſad, that you would be thought to be dropping in your <hi>Graves;</hi> and though your skins be ſo devoid of colour, that they might be taken for your winding ſheets; yet theſe <hi>Recipe's</hi> will give you ſuch a roſie
<pb facs="tcp:51143:5"/>cheerfulnes, as if you had new be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun your reſurrection. They are the handſome Ladies <hi>Panacaea,</hi> of ſuch efficacy that they will teach you creatures of mortality to retrace the ſteps of youth, and transforme the wrinkled hide of <hi>Hecuba</hi> into the tender skin of a tempting <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inchaſe but your cheeks Ladies, with ſome of our auxiliary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guents, and ye ſhall ſee, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act complexions make but foyles to advance your features: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited beauties craven'd with their own defects ſhall crouch in your preſence, and force you almoſt to be proud; while having no parts to value, they ſhall dispond them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.
<pb facs="tcp:51143:5"/>When once your <hi>artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all roſes</hi> diſplay themſelves, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhall ſeem <hi>pale,</hi> as if they <hi>envied</hi> your tempting perfectious; and their <hi>naturall vermilion</hi> ſhall only ſerve them to <hi>bluſh</hi> that their features are outvied by yours. Other Ladies in your company ſhall look like brown-bread ſippets in a diſh of ſnowie cream, or if you will, like blubberd juggs in a cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board of Venice glaſſes, or earthen Chamber pots in a Goldſmiths ſhop.</p>
            <p>If you glory in Captives, and deſire by a sparkling splendour to fire <hi>Platonick Amoretto's</hi> out of their lawleſſe liberty, borrow but luſtre from theſe <hi>Artificiall Smegmaticks,</hi> and you ſhall find
<pb facs="tcp:51143:6"/>none compoſed of a mettal ſo <hi>cold</hi> and Saturnine, that can <hi>Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-like</hi> reſiſt your actuating <hi>flames:</hi> for whiles thoſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams who ſlight the uſe of theſe helps, ſhall have nothing to heigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten affection but the <hi>Antiperiſtaſis</hi> of a <hi>December</hi> look, and <hi>Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matique</hi> complexion, your <hi>Aprill</hi> and <hi>Sanguine</hi> face ſhall infuſe heat into the cold miſogyniſt, and make the ſtouteſt heart a <hi>ſacrifice</hi> to love and <hi>altar</hi> too. If any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine uncaptivated, it ſhall only be thoſe <hi>leaden</hi> hearted cowards, who dare not approach your infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming preſence for feare of <hi>melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> or thoſe emerited Souldiers of <hi>Venus,</hi> whoſe frigid conſtitutions
<pb facs="tcp:51143:6"/>baniſh all youthfull <hi>fires,</hi> out of a timorouſneſſe of being <hi>calcin'd.</hi> Nay the Lillies and Roſes of your cheeks ſhall be the Old mans true <hi>Anacampſerote,</hi> ſuch drugs that ſhall make him think of former joys.</p>
            <p>But perhaps a zealous <hi>Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body</hi> cenſures you for <hi>evill hearts</hi> becauſe you aime at having <hi>good faces;</hi> and would like you the worſe, ſhould you once look ſo well. Yet refuſe not <hi>enlightned,</hi> yea <hi>enlivened eyes,</hi> but with <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than taſt a little hony</hi> though a <hi>furious Saul forbids it.</hi> Be not baniſht company for want of Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, when Art affords an innocent ſupply; nor live a Martyr to that
<pb facs="tcp:51143:7"/>narrow conſcience, which forbids <hi>the uſe of oyle to make a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full countenance.</hi> Borrow our <hi>ruddie vermilion,</hi> and become <hi>purple-pluſht roſes</hi> to be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the hand of ſome captivated <hi>Hero,</hi> leaſt in the <hi>green-ſickneſſe</hi> livery of your own ſwarthy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions, you be taken for <hi>thiſtles</hi> and crapt by <hi>Aſſes.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:51143:7"/>
            <list>
               <item>THE INDEX.</item>
               <item>The Prooeme.</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>PART. I. Of the whole Body and Beautifying thereof. 5.</head>
                     <item>Cap. 1. <hi>How Women with Child are to order themſelves that they may be delivered of fair and handſom Children.</hi> Pag. 7</item>
                     <item>Cap. 2. <hi>What courſe of life may probably be the beſt either to procure Beauty or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it.</hi> Pag. 16</item>
                     <item>Cap. 3. <hi>External means to gain a good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion.</hi> Pag. 30</item>
                     <item>Cap. 4. <hi>How to beautifie a white and pallid complexion.</hi> Pag. 39</item>
                     <item>Cap. 5. <hi>To ſmooth a rough and uneven Skin.</hi> Pag. 41</item>
                     <item>Cap. 6. <hi>How to cleans the ſweatie and ſluttiſh Complexion.</hi> Pag. 42</item>
                     <item>Cap. 7. <hi>How to repair the beauty of an itchy or ſcabby skin,</hi> Pag. 46</item>
                     <item>Cap. 8. <hi>To adorne the ſcurffie and mealy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion.</hi> Pag. 51</item>
                     <item>Cap. 9. <hi>How to poliſh the Skin when it is disfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured with Scars, or marks of the Small Pox.</hi> Pag. 54</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:51143:8"/>
                     <item>Cap. 10. <hi>How to remove ſpots in what part of the body ſoever.</hi> Pag. 58</item>
                     <item>Cap. 11. <hi>To reduce the body that is too fat to a meane and handſome proportion.</hi> Pag. 63</item>
                     <item>Cap. 12. <hi>To make the body or any part thereof plump and fat, that was before too leane.</hi> Pag. 65</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>PART. II. Of the Head, Neck, and Breaſts, 70</head>
                     <item>Cap. 1. <hi>To cure Redneſs and fiery Pimples in the Face.</hi> Pag. 71</item>
                     <item>Cap. 2. <hi>How to free the face from freckles.</hi> Pag. 82</item>
                     <item>Cap. 3. <hi>To whiten a tan'd viſage and to keep the face from Sunburn.</hi> Pag. 83</item>
                     <item>Cap. 4. <hi>To remove running Tettars, or ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Puſtules.</hi> Pag. 85</item>
                     <item>Cap. 5. <hi>How to help the Complexion when it is marr'd with blue and congealed blood, or black and blue, proceeding from a ſtroak or bruiſe.</hi> Pag. 87</item>
                     <item>Cap. 6. <hi>To ſmooth the face disfigured with wrinckles.</hi> Pag. 89</item>
                     <item>Cap. 7. <hi>How to cure chaps in the Face.</hi> Pag. 91</item>
                     <item>Cap. 8. <hi>Remedies for the Face when it is Burnt or Scalded.</hi> Pag. 92</item>
                     <item>Cap. 9. <hi>To beautifie the Face howſoever dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured.</hi> Pag. 94</item>
                     <item>Cap. 10 <hi>How to faſten the Hair, and keep it from falling off.</hi> Pag. 102</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:51143:8"/>
                     <item>Cap. 11. <hi>Remedies for the want of haire, how to make it grow on any bald place, or there where it never came before.</hi> Pag. 104</item>
                     <item>Cap. 12. <hi>How to take away haire and keep it from growing againe.</hi> Pag. 107</item>
                     <item>Cap. 13. <hi>How to make the haire Curle.</hi> Pag. 109</item>
                     <item>Cap. 14. <hi>To make the Haire Lank and flag.</hi> Pag. 112</item>
                     <item>Cap. 15. <hi>To lengthen the Haire.</hi> Pag. 113</item>
                     <item>Cap. 16. <hi>To ſoften the Haire when too harſh and ſtiffe.</hi> Pag. 115</item>
                     <item>Cap. 17. <hi>Remedies for the Hair when it ſplits.</hi> Pag. 117</item>
                     <item>Cap. 18. <hi>To make the haire of what colour you please.</hi> Pag. 119</item>
                     <item>Cap. 19. <hi>How to cleanſe the haire of ſcurfe and dandruffe.</hi> Pag. 123</item>
                     <item>Cap. 20. <hi>How to beautifie the forehead.</hi> Pag. 125</item>
                     <item>Cap. 21. <hi>How to beautifie and adorn the brows.</hi> Pag. 127</item>
                     <item>Cap. 22. <hi>Remedies for Inflammation, Bloodſhot, or Spots in the Eyes, and yellowneſs of the Eye-lids.</hi> Pag. 130</item>
                     <item>Cap. 23. <hi>To alter the ill colour of the eyes and how to make them bigger or leſſe.</hi> Pag. 135</item>
                     <item>Cap. 24. <hi>To make the Lips ruddie,</hi> Pag. 135</item>
                     <item>Cap. 25. <hi>How to ſmooth the Lips when they are rough and chapt.</hi> Pag. 137</item>
                     <item>Cap. 26. <hi>Remedies for ſuch vices as are incident to the Noſe.</hi> Pag. 140</item>
                     <item>Cap. 27. <hi>How to faſten cleanſe, and preſerve
<pb facs="tcp:51143:9"/>the Teeth.</hi> Pag. 142</item>
                     <item>Cap. 28. <hi>To Sweeten the Breath.</hi> Pag. 145</item>
                     <item>Cap. 29. <hi>How to beautifie the Neck.</hi> Pag. 148</item>
                     <item>Cap. 30. <hi>How to keep the Breaſts from growing too big, and to make them plumpe and round.</hi> Pag. 151</item>
                     <item>Cap. 31. <hi>Remedies for Inflammations or Hardneſs of the Breaſts, and chaps in the Nipples.</hi> Pag. 153</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>PART. III. How to Beautifie the Arms, Hands Leggs and Feet. 157</head>
                     <item>Cap. 1. <hi>To remedie ſweating of the Armpits, and other inconveniences proceeding thence.</hi> Pag. 158</item>
                     <item>Cap. 2. <hi>For Chaps and Warts in the Arms or Hands.</hi> Pag. 160</item>
                     <item>Cap. 3 <hi>How to make the Hands fair and white, and to leſſen the Veins when they appear too big.</hi> Pag. 162</item>
                     <item>Cap. 4. <hi>For the Hands when they are ſwoln and look red or blew with cold.</hi> Pag. 166</item>
                     <item>Cap. 5. <hi>Remedies for thoſe vices which are inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the nails.</hi> Pag. 168</item>
                     <item>Cap. 6. <hi>Remedies for the galling, fretting and ſweating of the feet.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cap. 7. <hi>Remedies whereby to be freed from Kibes and Cornes.</hi> Pag. 172</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>PART. IIII. Sents and Perfumes fitted for ſeverall occaſions.</head>
                     <item>Cap. 1. <hi>Perfumed Pomanders for Bracelets.</hi> Pag. 176</item>
                     <item>Cap. 2. <hi>Pouders for the Hair, Linnen, and Sweet Baggs.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51143:9"/>
            <head>Artificiall EMBELLISHMENTS.</head>
            <div type="proem">
               <head>The Prooeme.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Soule</hi> that better part of Man, when it becomes Tenant to the <hi>Body,</hi> ſhould have it not a <hi>Priſon</hi> but a <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace,</hi> a <hi>Lodging,</hi> whoſe ſtructure and ſuperficiall Ornaments might make its Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage pleaſant, and invite its ſtay; not a <hi>Dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> a <hi>Cyprian Ceramo</hi> to ſtifle it with its loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome compoſure, or with its deformed Frontis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece to fright it to a ſeparation. It would be too much to the diſcredit of our Nobler part, ſhould we be as Mountains graved with golden Ore, which clouded with barren duſt, and ſterill ſands, uſually ſeem as poor without as they are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51143:10"/>rich within. Surely diamond ſoules inchas'd with Noble functions, deſervé a cryſtall caſe, and nature it ſelfe cloaths Orientall Jewels in mother of Pearl. The crooked body may perhaps yeeld ſervice, but never gaine repute to a ſprightly mind: and ſad was the fortune of <hi>Socrates</hi> whoſe <hi>Royall</hi> Soule was condemn'd to the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of a crooked or miſhapen body: More hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Fortune had the Roman <hi>Lucretia,</hi> whoſe braver Spirit, had for its lodging a <hi>White-hall,</hi> ſutable to its <hi>Grandure,</hi> I mean her body, ſo fair in features, that her Companions, ſome called her, others believed her <hi>Venus</hi> in the diſguiſe of <hi>Lucretia,</hi> or <hi>Lucretia</hi> coppied out from <hi>Venus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Should we be as ſtately clothed as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpian</hi> was, when <hi>Alexander Severus</hi> wrapt him in his Imperiall Robes, we would neither think our ſelves too gaudy, nor our Bodies cloathed in too rich apparell: and ſhould we be contented with any tatter'd, deformed Body, which ſhould be neat apparell to the ſoule, and which it either finds or elſe would make ſo? For could our Soule alwaies have a ſupply of materials ſuting its active power, none ſhould ever be deformed, but too often encountring diſobedient matter, which repells its plaſtick beams, it frequently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats it ſelfe, and in a retired ſolitude ſeems to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51143:10"/>lament that Art comes not Auxiliary to its ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour.</p>
               <p>In pitty to ſuch impriſon'd ſoules, Art unlocks its Magazeen of Medicines, endeavouring to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite all parts of the Body in charming Concords of alluring features, and give each Member ſuch a pleaſing ſplendour, that Native Beauties ſeem but dull and dying ſhadows, to ſet forth their more rich and lively Colours. But all Bodies not being equally capacitated for its impreſſions, it uſually imploys its skill about the Female Sex; whoſe ſoft and pliant earth, Nature works with a more carefull hand, to make it a thriving ſoile for the tender plant of Beauty; ſo that it ſlights Men, and caſts them by, as Canvace too courſe and rough to draw thereon the taking lineaments of a cleare and ſmooth-fac'd <hi>Venus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ye Ladies then are the Dearelings that Art moſt reſpects, and for whoſe ſake are compoſed ſuch Aromatique unguents, ſuch beautifying oils and eſſences, that would you but accept their profer'd aſſiſtance, there is none of you but might equallize a <hi>Hellen:</hi> here only would be the difference, that a <hi>Paris</hi> came from <hi>Troy</hi> to Raviſh her, but multitudes would make longer journeys to Admire you.</p>
               <p>This ſubſequent Treatiſe, (ſolely compoſed Ladies for your concernment) is abundantly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51143:11"/>ſtored with ſuch <hi>Artificiall Embelliſhments:</hi> and that it might not it ſelfe, be deficient in what it preſents to you, Beauty; it is regularly metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diz'd into a quaternion of parts. The <hi>Firſt</hi> whereof treats of Embelliſhing the Body in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall; the <hi>Next</hi> of the Head, neck and breaſt; the <hi>Third</hi> of the Hands, Armes, Leggs and Feet; and the <hi>Laſt</hi> ſupplies you with Sents, Perfumes and Pouders, fitted for the exigencies of any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergent occaſion. Of each of theſe in Order.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51143:11"/>
               <head>Artificiall Embelliſhments.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>PART. I.</hi> Of the whole Body, and the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying thereof.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Body, that weak and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving manſion of mortality, is expoſed to the treacherous un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derminings of ſo many Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and Diſtempers, that its own frailty ſeems Petitioner for ſome artificial Enamel, which might be a fixation to Natures inconſtancy, and a help to its variating infirmities. For he that narrowly obſerves that fading houſe of diſtemper'd clay, will ſoon find that it aemulats the <hi>Moon</hi> in muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; that though to day it be varniſht with a purple and lively bluſh, to morrow it will be ſo white waſht with a meager paleneſs, as if Death had took it to hire, and made it a whited Sepulchre; that though to day it be ſo <hi>ſmooth</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:51143:12"/>and <hi>plain,</hi> that <hi>Venus</hi> her ſelf might be tempted to take her Recreation there; to morrow it will be ſo <hi>rough-caſt</hi> with a naſty Elephantiaſis, that <hi>Cupid</hi> can ſcarce walk there without being over ſhooes.</p>
               <p>Now to ſublimate Nature beyond the reach of Sickneſs, to a laſting and aetherial Pulcritude, and by coſmetick Antidotes to fortifie it with an incapacity of being ſuppriſed by any feature-fretting malady, would be a buſineſs ſhould puzzle not only a whole Elaboratory of <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts,</hi> but their <hi>Archeus</hi> too; although of the privy Council to Nature, and confident to her recluded privacies. But to make that Lure of Love, <hi>Beauty,</hi> of a more than ordinary luſtre; to fix the Complexion of the Body ſo, that it be not too frequent in its variation; or to keep the fair and damask skin from being too much ſullied with Deformities filthy fingers, is a task not tranſcending the ſphaere of a modeſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking activity.</p>
               <p>For it is that, which hath with happy ſucceſs been often effected, by a convenient <hi>regulating the phantaſie,</hi> or imagination of the Mother, whilſt ſhe is with Child; by <hi>uſing food of quick concoction,</hi> and eaſie nouriſhment; by <hi>moderate and frequent exerciſe;</hi> by <hi>the application of thoſe things which adorn the body</hi> with an enamour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and lively colour; by <hi>taking away thoſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51143:12"/>which may vitiate the features,</hi> as ſwarthineſs of the Complexion, ſcars and ſpots of the Skin, naſty ſweat, &amp;c. by <hi>keeping the body and every member thereof, that it be neither too groſſe or too lean,</hi> and the like: Concerning all which, we intend to give ſome Directions in the following Chapters of this Firſt Part.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> How Women with Child are to order them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that they may be delivered of fair and handſom Children.</head>
                  <p>INtending to furniſh you (lovely Ladies) with ſuch Preſcriptions as moſt neerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the beautifying of the Body; it will be requiſite to begin with ſome ſpecial and ſingular means, how to help the comely formation, of the tender <hi>Embryo,</hi> while it is yet in Natures <hi>Elaboratory,</hi> the <hi>Wombe;</hi> that ſo it may be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from the confuſed <hi>Chaos</hi> of the leſſer world, not a <hi>miſhapen</hi> or <hi>monſtrous</hi> lump, but a ſparkling luminary, and a piece that Nature may take for a pattern, when ſhe attempts the compoſure of a perſon ſhe intends to boaſt of.</p>
                  <p>Amongſt thoſe ſeveral things which tend to this exact compleating of the <hi>Foetus,</hi> there is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51143:13"/>nothing more ſignally concurrs than the <hi>imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> of the breeding Mother. This is that buſie Architectrix of the brain, which contrives ſuch machinations, and acts ſuch miracles, that it is a miracle almoſt to find any that believe them. For, let but the great-bellyed Mother exerciſe moderately, and uſe ordinary whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, diet, there will need nothing more to have Children ſo fair, that you may by their own ſplendor be lighted to view their perfections; then the regular ordering of the <hi>fancy:</hi> which is ſuperintendent to the growing infant, and the Mothers active <hi>emiſſary,</hi> that with all obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiouſneſs executes her <hi>wiſhes</hi> on the tender Babe in the Wombe. For finding the ſoft and plyant <hi>Faetus</hi> pinion'd in a membranious <hi>mantle,</hi> and lying helpleſly drowſie in Natures <hi>cradle,</hi> it freely without reſiſtance makes impreſſion as the Mother directs it. So that ſhe by the help of this inviſible Agent uſually works &amp; adorns the Infant with thoſe features which her mind moſt runs upon, and ſhe her ſelf affects.</p>
                  <p>He that conſiders the various relations that ſeveral Authors make of the <hi>Phantaſies</hi> imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Tyranny</hi> over the growing <hi>Embryo,</hi> will with ſmall reluctancy admit its Plaſticks power in a comely compoſure. <hi>Helmont</hi> makes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of a Taylors Wife, who being big with Child, and ſeeing before her doors a duell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51143:13"/>two Souldiers, one whereof loſt his hand in the combate; fell preſently (being frighted with the ſight) into labour, and was delivered of a Daughter with one hand, the other arm bleeding, and having the hand cut off at the ſame place with the maimed Souldier. The <hi>ſame Author</hi> gives us another ſtory altogether as ſtrange, of a Merchants Wiſe at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and a familiar acquaintance of his, who ſome weeks before the time of her Delivery, hearing that there were thirteen condemned perſons to be beheaded, was deſirous to ſee them executed, and to that purpoſe gets to a friends houſe in the Market-place, where the windows look'd full out upon the Scaffolds; but ſcarce had ſhe ſeen the firſt ſuffer, when ſhe cried out for a Midwife, and was delivered of a lovely Boy, that had his head newly parted from his ſhoulders. Other Writers alſo give us the like ſtories. <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> in his Philoſophy, tells us of one great with Child, that being ſet upon by a company of bloody Villains, and ſtab'd in ſeveral parts of her body, ſuddenly after died, and the Child that was cut out of her Womb, had ſo many blue ſpots like broiſes in his body, as the Mother had ſtabbs, and in the very ſame parts, wherein ſhe was wounded. <hi>Munſter</hi> likewiſe makes mention of a Woman with Child, that ſtanding whiſpering with another, and a third coming ſoftly behind,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51143:14"/>and knocking their foreheads together, was ſoon after delivered of Twins, with their foreheads joyned together. Beſides all this, there are yet more ſtupendious actions, which may be recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as the products of a working Phancie, That <hi>Alcippe</hi> (in <hi>Pliny</hi>) ſhould be delivered of an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant: that a Woman in <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſhould be Mother to a Child with a Rams-head: or, that <hi>Plutarcks</hi> Matron, expecting a Son, ſhould be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with an ugly Centaure, are effects which the moſt rational heads generally refer to the <hi>imagination.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now if <hi>Phanſie</hi> or the Imaginative power can tranſpoſe the parts of the <hi>Foetus</hi> and make it a monſter; if it can turn <hi>executioner,</hi> and ſet the little Infants ſoul free from the priſon of its bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, while its body is ſtill priſoner to the womb; why may it not as well act the <hi>Painter,</hi> and have the diſpoſing of Natures <hi>colours,</hi> to draw as it pleaſeth, raviſhing, or elſe leſs inticing features? Certainly, if we confider what <hi>Galen</hi> relates of a woman who brought forth a Son not like the Father, who was much deformed, but reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling a comely picture hanging in her Chamber, whereon he wiſhed her to think earneſtly when ſhe embraced her Husband: Or if we call to mind how ſome by often looking on a Black-a-moores picture, have been delivered of a Child clouded with Natures ſooty mask, and wrapt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51143:14"/>in the ſable mantle of a ſwarthy skin; we cannot but be convinced, that the Infant comes into the world apparel'd with thoſe features, which the Phancy, that commanding Empreſs of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers brain, diſpences from her own ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robe.</p>
                  <p>So that if ye deſire (Ladies) to have Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, whoſe beauty ſhall ecclipſe all other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and be an attracting magnet to neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring eyes, propoſe to your Phancies ſuch pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns as may excite both your own, and others admiration; whether it be ſome perſon who monopolizes perfections, and is the royal exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer of unparallel'd beauty, or ſome lively pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil'd picture of a moſt abſolute proportion of parts, temper of colours, and vivacity of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect. For ſome ſuch exquiſite pattern being once made choice of, and in time of conception, or elſe of being with child, often thought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and beheld with intenſneſs, will by little and little imprint in the mind a noble <hi>Idea</hi> of the ſame perfections, which the active <hi>Phancie</hi> ſoon apprehends as a propoſed pattern, to work thereby a parallel piece; and therefore with an obſequious celerity informs the <hi>appetite,</hi> which immediately ſummons the <hi>ſubtle humors</hi> and the moſt <hi>ſpirituous</hi> parts of the blood, as inferiour officers, and they receive an impreſſion of this <hi>Idea,</hi> which they carry in triumph through
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51143:15"/>all the coaſts of the <hi>microcoſme,</hi> till they arrive at thoſe parts whereto they were deſigned by the direction of their <hi>Empreſs Phancy:</hi> Who thinking no repoſitory too ſecure for ſo fair a ſpecies, commands thoſe agile emiſſaries to trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure it up in the ſeed, which is the moſt new and durable aedifice in all its <hi>dominions,</hi> and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to laſt when all the reſt ſhall lye buried in the duſt of their final ruines, Or if ſhe be intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with this <hi>Idea,</hi> in the time of the Mothers being great, ſhe immediately ſends thoſe active agents with it to the Womb, that <hi>mint</hi> of the microcoſme, to have it <hi>ſtampt</hi> by the Plaſtick faculty on the growing <hi>Foetus,</hi> that ſo it may be in a capacity to act its princely part on the theatre of the world, where it may attract the eyes of future admirers, and with a radiant luſtre vye with its Prototype.</p>
                  <p>But ſome of you perhaps may be ſo ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous as to enquire, that ſeeing the Phancie is meerly a cognoſcitive faculty, and Women uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally fix their thoughts on ſeveral and various objects during the times of Conception and Gravidation; how it comes to paſs that we find not the Infant ſubject to more numerous mutations, according to the variety of impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made by ſundry ſpecies on the imagination? The Reply to this will be eaſie, if we conſider, that if the matter were more ſeriouſly pondred,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51143:15"/>we ſhould not find the <hi>Imagination</hi> ſo ſeldome active as generally is ſuppoſed: for it is very probable that the reſemblance of every child, whether with the father, mother or any other perſon, hath ſome near dependance on ſome operation or other of the mothers Phantaſy; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as her mind was with more intenſneſs fixt upon ſuch or ſuch a party. But yet again it is not every act of the phantaſy, which is able to affect the formative power reſiding in the womb; but only that which is ſtrong, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with the powerfull commotion of the ſpirits and humours in the body. So that there being not many acts of the phantaſy concomita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the energie of ſuch commotions, 'tis no wonder that infants ſignally affected with the mothers phantaſy are ſo few. Thoſe phantaſies onely induce ſuch agitations of the humours &amp; ſpirits as are requiſite to affect the Foetus, which are followed by violent <hi>paſſions</hi> of a ſurpriſing <hi>feare</hi> or an earneſt &amp; longing <hi>deſire:</hi> for theſe are the moſt turbulent and impetuous paſſions that the mind is ſubject to; which exciting the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuious humours and ſpirits in all parts of the body, cauſe both in the mother and infant remarkable alterations.</p>
                  <p>Take but an inſtance or two of the effects of both theſe unruly paſſions. <hi>Baptiſta Porta</hi> in his natural magick, tels us of a woman who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morouſly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51143:16"/>affecting a Marble ſtatue, dead indeed in it ſelf, but for her luſt too lively, by frequent looking on it, and continuall keeping of it in her mind, brought forth a ſonne plumpe, pale, of a glittering colour and in every thing repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the features of the too much admired marble. <hi>Ficinus</hi> reports for a truth of a woman that ſhe brought forth a daughter which had a wel proportioned body, but for a head onely two Scallop-ſhels joyned to the ſhoulders, which ſhe opened at pleaſure to receive her meat and lived ſo eleven yeares; and that which occaſioned the production of this monſter, was, as he ſays, the mothers longing for Scallops whilſt ſhe was with child and not being able after great induſtrie to get any to ſatisfie her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient deſires. So <hi>Delrio</hi> in his magical diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, gives us a relation of a noble Lady that was nurſe to a very beautifull prince then Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin of France, whom ſhe loved ſo entirely that ſhe cauſed his effigies to be drawn, and carried it about with her, ſcarce induring it out of her ſight; whereon it hapned that ſhe became mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to a child ſo like the young Prince, that the generality of people knew no other diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſave that of their cloaths. And as for the paſſion of <hi>fear, Levinus Lemnius</hi> hath the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of an unhappy wagge that ſuppriſing a great bellied woman with the ſight of a boys picture
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51143:16"/>with a monſtrous great head, cauſed her to bring forth a child of the ſame miſhapen mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude.</p>
                  <p>Theſe inſtances are ſufficient to demonſtrate that the <hi>phanſie</hi> when attended with either of thoſe <hi>paſſions,</hi> hath power to alter the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and complexion of the yeelding <hi>foetus;</hi> and that to have handſome and beautifull children there is little elſe required, then the avoiding all monſtrous objects and ſtories which may diſtract the phanſie; and in their ſtead, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of ſome amiable object, from whence the phantaſie affecting it with a paſſionate tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, may coppy out an Idea of perfect beauty to communicate to the plaſtick facultie; whoſe chiefeſt care is to erect a ſtately ſtructure out of the rude maſſe that lyes ſo confus'd within the womb.</p>
                  <p>This is the opinion of ſeverall antient and excellent Phyſitians as <hi>Hippocrat.</hi> in his book of <hi>Superfoetation. Galen</hi> in the 14. cap. of his book concerning <hi>Theriacle</hi> to <hi>Piſo.</hi> And <hi>Laurentius</hi> in his <hi>Anatomicall Contraverſies. l.</hi> 8. <hi>q.</hi> 10. of <hi>Wierus. Codronchus.</hi> But enough of theſe. I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten in the next chapter to give directions what <hi>courſe of life</hi> is requiſite that thoſe lead, who would purchaſe that they have not, or elſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that beauty they have alreadie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:51143:17"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> What courſe of life may probably be the beſt either to procure Beauty or preſerve it.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>COurſe of life</hi> here mentioned, is intended as a generall notion, comprehending all thoſe things which <hi>Phyſitians</hi> uſually terme <hi>res non naturales:</hi> ſo that it almoſt takes in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever may cauſe a ſenſible alteration in the body, as the <hi>external aire, ſleeping</hi> and <hi>watching, repoſe</hi> or <hi>exerciſe, evacuation</hi> or <hi>retention</hi> of the excrements, <hi>paſſions</hi> or <hi>perturbations</hi> of the mind, and laſtly <hi>meats</hi> or <hi>drinks</hi> whether medicinall or alimentary. For each of theſe as we ſhall briefly ſhew do ſignally affect both body and beauty too.</p>
                  <p>Firſt then the <hi>aire</hi> is that liquid <hi>ocean,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in each Pilgrim of us all muſt <hi>traffique</hi> if we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to make thriving husbands, or gaine the leaſt addition to the too ſoon waſted number of our fleeting days: It is our more gentle <hi>Aeolus,</hi> that breaths forth proſperous <hi>gales</hi> into the expanded lobes of our lungs, to <hi>land</hi> us ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the ſilver top't Alps of hoary haires. But ſeldome is it that it keeps ſuch an evenneſſe in in its <hi>blaſts,</hi> as not to cauſe ſome ſenſible <hi>varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51143:17"/>in our beauty that <hi>Loadſtone</hi> of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: For it variouſly affects the body both within and without. <hi>Inwardly,</hi> as it is ſuckt into the lungs, thoſe panting bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, ſo naturally contrived to keep the boſie furnace of the heart boiling; then it communicates its qualities to the very fountain of life; next to the blood, and ſo univerſally to the whole body. <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly,</hi> as it beats continually upon the ſuperficiall skin, and cauſes roughneſſe, chaps and ſundry other accidents accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to its ſeverall conſtitution. So that great care is to be taken to preſerve the body from the impreſſions of an ill diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>aire,</hi> whether too moiſt, or too dry, too hot or too cold. For an <hi>aire</hi> too <hi>moiſt</hi> will ſoon <hi>waſh</hi> off natures <hi>paint;</hi> and if ladies live too long in foggs, it is the readie way to ſtaine their <hi>damask</hi> skins. The <hi>lillies</hi> and <hi>roſes</hi> of the cheeks will fade rather then flowriſh if too much <hi>water'd:</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> her ſelf though borne in <hi>Neptunes</hi> watery pallace would never be nurſt there, fearing the tender plants of beauty would never thrive in that liquid <hi>ſoile.</hi> Wherefore I can ſcarce approve the practice of ſome Ladies, who to allay the petty exorbitancie of a ruddie colour, in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51143:18"/>the evenings wherein damp miſts and dews fall, expoſe their naked breaſts and faces to <hi>Cynthia</hi>'s moiſtening rays, as if the moon (becauſe pale her ſelf) would make them ſo; or her ſpitting in the face were to ſcoure it. Certainly beauty never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents that <hi>Laundreſſe</hi> ſhould <hi>whiten</hi> her livery, who uſes no other <hi>ſope</hi> then her own foggie excrements. Such practiſes, I confeſſe, ſince they occaſion rheums, catarrhs, and diſtillations may make the face white or pallid but never faire or handſome. So on the contrarie an <hi>aire</hi> too <hi>dry</hi> doth ſo wrinkle and chap the skin our native <hi>ſhirt,</hi> that nature or art can ſcarce ever work it with a beautiful <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidery.</hi> Next a <hi>bleake</hi> and <hi>piercing aire</hi> is a mortall enemy to a lovely complexion; it makes the skin rough, conſtipates the pores and hinders the exhalation of the excrements, and theſe lying betwixt the skin and the fleſh do exceedingly vitiate the complexion, making it livid and dull. So that thoſe Ladies are to be reproved that goe with their breaſts bare and naked in the midſt of froſt and ſnow. Thoſe ſwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mounts where <hi>Cupid</hi> makes his neſt, ſhould have a warmer <hi>covering</hi> then a ſnowie <hi>fleece,</hi> for feare thoſe milkie foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51143:18"/>may be curdled with a chilly cold, and he forc'd to ſhift for fairer lodgings. Neither is the contrary extream of <hi>heat</hi> leſſe prejudiciall to a faire and tender skin; it tempts the blood to the externall parts, and there tanns it into a wainſcot hew: Be carefull Ladies then, not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe your beauty to a parching heat, for feare you ſoon bewaile your raſh attempt in the ſable vaile of a ſootie skin. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if it be in your power to chooſe an <hi>aire</hi> to better your complexions, make choice of a ſeat ſomewhat raiſed that it be not expoſed to the inconveniences of fogs and miſts, which too frequently peſter the lower habitations; let it be ſheltered round with pleaſant woods and groves which may fence you from the blew im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of a pinching <hi>Boreas,</hi> and in the Summer ſecure you that <hi>Sol</hi> with his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous beames ſhall not kiſs your beauty away. But in this election of <hi>aires</hi> regard is to be had to the conſtitution of the perſon; for thoſe whoſe cheeks are tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctur'd with a deeper bluſh, ought to chooſe a cooler; and thoſe whoſe lillie features ſeem wan and pallid, a hotter place; yet with this caution, that they expoſe themſelves to no heat or cold but what is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51143:19"/>moderate; for extremity of cold too vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently repels the blood inward and exceſſe of heat draws it too much out.</p>
                  <p>In the next place <hi>moderation</hi> either in <hi>ſleeping</hi> or <hi>waking</hi> conduces much to the preſervation of a comely face. Exceſſive <hi>ſleep</hi> makes the body dull and heavie, the colour pale, ſwarthie and livid; for it is eaſie to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> know Morpheus's ſluggiſh vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries by thoſe <hi>ſullied</hi> impreſſions his <hi>leaden</hi> heels leave in their fleſhie robes. So on the other ſide <hi>watching</hi> over much ſpends the ſpirits, exceedingly dries the moiſture of the body; and if you make it a frequent cuſtome to extend it to unuſuall periods, it will ſcarce leave ye, Ladies, <hi>blood</hi> enough to <hi>crimſon</hi> your cheeks with a <hi>vermilion</hi> bluſh for the loſſe of your beauty.</p>
                  <p>What hath been ſaid of <hi>ſleeping</hi> and <hi>watching</hi> may rationally be interpreted of <hi>repoſe</hi> and <hi>exerciſe:</hi> for repoſe is but a waking <hi>ſleep</hi> and <hi>exerciſe</hi> a more active <hi>watching.</hi> If any love their eaſe too much they ſoon contract the <hi>ruſt</hi> of idleneſſe, which will ſurely <hi>ironmould</hi> the fineſt skin; and they that exerciſe immoderately; quickly were out beauties ſilken livery; and when once ye come Ladies to weare deformities home ſpun garments, you are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51143:19"/>quite broke for beauties; for none will think you worth the looking after, and your whole <hi>ſtock</hi> of features will hardly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure any to <hi>lend</hi> you an eye.</p>
                  <p>How much <hi>evacuation</hi> or <hi>retention of the excrements</hi> either promote or hinder a good complexion, you will eaſily imagine if you conſider that the reaking entrails are the bodies <hi>ſinke,</hi> which, if it be not duely cleans'd and ſcour'd, affects the face with ſuch noiſome <hi>exhalations</hi> that the ſquea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Queen of love will never be wonne upon to make it her court of reſidence.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>perturbations</hi> and unruly <hi>poſſions of the mind</hi> do offer greater violence to the features then any thing elſe; their impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous motions raiſe an earthquake in the leſſer world which ruines the ſtately ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Cupids palace. <hi>Griefe</hi> is the moth of Beauty, it frets out the characters of natures faireſt Orthography; wearing off thoſe ruddie and carnation flouriſhes which her skilfull pencill drew, it makes the face a diſcolourable blank; and renders thoſe who over much indulge it, ſo wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and pale, that they ſeem but walking ſhrouds to carry themſelves to their own ſhadie ſepulchers. <hi>Anger</hi> is beauties <hi>burning</hi> feaver, which <hi>fieres</hi> the <hi>furnace</hi> of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51143:20"/>heart with too ſcortching <hi>flames</hi> that <hi>bake</hi> the exteriour features into a brownbread ſwarthineſſe: and it would be ſtrange, ſhould ſuch courſe fare ever feaſt ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors eyes. <hi>Feare</hi> congeals the blood and baths the body in a chilly ſweat, which often enlivens the haire to an active though frightfull erection, but never clears the skin: nay it does your beautie more miſchiefe then if you ſhould intoxicate your ſelves with <hi>Circe's</hi> bewitching potion: for the worſt this could do, would be to make ye handſome beaſts; but feare cauſes a more frightfull metamorphoſis and makes ye foule deformed women. Laſtly <hi>melancholy</hi> is a ſullen humourſome ſpirit that raiſes tempeſts in the very center of the body; which overcloud the face with griefe, and wrinkle the forehead before Thirty: it makes that Ladie whom it once over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes, to be out of love with the whole world and beauty to be out of love with her: while ſhe thinks her ſelfe weary of other mens eyes, other men finding little worth their ſight, are as weary of viewing her: they ſoon perceive that beauty <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting</hi> her maiden <hi>lillies</hi> and ruddie <hi>roſes</hi> to ſome more courted <hi>Elyſium;</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51143:20"/>that face ſhall lye <hi>fallow,</hi> which me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy frowns wrinkle into uneven <hi>fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows.</hi> What hath thus particularly been ſaid of ſome <hi>perturbations</hi> of the mind, may be underſtood of all in general; ſo that all <hi>paſſions</hi> whatever, as they are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally call'd the Souls burning feaver, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they make it ferment it ſelf into a pernicious exceſs; ſo may they fitly be named the Beauties waſting conſumption, ſince they leave no marks of that excellent comelineſs, which uſeth to work aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all beholders, but make the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer good looks give place to a ſallow complexion.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, <hi>Meats</hi> and <hi>Drinks</hi> have a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouling power over the features, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable lineaments of a taking face, and give great occaſions towards the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king or marring a beauty: For by <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking,</hi> the humors, and more ſolid parts of the body, which are in a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive emanation, are nouriſhed and kept in continual repair. Certainly, if we may believe Phyſitians, the moderate uſe of healthful <hi>dyet</hi> corroborates the innate heat, makes the external members well coloured, and lively to perform thoſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for which Nature hath intended
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51143:21"/>them. On the contrary, an <hi>intemperate life,</hi> abandon'd indifferently to all ſorts of <hi>meats,</hi> without diſtinction either of time or meaſure, ſtifles the internal heat, breeds corrupted blood, from whence proceed obſtructions of the more noble parts, a vitiated maſs of malignant humors, which cauſe a diſcoloured, pale and tawny viſage, ſtinking breath, rotten teeth, running eyes, and infinite other inconveniencies: Wherefore, let thoſe that would be beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties favourites, not ſtudy too much kitchin Philoſophy, nor buſie their thoughts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout too ſtately furniſhing their ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Tables, let them have a care of making too bold with <hi>Wine;</hi> if <hi>Bacchus</hi> ſet the face with his fiery carbuncles, and pitch his ſtandard there, beauties vermilion He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauldry will ſoon be expung'd. Yet, on the other ſide, I would not have any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon bring her ſelf down to the loweſt <hi>Gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ut</hi> of <hi>abſtinence,</hi> for this will ſpoyl the <hi>harmony</hi> of a well <hi>tun'd</hi> face, as much as if the <hi>guts</hi> were <hi>ſcrew'd up</hi> to an <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>la</hi> òf <hi>intemperance.</hi> There is but little differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in either extream; exceſſive <hi>gluttony</hi> makes a Lady ſuch a mountain of <hi>greaſie</hi> mummy, that ſhe needs no other <hi>pomatum</hi> for her bloated checks, than the naſty
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51143:21"/>
                     <hi>ſweat</hi> that dribbles from her brow: And <hi>unuſual abſtinence</hi> makes the body like a thin thatch'd Tenement, that hath out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the hopes of having fairer gueſts than grunting Swine; the skin repreſents ſome white earth plaiſtering, and the bones ſo many uneven-laid laths to bear it out. Yet is it the practice of many that are neat and well proportioned enough, fearing they might grow too big and groſſe, to meagre themſelves by long and tedious <hi>faſtings;</hi> and when they eat, to ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe <hi>meats</hi> of bad concoction, as herbs, fruits, ſallads, vinegar, that ſo by a hard and courſe <hi>dyet,</hi> they might become neat and ſlender; when all they do is nothing elſe but to extenuate and diſcolour the body by ſo rude an abſtinence. It were better if ſuch would follow the counſel of Phyſitians, to <hi>eat</hi> often and little, and that meat of good nouriſhment; to <hi>eat</hi> only once a day, or eating twice, to riſe from Table only half ſatisfied, and ſo they might become of a mean and graceful ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitude; without detriment either to health or beauty. I have hitherto ſpoken of <hi>Meats</hi> and <hi>Drinks</hi> that are <hi>Alimentary;</hi> there are yet others that are <hi>Medicinal,</hi> and that equally with theſe advance the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51143:22"/>beauty. For ſince it is a thing very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, if not impoſſible, to live alwayes in ſuch an <hi>Air</hi> as our temperament and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution require, and that many unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come emergencies neither ſuffer us long to be without <hi>care</hi> and <hi>vexation,</hi> nor to keep an exact <hi>dyet,</hi> or to take it in ſuch a mediocrity and oppertune time as is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the breeding of good blood; ſince (I ſay) it is a thing ſo troubleſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to govern our ſelves by the rules and meaſure of an exact method, it will be expedient to anticipate that alteration or corruption, which may happen amongſt the humours of the body, (through <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs,</hi> or any other miſdemeanour in our courſe of life,) by ſome means or other, which hath power to expel thoſe vitious qualities, which may cauſe an ill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion; that ſo the colour may be kept cleer and lively, the skin ſmooth and ſubtle. The laſt means to effect this, will be in due time to <hi>purge</hi> the body with ſome quick and gentle <hi>medicament,</hi> as <hi>Caſſia, Manna, ſyrup of Violets, white Roſes</hi> or the like; if you would clear the body of ſuperfluous humors after too much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulging your pallat, you may take half a dram of <hi>pillulae Ruffi</hi> going to bed, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51143:22"/>the next day you ſhall have all the reliques of your late intemperance, ſwept out in three or four ſtooles. <hi>Vinegar of Squills,</hi> if taken in a morning for ſeveral times to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and you exerciſe moderately after it, beautifies the body with a very freſh and lively colour. The ſame effects have the <hi>Trochisks of red Roſes,</hi> if you carry them about you and take now and then one at your pleaſure. The frequent uſe of <hi>Clyſters</hi> is not without reaſon much commended, for that they do not only make the body ſoluble and <hi>purge</hi> the pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant humors, but alſo divert thoſe fumes and vapors which aſcending to the head alter much the beauty of the face. <hi>Syrup of Fumitory, Agrimony, Cichorie,</hi> open ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, and correct the intemperature of the liver; and for this reaſon are of ſingular uſe for clearing the complecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>It would not be amiſs, if I here put you in mind, to keep the body and all its parts at <hi>eaſe,</hi> without ſtraitning them or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring their free motion and repoſe: For to <hi>girt</hi> the body too cloſe, to <hi>bind</hi> the arms or legs too hard, draws the blood too much from the face, and makes it deſcend to the more inferiour parts. Your
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51143:23"/>own obſervation may ſatisfie you in this particular, for you may frequently perceive thoſe perſons become pale and looſe their complexion, who to have a ſmall and ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der body, girt themſelves too cloſe; or to have a handſome leg and foot, uſe ſtock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and ſhoes much too ſtreight.</p>
                  <p>When the humors apt to corrupt are expel'd and the blood purified, in the place of the vitious, you are to ſupply the body with good humors, by <hi>food</hi> of light concoction and good nouriſhment, as <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nado's,</hi> well <hi>ſeaſoned Broths,</hi> and the like. But before you <hi>eat,</hi> riſe ſomething early, and <hi>exerciſe</hi> moderately, that ſo you may help Nature to diſperſe thoſe humors which were heap'd together during ſleep, and make an equal diſtribution of the ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which in the laſt nights repoſe hath been digeſted. It is the ill cuſtome of ſome Ladies, that they might meliorate their complexions, to take in their beds <hi>Broths, Aſſes</hi> or <hi>Goats milke,</hi> and after <hi>ſleep</hi> upon it: ſuch nouriſhment although it be good and commendable in it ſelf, yet taken in ſuch a ſluttiſh manner, inſtead of breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good blood, is ſoon corrupted and turn'd into a malignant nature; both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſtomach when ſuch meat is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51143:23"/>is not as yet diſcharged of its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements and pituitous ſuperfluities; and the appetite is not as then excited; for that the animal ſpirits which are the cauſes of it, are yet dull and drowſie. Moreover, in the morning Nature being careful of its oeconomy, is imploy'd to drive outward thoſe humid redundancies which were heaped the night before up in the body; but ſuch unreaſonable <hi>eating,</hi> diverts Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from that expulſion, and conſtrains her to retire inward to promote concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo that being diſtracted by two ſuch contrary motions, ſhe performs neither ſo, as much to farther the bodies health. Thus much for that <hi>courſe of life</hi> which ought to be obſerv'd by thoſe who would have their raviſhing features penetrate thoſe flinty breaſts againſt which <hi>Cupids</hi> ſhafts ſeem too blunt and dull: the next <hi>Chapter</hi> ſupplyes you with Remedies which ſhall ſo ſet off the loathſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections of a blear-ey'd and wither'd Maegaera, that ſhe ſhall be taken for ſome attractive and heart ſubduing <hi>Venus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:51143:24"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> External means to gain a good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion.</head>
                  <p>IF in the <hi>flowry</hi> enamell of Natures <hi>gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> there be any <hi>ſenſitive plant</hi> tis beauty: for though it may <hi>thrive</hi> and <hi>flouriſh</hi> perhaps in the face that <hi>Elyſium</hi> of delights, during the youthfull <hi>May</hi> of warmer yeares, yet even then muſt it be cheriſh'd with a tender care: for ſo ſenſible is it of the ſofteſt touch, that if the <hi>Sun</hi> (intending to borrow ſome of its luſtre to increaſe his owne) do but gently ſalute it with its ſubtle &amp; limber rayes, it preſently ſhrouds it ſelfe in a mantle of Jet, as if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting his mildeſt embraces; as a rude in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity, it were reſolv'd to benight the face in a gloomy coverture, in ſpight of his world of glory. So againe if ſullen <hi>Aeolus</hi> come ſo nere to blow upon it with his chilly breath, it preſently contracts its expanded roſes, as if it had rather degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate into a deformed nature, then expoſe it ſelf to the ſaucie blaſts of that bluſtring courtier. We can't then be too carefull of a flower which is ſo nice and tender, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51143:24"/>can any with diſcretion blame thoſe Ladies that through an innocent care of enamouring looks, uſe ſome artificiall wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to preſerve and cheriſh thoſe features, which are of themſelves too apt to fade and wither. I muſt here yet give them this caution, to avoid thoſe things which ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adulterate then adorne the skin, ſuch as <hi>Spaniſh white</hi> and <hi>Mercury:</hi> the leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences they muſt ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ect from ſuch drugs (except prepared by a very skilfull Artiſt) are a wrinkle-furrowed viſage, ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king breath, looſe &amp; rotten teeth. So that it will be more ſafe and better to uſe <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coctions, Pomatums, ointments</hi> and ſuch like applications as you find deſcribed here, which are not in the leaſt dangerous and doe exceedingly adorne the beautie.</p>
                  <p>As for the uſe of them, before they are applyed, the part muſt be waſhed with warme water, and after with water and ſope, or ſome other deterſive liquor, which may prepare and fit it for the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the enſuing medicaments. Such pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative liquors may be, diſtilled waters of mallows, elder, beanes, water lillies; cows milke diſtilled; infuſion of white bread, decoction of French barly, or any thing of the like nature, whereof you may have
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51143:25"/>your choice in this Chapter. When the part is cleanſed, apply ſome of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Coſmeticks, let them lye on all night, and in the morning waſh with bran and water, or elſe with Violet water. The moſt approved Compoſitions for the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying of the Body, are theſe:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the Roots of Dragonwort, Arum (or Cuckoe-pintle) Briony, of each one <hi>ounce:</hi> ſweet almonds peel'd, half a <hi>pound:</hi> bean bran half an <hi>ounce:</hi> Camphire, ſal gem. ſal ammoniac. borace, rock allum, all poudred of each two <hi>drams,</hi> incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them together with the whites of eggs, and form thereof little balls, which diſſolve in cold water, waſh your face therewith going to bed, let it lye on till the morning, and then waſh it off with this water following:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> a pottle Pot well glaz'd, fill it half full with the roots of white or marſh mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows waſhed and ſlic'd, adde thereto a <hi>pint</hi> of white wine, a <hi>dozen</hi> egg ſhells clean waſht and poudred, afterwards pour in ſo much river or ſpring water as will fill up the Pot, boyl all theſe together to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of a <hi>third part,</hi> and then adde the crum of a penny white loaf, and as much as a bean of verdigreeſe, pounded and tyed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51143:25"/>up in a little bag, ſtrain the decoction in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a baſin, and adde to half thereof an <hi>ounce</hi> of finely poudred ſugar, moiſten a fine white ragg in this water, and waſh the face therewith, without wiping after it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> two white pigeons, pull them, and caſt away the guts, head, wings and leggs, then mince them into ſmall pieces, then put them into a glaſs alembick, ſtrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bottom with ſome plantane leaves; adde thereto oyle of ſweet almonds three <hi>ounces,</hi> butter four <hi>ounces,</hi> a <hi>pint</hi> of Goats milk, the crum of a white loafe, borace and ſugar candy of each two <hi>drams,</hi> burnt allum and poudred camphire of each three <hi>draws,</hi> the whites of 24 eggs, let all theſe infuſe for the ſpace of twelve hours, then carfully ſtop the alembick, and diſtil them in <hi>Balneo Mariae;</hi> put the diſtilled water into glaſs viols to ſettle in a cool celler, ſtrein it through a fine cloth, and waſh your face there with morning and evening: it makes the face, or any other part, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding comely: and is that pigeon wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which hath been ſo much pris'd by the Court Dames at <hi>Paris.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> allum, ſal gem, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> borace and camphire half an <hi>ounce,</hi> oyle of Tartar four <hi>ounces;</hi> beat and work
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51143:26"/>them together, then adde a pint of briony water, diſtill them altogether in B.M. the water you draw from them will be of marvellous vertue to beautifie any part, and make it of a ruddy complexion. Of the ſame effect is that which follows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> madder, frankincenſe, myrrhe, oriental ſaffron, maſtick, of each like quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities, bruiſe them all, and ſteep them in white wine, anoint the face therewith go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to bed, in the morning waſh either with cold or warm water, it will purple any part with a gallant and pleaſing bluſh. Or, take fraxinella roots, chew them, and tye them in a fine ragg, and bath the face.</p>
                  <p>This following is much commended for making the face white and clear as ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaſter; <hi>Take</hi> myrrhe two <hi>ounces,</hi> fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincenſe half an <hi>ounce,</hi> white ginger three <hi>drams,</hi> cinnamon and ſublimate of each two <hi>drams,</hi> camphire one <hi>dram,</hi> whites of three or four eggs, put all theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the belly of a young pullet or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon well waſh'd, and cleanſed; add there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Goats or Aſſes milk, diſtil all together, and you ſhall have ſuch a water that few things can equal it. If you fear it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſublimate, after you have
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:51143:26"/>uſed it two or three times, you may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continue it, and uſe this following:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the white of an egg, beat it toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with roſe water, anoint the face there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and when it hath ſometime been dried on waſh with roſe water. Or often bath the face with roſe water camphora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. It is exceeding good to prevent thoſe inconveniencies which may happen from the uſe of ſuch things as too much dry and parch the face.</p>
                  <p>Slice <hi>four</hi> oranges and as many lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, take white ſugar and rock allum of each one <hi>ounce;</hi> infuſe them three or four hours in a <hi>quart</hi> of milk, then diſtil them in B. M. and wet ſome fine cloth in the water to lay over the face when you go to bed. Or, take Goats milk one <hi>quart,</hi> juyce of citrons one <hi>pint,</hi> white wine vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar half a <hi>pint,</hi> the flowers of beans, water lillies, fumitory, of each three <hi>hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls,</hi> the whites of half a <hi>dozen</hi> eggs, cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire two <hi>drams,</hi> diſtil and uſe them as the other.</p>
                  <p>Oyle of myrrhe is ſingular good to preſerve the beauty, if when you go to bed you waſh your face with the diſtilled water of bean flowers, and afterwards anoint it with that oyle: It is thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51143:27"/>
                     <hi>Take</hi> new laid eggs and boyl them hard, ſlit them and take out the yolks, then fill them up with poudred myrrhe, cloſe them together, lay them in a moiſt cool place, and the myrrhe will diſſolve into a water, which is the oyle. After the ſame manner you may prepare oyle of Tartar, if you calcine and put it into the eggs, it is an exceeding good Coſmetick.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Unguentum Citrinum three <hi>ounces,</hi> ſperma coeti an <hi>ounce and a half,</hi> ſalt of Ceruſe <hi>half an ounce,</hi> oyle of eggs as much, maſh them together and make a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niment. To make ſalt of Ceruſe, you muſt pouder the ceruſe very fine, and mix it with ſome diſtilled vinegar, ſo that to one <hi>ounce</hi> of ceruſe there may be four <hi>ounces</hi> of vinegar; let it infuſe three or four dayes, then draw it off by filtration, and and ſet that which is drawn off over the fire, in an earthen pot well glaz'd and dried till it become a ſalt, as they make their cauteries.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> prepared ſnails, <hi>that is,</hi> drawn out of their ſhels and waſht ſo long in ſalt and water till they looſe their ſlime, then pound them and lay one bed of them in the bottom of an Alembicke, and on them make an other bed of ſal gem, allum, fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincenſe,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:51143:27"/>borace, camphire of each pounded two <hi>drams,</hi> then poure on ſo much juice of limmons as may cover them two fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, ſo let them macerate 5 or 6 hours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and then diſtill them in <hi>Bal. Maris.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> twelve limons, as many hen egs, halfe a <hi>pound</hi> of turpentine well waſht, put the turpentine in the bottome of the alembick, boile the egs hard and diſtill all in <hi>B. M.</hi> this water is excellent to whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the skin and change the complexion, if you waſh wiſh ſpring watar and dry the face, and after waſh with this without wiping.</p>
                  <p>This bath is very good, <hi>Take</hi> two <hi>hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulls</hi> of ſage leaves, the like quantity of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender flowers and roſes, a little ſalt, boile them in ſpring water and therewith bath your body; remembring that you are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to bath after meals for it will occaſion many infirmities; bath therefore two or three hours before dinner, it will cleare the skin, revives the ſpirits and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens the body, the ſame effects hath this following.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> roſe water, vineger, ſalt, boile all together in faire water, take thereof a pint, mix ſome bran with it, and waſh the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51143:28"/>body all over with it, let it dry on, then waſh it off, nothing can be better to mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difie the body.</p>
                  <p>Some Ladies delight much in ſweet baths, therefore into half a <hi>pint</hi> of water they put 5 or 6 <hi>drops</hi> of oile of ſpicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard; ſome beſide this adde musk, amber, civet, lignum aloes, benjamin, ſtorax, myrrh, cloves, roſes, limmon and orange flowers, roſemary, lavender, mint, penny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>royall. But your chymicall extracts far excell all theſe, if you mix but halfe a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen <hi>drops</hi> with your bath; ſuch are the oile of oranges, cloves, mace, nutmegs and the like.</p>
                  <p>When your bath is provided remember if you priſe your health or beauty, that it be not too hot; for then it ſcorcheth the skin and makes it rough; and cauſes very many untoward infirmities. Thus much for the <hi>meanes</hi> to <hi>gaine</hi> a <hi>good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion,</hi> I come in the next place to give ſome ſpeciall remedies, how to correct the more particular vices of an ill complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: as a <hi>pale</hi> and <hi>ſwarthy colour,</hi> a <hi>rough, harſh, groſſe</hi> or <hi>ſluttiſh</hi> skin, <hi>ſweat, ſpots, itch, ſcab, leproſie, ſcurf</hi> and the like.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:51143:28"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> How to beautifie a white and pallid complexion.</head>
                  <p>Such colours when they annoy the complexion principally proceed from ill humours, which abound in the body &amp; are expelled forth to the externall ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the skin; wherefore thoſe that deſire to correct any vitious colour that offends their bodies, muſt in the firſt place by ſome <hi>purgation</hi> evacuate that humour, whereto their diſtemper ows its originall. Now the paleneſſe of the complexion in women is principally occaſioned by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of the ſpleen and liver, which cauſe in them a ſuppreſſion of their month<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purgations, which cauſe being by an orderly courſe of phyſick removed, the body muſt be repleniſht by a good and commendable <hi>dyet.</hi> If this doe not recover their decaying beauty they may proceed to <hi>externall applications;</hi> and to make their cheeks and lips ruddie and lively, with good ſucceſs uſe theſe things fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
                  <p>Diſſolve the ſhavings of Braſil and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kanet, in allum water, wherewith (after
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:51143:29"/>you have ſufficiently cleanſed the face with water of lillies or bean flowers) bath the cheeks and lips, letting it dry on. Or elſe bath the cheeks, lips or any other part that is too pale and white with allum water wherein a pciee of red turnſoile hath been often ſteeped, or rub thoſe parts with a peece of ſhipskin coloured red. To chafe the parts often with the hand or a courſe cloth makes them look red and lively; for ſuch frictions draw the blood and ſpirits outward. Or in caſe of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty uſe Pomatum and Vermilion made of cinnaberis. Or, <hi>Take</hi> red Saunders bruiſe and ſteep it for 3 dayes in <hi>Aqua Vitae,</hi> then boile it for an hour over a gentle ſire ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a little allum and gum arabick, than ſtrein it and bath the parts therewith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> rock allum <hi>unc.</hi> 1. boile it in a <hi>pinte</hi> of running water, when it is diſſolved take it off from the fire, let it cool, then adde to it Vermilion finely powdred <hi>one ounce,</hi> boile them againe to a conſumption of half, ſtreine the decoction and keep it for your uſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Braſil one <hi>ounce,</hi> Cloves <hi>halfe a ſcore,</hi> grains of Paradiſe two <hi>ſcruples,</hi> boile them with a <hi>pint</hi> of rectified <hi>Aqua vitae</hi>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:51143:29"/>in a covered veſſel; uſe it when it is cold.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> To ſmooth a rough and uneven Skin.</head>
                  <p>THe skin is the bodies native <hi>ſhirt;</hi> which if it be of a courſer <hi>thread,</hi> it is ſome of Natures <hi>homeſpun houſwifry,</hi> careleſly hudled up when ſhe was in haſt to finiſh a <hi>finer peece.</hi> To <hi>ſmooth</hi> ſuch rug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, <hi>canvas</hi> and bring it to a pleaſing <hi>even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> that may vie with the poliſht Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaſter, art here preſents an inventory of of its beſt directions: ſo often prov'd that I preſume any <hi>courſe skin'd Ladie</hi> who will be ſo much her own friend to uſe them, may ſoon be freed from doing pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in natures <hi>ſackcloth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> peeld Almonds ſix <hi>pound,</hi> maſtick, prepard ceruſe and gum dragant of each four <hi>ounces,</hi> the whites of 4 eggs, pound all together very carefully, let it ſtand 5 or 6 days pounding it every day once, then put them in a preſſe and keep the oile that comes forth to anoint the skin withall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> hempſeed, pound it ſmall, moiſten
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:51143:30"/>it with a little <hi>aqua vitae</hi> then heat it in a frying pan made very clean, ſo hot that you cant endure to touch, afterward put it into a bag and preſſe it, the oile that comes from it is exceeding good for the roughneſſe of the skin.</p>
                  <p>Anoint any part that is too rough with oile of rape ſeed or bitter almonds, or oile of wheat. Or <hi>take</hi> ſweet almonds cleanſed and peeled foure <hi>pound,</hi> moiſten them with the ſpirit of wine &amp; roſe water mixt together of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> beat them together and fry them, when they begin to ſmoke put them in a bag, ſo preſſe them and there will come forth an oile very cleare, which you muſt put into a pot of raine water and beat it together til it become exceeding white: then keep it as a rare ſecret to ſmooth and polliſh the skin.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> How to cleans the ſweatie and ſluttiſh Complexion.</head>
                  <p>THE microcoſme through the ſordid ſluttiſhneſſe of ſome, is often <hi>drownd</hi>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:51143:30"/>in a naſtie <hi>deluge</hi> of ſweat; out a deſigne perhaps to take <hi>Cupid</hi> captive and <hi>bird<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime</hi> his wings with ſuch <hi>clammie</hi> excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: but if they have no other tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bait, then the greaſie <hi>pomatum</hi> which their own ill ſtuff'd bodies ſupply them with, I am afraid (though being blind he cannot ſee them) he'l ſmell them a mile off and ſo keep his diſtance. They would doe much better to break off this petty plot upon <hi>Cupid,</hi> and ſcour their bodies well with theſe abſterſives.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> bryony roots half a <hi>handfull,</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentary the leſſe, (or friars Coule,) pelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of the wall, elecampane, of each three <hi>ounces,</hi> whole beanes, rice, white vetches, French barly of each two <hi>ounces</hi> and <hi>a half,</hi> flowers of camomile, melilot of each one <hi>handfull.</hi> Boile all theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in raine water &amp; receive the fume up in the face. If you would have it for your whole body, double the quantities, boile them, powre them forth into a bath, ſet a ſtoole in the bath, caſt a ſheet over you and ſo receive the vapoure.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum Citrinum</hi> is of great effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to help this diſtemper if you adde thereto a little ſublimate carefully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, or a little white hellebore finely
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:51143:31"/>powdred. The fumes of the deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the ſhavings of Guajacum is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> bean meale, white vetches, ſweet almonds blanched, gum dragant, bryony roots of each half an <hi>ounce,</hi> pound them a part, then mix them and incorporate them with whites of egs; make them up into little balls. When you have occaſion to uſe them diſſolve them in barly water, and bath the skin therewith, going to bed, next day waſh with water wherein the fineſt flower hath been ſteept.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the roots of ſerpentary ſliced, dry them in the ſun, powder and ſift them, next incorporate them with roſe water into a paſt, dry them againe in the ſun and powder them, then adde a third part of ceruſe prepared ſo as is directed in the 2. <hi>part. c.</hi> 1. then worke all together with roſe water, dry them in the ſun, and at laſt bring it with beating it in a morter to a very fine powder. When you would uſe it, mix it with the juice of lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and ſo make it into a liniment for a ſweatie part.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> barly half ripe two <hi>pound,</hi> goats milke three <hi>pints,</hi> the whites of a dozen eggs, mix and diſtil them in <hi>balneo maris,</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:51143:31"/>then uſe it. Or take ſifted bran, the beſt leaven two <hi>pound,</hi> as much vinegar as ſhall be requiſite, the whites of <hi>eight</hi> eggs, mingle them, and make it into a paſte, then diſtil it in B. M.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take thirty</hi> Snails prepared, a <hi>quart</hi> of Goats milk, hogs ſuet three <hi>ounces,</hi> cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre poudred two drams, beat them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and diſtil them in an Alembick.</p>
                  <p>The ſluttiſhneſs and ſweat of the skin, may proceed either from an external cauſe, as negligence to wipe and cleanſe the face from that filth and ordure which may be ingendred by the aire, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accident; and then there needs no more to beautifie it, than a conſtant waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and rubbing it: Or, from an internal, as fuliginous vapours d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ain'd betwixt the <hi>Cutis</hi> and <hi>Epidermis,</hi> by reaſon of its den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity. This is the more frequent cauſe, and for the more general cure of it, the body muſt throughly be purged of thoſe humors which produce ſuch excrements; and for topical applications, you are to uſe ſuch things as are ſet down in this Chapter. Or you may ſcour and cleanſe the body with water wherein fine wheat flower, or the crum of white bread hath been infus'd, adding to it a ſmall quantity
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:51143:32"/>of the juyce of limmons. Or with the decoction of mallow roots, or lillies. As alſo with the infuſion of the roots of briony, with the juyce of the roots of ſowbread, or wild cucumers incorporated with bean meal, with the oyle of ſulphur or tartar, mixt either with clear fountain water, or elſe with any of the former decoctions. Thus far concerning the <hi>naſty ſweat of the skin;</hi> the next inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience that damages the beauty, and which we intend to give remedies how to correct, are <hi>itch</hi> and <hi>ſcabs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> How to repair the beauty of an itchy or ſcabby skin.</head>
                  <p>I Am afraid, Ladies, that whilſt I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe remedies for ſo loathſome a skin-defiling malady, you will think I have forgot ye, and am now addreſſing my ſelf to your kitchin maids: I muſt confeſſe theſe fretting exulcerations are more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently incident to ſuch as are forced to content themſelves with courſer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; as amongſt the fleecy troops, thoſe are ſooneſt ſcabby that feed in unwhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:51143:32"/>paſture. Yet the higheſt and beſt fed, are not alwaies exempted from the infection; nor are the moſt delicate La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, eſpecially if any thing irregular or intemperate, wholly ſecured, that they ſhall be no fuller of ill humors than their skins can hold. If ever then your ill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed humors grow ſo ſtrong, to break their way through the incloſing skin, it will do you no harm to have ſomething in readineſs that may check their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Fumitory water an <hi>ounce and a half,</hi> ſuccory water three <hi>ounces,</hi> ſyrup of fumitory and ſuccory of each one <hi>ounce;</hi> mix altogether, and take it for your mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings draught, uſe it for five dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: then uſe this excellent medicine;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Sena two <hi>drams,</hi> rhubarb one <hi>ſcruple,</hi> annis ſeeds half a <hi>ſcruple;</hi> white wine <hi>half a pint;</hi> put all into an earthen bottle, ſtopit cloſe, and ſet it over warm embers all night, in the morning ſtrain it out and drink it: if the ſtomack be weak, and love not Potions, you may uſe theſe following Pills:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Citrine mirabolans, rubarb, of each half a <hi>dram,</hi> aloes waſht in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of ſena one <hi>ſcruple,</hi> make them up
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:51143:33"/>into Pills with ſyrup of Fumitory; then anoint your ſelf going to bed with this oyntment. <hi>Take</hi> Brimſtone an <hi>ounce and a half,</hi> ſalt and ſallad oyle one <hi>ounce,</hi> grind the ſalt and ſulphur exceeding ſmall; mix them with the oyle, and when you go to bed uſe it for three or four nights; only chafing it very well into the palms of the hands, then draw on a pair of gloves; and keep them on all night; it will cure all <hi>itch</hi> and <hi>ſcabs</hi> throughout the body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> as much mans urine as will ſerve to bath the diſeaſed up to the knees; add thereto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> charecoal of oak poudered and black hellebore, but more hellebore than coal: bath therewith the leggs for fifteen mornings together, and longer if need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite. This hath its effect on every member of the body, ſo that whether it be Totter, Leproſie, Itch, or running Scab, in ſhort time it is cured with this medicine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mercur.</hi> and other experienced Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, commend the ſucceſs that theſe ointments have, if they are applied to the pulſe: <hi>Take</hi> oleum laurinum ſix <hi>drams,</hi> quickſilver one <hi>dram and a half,</hi> borace three <hi>drams,</hi> ceruſe one <hi>dram,</hi> cummin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds one <hi>ſcruple;</hi> make them into an
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:51143:33"/>ointment. Or, <hi>Take equal parts</hi> of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race and aloes, a <hi>third part</hi> of prepared quickſilver, as much oyle of Lawrel, make them into an Unguent; and with either of theſe anoint the pulſes going to bed: after you have bathed your arms for ſome while in warm water. I find theſe much extol'd, but I would not have you uſe them before you have try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſomething elſe becauſe of the quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver.</p>
                  <p>Before you practice with any medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, remember to purge the body of that humor which is the cauſe of your diſtemper. I ſhall here only add two or three odoriſerous waters which cure all ſuch infirmities, and make the skin ſmooth and delicate. <hi>Take</hi> Bawm, what quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty you pleaſe, beat it well, then ſet it to macerate one night in white wine, the next morning draw off the water in a glaſs ſtill. It is exceeding ſweet, and in a ſhort time cures all ſcabs throughout the body, if you add a grain of musk and bath it therewith: mixt with natural balſame, and anointed on the face, 'twill make it of a lively roſe colour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> dried Sage eight <hi>ounces,</hi> nutmegs five <hi>ounces,</hi> ginger, cloves, cinnamon,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:51143:34"/>grains of paradice, of each four <hi>ounces;</hi> bruiſe them, and then ſet them to digeſt for twenty four hours in good white wine, afterward diſtil them according to art in an Alembick: The water drawn from thence is ſo excellent, that if you drink it in a ſmall quantity for three dayes faſting, it cures all Tetters and Scabs, breeds good blood, and cauſes a lovely complexion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Turpentine a quarter of a <hi>pound,</hi> honey two <hi>ounces, aquae vitae</hi> three <hi>ounces,</hi> wood of aloes beaten ſmall, ſweet ſaunders, of each three <hi>drams,</hi> gum ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick one <hi>dram,</hi> nutmegs two <hi>drams,</hi> ambergreece one <hi>dram,</hi> powder all ſmall, and diſtil them with a gentle fire; and in your operation you ſhall draw <hi>three</hi> ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſorts of liquors: the <hi>firſt</hi> is clear, the <hi>ſecond</hi> (when the fire is increaſed) falls in drops like burning coals, the <hi>third</hi> deſcends a little blacker and thicker than honey. The firſt is called <hi>mother of bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame;</hi> the ſecond <hi>oyle of balſame;</hi> and the third <hi>artiſicial balſame:</hi> If you anoint your ſelf with the <hi>firſt</hi> of theſe, it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding good for ſpreading Scabs, or itch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tetters; kept in the mouth, it ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens the breath, faſtens, preſerves, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:51143:34"/>whitens the teeth; anointing the face therewith, it makes it ſmooth and ruddy. The <hi>ſecond</hi> and <hi>third</hi> liquors recover complexion loſt, are good for any bruiſe, cure all diſtempers ariſing from the blood, or phlegme corrupted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> To adorne the ſcurffie and mealy Complexion.</head>
                  <p>That Complexion is ſaid to be <hi>mealy</hi> and <hi>ſcurffie,</hi> which appears full of little white ſcales that fall off like ſmall bran, when the face or other part is rub'd with a woollen cloth. The thin and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger conſtitution is moſt frequently troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with this diſtemper; and it proceeds from thick and groſſe humors detain'd betwixt the cuticle and the under skin, which corrupt after ſome continuance, and then corrode that ſlender covering into a ſcaly duſt.</p>
                  <p>To embelliſh ſuch a complexion, the chiefeſt care muſt be to diſlodge thoſe humors that lye betwixt the <hi>Epidermis</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:51143:35"/>and the groſſer skin; for which intent you may uſe urine, or white wine wherein ſliced limmons have been boiled; a lixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vium made with the aſhes of beets and coleworts, wherein boile lupins and beans, and in the ſtreined liquor diſſolve a <hi>ſpoonful</hi> or <hi>two</hi> of honey or gall, or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the like nature to bath the face withal.</p>
                  <p>If the face be very lean, inſtead of the foregoing Fomentation, you may uſe this that is not ſo drying. <hi>Take</hi> the leaves of bugloſſe, borage, pellitory, mallows, fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitory, violets, cichory, endive, lettice, poppy, fengreek, cleans'd barly, boyle them together in water, adding a <hi>little</hi> bran bound up in a bag; after the face hath been bathed, waſh it with this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> bitter almonds, the meal of beans and vetches, of each one <hi>ounce;</hi> allum, borace, maſtick, olibanum, gum tragant, of each half an <hi>ounce;</hi> juyce of limmons ſeven <hi>ounces;</hi> water of plantane, roſes and white lillies, of each three <hi>ounces;</hi> new Goats milk four <hi>ounces;</hi> mix all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and diſtil them with a gentle fire.</p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:51143:35"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take Mel roſatum,</hi> roſe water, juyce of limmons, of each two <hi>ounces;</hi> gum tragagant, maſtick, ceruſe prepar'd, ſtarch, olibanum, of each three <hi>drams,</hi> allum, white corral, cuttle bone, borace, of each two <hi>drams;</hi> ſal gem, a <hi>dram and a half;</hi> bean meal one <hi>ounce;</hi> the whites of <hi>three</hi> eggs, ſnails beaten with their ſhells, ſix <hi>ounces;</hi> camphire half a <hi>dram;</hi> cinnamon <hi>half an ounce;</hi> mix them, and diſtil them in <hi>Balneo Maris,</hi> then apply the water to the face.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take Enula campan,</hi> burdock roots, of each two <hi>ounces;</hi> boile them in ſtrong vinegar, pound them and paſſe them through a ſtreiner; add ſolphur vive two <hi>drams,</hi> ſalt calcined a <hi>dram and a half,</hi> juyce of limmons two <hi>ounces;</hi> dip a cloth in this compoſition, and ſo bath the skin with it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the water that is found in cavities of oaks, waſh the skin therewith: Or, <hi>Take</hi> the juyce that is newly preſt from agrimony incorporated with ſalt and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar; or the juyce of burdock mixt with ſulphur vive. The Decoction of ſcabious drank for ſome mornings toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, cures the skin of this infirmity. Or, <hi>Take</hi> the roots of ſcrofulary out of the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:51143:36"/>ground in <hi>Autumne,</hi> beat them together with freſh butter, put it into an earthen pot cloſe ſtopt, ſet it in a moiſt place twelve or fifteen dayes, the butter will ſoon diſſolve, ſtrein it, and keep it to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> How to poliſh the Skin when it is disfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured with Scars, or marks of the Small Pox.</head>
                  <p>VArious are the ſuppriſing caſualties that deform a poliſht Skin; each wound is a <hi>grave</hi> where Loves dumb ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>lyes inſhrin'd;</hi> and Chirurgeons uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the unskilful <hi>Plaiſterers,</hi> that make an ill-rais'd cicatrice the ſwelling monument to departed beauty. The feature fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Pox, if it ſets but a <hi>foot</hi> within that paradice of perfections the face; it leaves more disfiguring impreſſions there, than a <hi>Coridons clouted ſhoes</hi> on a <hi>Cedar floor.</hi> Now to ſmooth, Ladies, and poliſh your skins after ſuch diſaſters, priſe the medicines commended to you in this <hi>Chapter</hi> as ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:51143:36"/>they'le make the hills and dales of uneven faces meet without a miracle, levelling them to ſuch a ſmoothneſs, that little <hi>Cupid,</hi> though blind, may ſport him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf there and never ſtumble.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> maſtick two <hi>ounces,</hi> gum arabick one <hi>ounce,</hi> ſaffron <hi>half an ounce,</hi> turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine three <hi>ounces,</hi> old ſallad oyle two <hi>ounces;</hi> make the maſtick and gum ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick into a groſſe pouder, then put them into the oyles and turpentine, diſtil all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a glaſſe Alembick, and anoint the face with the water going to bed; in the morning waſh with warm water, wherein the fineſt flower hath been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed. It is exceeding good for any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figuring ſcarr that appears after the conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidation of a wound. Of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is the next that follows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> oyle of Tartar, and the mucilage of Pſyllium ſeeds extracted with roſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, of each one <hi>ounce;</hi> ceruſe diſſolved in oyle of roſes <hi>as much,</hi> borace and ſal gem. of each one <hi>dram;</hi> incorporate them well together and make an oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Or, <hi>Take</hi> Tartar well burnt, boile eggs hard, take out the yolks after you have ſlit them, and fill up the cavities with the burnt tartar; put them in a moiſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:51143:37"/>place, and keep the water that comes from thence as excellent for ſcars.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> litharge of gold two <hi>ounces,</hi> ceruſe and ſalt, of each <hi>half an ounce;</hi> vinegar, roſe and plantane water, of each three <hi>ounces;</hi> camphire <hi>half a dram;</hi> mingle and filtre it, ſo keep it for uſe. Or, <hi>Take</hi> wild cucumer roots finely powdred one <hi>ounce,</hi> allum two <hi>drams,</hi> ſulphur vive, nitre, of each one <hi>dram;</hi> incorporate all together with lard well waſht, uſe it as an ointment. Theſe two are of the ſame vertue with the former.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> oyle of Lillies, capons greaſe, oyle of roſes, of each one <hi>ounce and a half;</hi> waſh theſe well in roſe and lilly wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; then add to them the whites of <hi>four</hi> or <hi>five</hi> eggs half boiled in their ſhells, oyl of ſweet and bitter almonds, of each one <hi>ounce;</hi> incorporate them together in a marble mortar, and in the working put in the mucilage of melon ſeeds, litharge of gold and chalk poudred, of each two <hi>drams;</hi> make them into an Unguent: applied to the face, it takes away all thoſe ſcars the Small Pox too frequently makes there. Hares blood, if you bath the skin often with it warm, fills the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities with fleſh, and makes the skin even
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:51143:37"/>and plain. It is likewiſe an approved ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment, That the water which comes from Sheep or Goats hoofs burnt, is very good for the ſame. Or, uſe this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Litharge of gold waſht nine times in roſe water, and ſifted as often, two <hi>drams;</hi> reed roots dried and pounded, rice meal, powder of burnt bones, bean meal, of each one <hi>dram;</hi> beat all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther very ſmall, then ſift it through fine tiffiny; incorporate it with the mucilage of flax ſeed, fengreek and pſyllium ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted in lilly water, and ſo bring it into the form of an Unguent. Apply it to the face going to bed, on the morrow waſh with barly water.</p>
                  <p>Bath the places with warm water, then ſtrew thereon the cinders of burnt Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, either alone or with myrrhe. Or, bath the places with water wherein cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon hath a long time boiled, then put thereon the powder of litharge, it will in ſhort time take away all marks of the Small Pox.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> wheaten ſtarch, blancht almonds, of each two <hi>drams;</hi> ſweet coſtus, gum tragacanth, of each <hi>half a dram;</hi> reed roots <hi>half an ounce;</hi> barly meal, whole
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:51143:38"/>melon ſeeds, beans dryed and pounded three <hi>drams,</hi> ſaffron one <hi>ſcruple,</hi> powder and ſift the whole, mingle them with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual parts of roſe water and juice of orange peel, make a liniment, and with a feather anoint the ſcars of the pox, leave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſo all night; on the morrow waſh with the decoction of camomile and mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilot.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> How to remove ſpots in what part of the body ſoever.</head>
                  <p>I Have ſeen faces from whoſe features, beauty her ſelf might have taken co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, had not nature ſtudying too much neatneſſe plaid the <hi>curtezan,</hi> and ſpoiled that which was handſome before by two much <hi>patching.</hi> Yet moſt Ladies never think themſelves <hi>Venus</hi>'s for beauty, except they have ſome artificiall <hi>mole:</hi> though ſuch <hi>ſtellae nebuloſae</hi> ecclipſe more then increaſe the native luſtre; and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where nature is too free in her ſpots they are alway reputed blemiſhes not ornaments. Thoſe then that have
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:51143:38"/>beauties characters defac'd with ſuch blots, if they have recourſe to theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing directions, ſhall find themſelves quickly freed, and their features ſo raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that were it the mode of this age to dedicate <hi>ſhrines</hi> to beauty, there is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of them but would have their <hi>Altar,</hi> where the moſt generous heart ſhould glory to be a <hi>ſacrifice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To take away any ſpot whatever.</head>
                     <p>Bath them for three mornings together with allum diſſolved in oile of Tartar, waſh after with lye and lupine meale. Or <hi>take</hi> two parts of plantaine water and one of roſewater, <hi>ſulphur vive</hi> powdred two <hi>ounces,</hi> rock allum beaten ſmall one <hi>ounce,</hi> boile them over the fire till a fifth part be conſumed, then take it off and ſtir it well till it be cool, afterward ſtrein it through a fine cloth and keep it for uſe. It takes away all kind of ſpots.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take</hi> ſugar candie, white frankincence of each two <hi>ounces,</hi> diſſolve them in juice of limmons halfe a <hi>pinte,</hi> boile them gently in a little skillet, then anoint the ſpots with it, after they have been waſhed with barly water.</p>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:51143:39"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take</hi> lye made of Vine aſhes, juice of coleworts, ox-gall of each a <hi>pound</hi> and a <hi>halfe,</hi> diſſolve therein half an ounce of allum and three whole egs beaten, wet a cloth in this compoſition and bath the ſpots therewith.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take</hi> turpentine and maſticke, tutia prepared, of each two <hi>ounces,</hi> camphire halfe an <hi>ounce,</hi> ſteep them three daies in ſtrong vinegar, diſtill them in an alem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick, and keep the water for uſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To cleer the skin of black ſpots.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take</hi> the diſtilled waters of dock and melon roots of each one <hi>quart,</hi> ten ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low eggs, ſalt nitre half an <hi>ounce,</hi> white Tartar two <hi>ounces,</hi> pound the nitre and tartar then mix them altogether, let them ſtand 24 hours, then diſtill them in an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lembick in B. M. waſh the black ſpots with the water in the morning, at night waſh them with oile of tartar and ſweet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds mixt together.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take</hi> maſtick powdred, ſulphur vive of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> bay berries as many; ſteep them in warme water for the ſpace of ten days ſtirring them carefully once
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:51143:39"/>or twice a day: then waſh the black pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with that water.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take</hi> roots of iris Florent. wild cucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, briony of each two <hi>pound,</hi> dittany four <hi>ounces,</hi> flowers of beanes, pellitory of the wall of each one <hi>handfull,</hi> flowers of water lillie two <hi>handfuls,</hi> ſteep them in white wine then mix them with goats milke; after diſtill them in an alembick, and keep the water to waſh the ſpots.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>For white ſpots.</head>
                     <p>Theſe proceed commonly from a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitous humour abounding in the body and are thus remedied. Take barly, lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines, red Vetches, the roots of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and leſſe dragon wort of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> pound them and incorporate them with the whites of eggs, make them up in little bals and dry them in the ſun: when you have occaſion to uſe them diſſolve one or two in roſewater, and ſo anoint the ſpots going to bed, in the morning waſh with the infuſion of the crum of white bread.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take</hi> the aſhes of aſphodill roots mix them with vineger and apply them. Or ſteep the rind of Caper roots in ſtrong
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:51143:40"/>vineger. Or verdegreece finely powdred &amp; macerated a day and a night in juice of limmons, wet a linnen cloth therein, and bath the ſpots.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>For green ſpots.</head>
                     <p>Powder the dryed roots of dragon wort, to two <hi>ounces</hi> of this powder adde ceruſe half an <hi>ounce,</hi> and as much cuttle bone powdred, worke them together with roſe water and make them into little bals, dry them and keep them for your uſe: when you have occaſion diſſolve a couple in a quantity of roſe water and therewith anoint the skin.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take</hi> the juice of chelandine &amp; ſtrong vineger make it into an ointment and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it. Or take brimſtone, myrrhe, fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincence, camphre of each two <hi>drams,</hi> ſteep them in roſe water the ſpace of 8 daies, ſtirring it once a day then let it ſettle and uſe it to waſh the face.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>For red tawny ſpots.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take</hi> Venetian ceruſe one <hi>ounce, lapis calaminaris,</hi> litharge of each two <hi>drams,</hi> prepared tutia, <hi>ſpodium</hi> of each one <hi>dram,</hi>
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:51143:40"/>powder them very ſmall, then adde the water of plantaine, houſleek, red roſes of each two <hi>drams,</hi> mingle them and keep it for your uſe.</p>
                     <p>In the morning faſting chew in the mouth a bit of maſtick as ſoon as you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it to diſſolve anoint the ſpots there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. Or powder pigeons dung, flax ſeed, French barly, ſoake them in ſtrong vinegar and anoint the ſpots.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> To reduce the body that is too fat to a meane and handſome proportion.</head>
                  <p>IT can be no pleaſing ſight, to ſee a ſoul preſt under a mountaine of fleſh, and the body ſtretcht to ſuch dimenſions that make it repreſent a walking barrell. Were there nothing more then this, 'twere ſufficient to deterre any from ſuch an unwildie magnitude, that it always proves its own accuſer, expoſing in too legible characters, <hi>Sloth,</hi> to every one that can but read. For when ere the carcaſe ſwels it ſelf into a bulk too <hi>volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous,</hi> idleneſſe is there deſcrib'd in <hi>folio.</hi>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:51143:41"/>Have a care Ladies then to keep your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in a mean proportion, and if ever they enlarge themſelves to extravagant limits, uſe theſe directions to reduce them to their former bounds, ſo you may regaine your credit and your beautie too.</p>
                  <p>Riſe early in the mornings and uſe ſome violent exerciſe to ſweat often; faſt much, riſe halfe ſatisfied from your meals; let your firſt courſe be oily and fattie things that the appetite may be ſoon ſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, and the body kept ſoluble; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond courſe ſharp, ſalt and bitter things: out all your meats with vineger, pepper, muſtard, juice of oranges and limmons; ſleep at night on a quilt.</p>
                  <p>It is good to bleed largely twice a year, the right arme in the ſpring, the left in the autumne; purge the body in thoſe ſeaſons with ſtrong phyſick, once a week take ſome laxatives, as <hi>pillulae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>uffi, extractum Rudii;</hi> every morning chiefely in winter uſe this powder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the feeds of annis, fennel, <hi>agnus caſtus,</hi> rue, carroway, cummin, pepper, ginger, mace, nutmegs, galingale, ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, dryed marjerom, gentian, round birthwort, of each equall parts,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:51143:41"/>take one <hi>dram</hi> of this powder in a glaſſe of white wine half an hour before meals.</p>
                  <p>Cooling applications may be layd to the heart or liver, as the juice or deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of plantane, ſhepheards purſe, hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaile, lettuce, white henbane, adding the powder of camfre, mirtle or the like.</p>
                  <p>If any one particular part be too cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulent, for the reſt of the body, you may bring it to a correſpondent proportion if you uſe this unguent, <hi>Take</hi> Fullers earth, ceruſe and lead, mix them with the juice of white henbane and the oile of mirtle; anoint the part therewith, having firſt ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed it with vinegar, wherein brimſtone, ſalt nitre, and rock allum have been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd. Some uſe with ligaments to bind thoſe paſſages, whereby the member is ſupplyed with nouriſhment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> To make the body or any part thereof plump and fat, that was before too leane.</head>
                  <p>IN a contrary extreame to corpulency, are thoſe breathing <hi>Skeletons</hi> that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:51143:42"/>Lent in their face at a Chriſtmas <hi>feaſt,</hi> and look ſo meagerly that their Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, ſince they have nothing leaft but <hi>skin</hi> and <hi>bones,</hi> dare not for feare of a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loeciſme injoine them pennance to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the <hi>fleſh.</hi> No part about them thrive ſo well as their bones, and theſe look as luſtie, as if they had eaten up the fleſh, and were readie to leap of the skin to fall upon others. Truly Ladies ſuch lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is a ravenous gueſt, and will keep you bare to maintaine him, if you have a mind to be rid of his company, obſerve theſe preſcriptions following and I dare ingage he ſhall not long diſturb you.</p>
                  <p>Let your chamber in the ſummer time be kept ſomething cool and moiſt with violets, lillies, or the like freſh flowers: before you eat, chafe the body till it look red, then walke and ſtirre about ſome houſwifes imployment. When you eate take nothing that is ſalt or ſharp, bitter or too hot, but let your meats be ſweet and of good nouriſhment, as freſh egs, mutton, veale, capon, and for three hours after meat take your recreation in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, ſinging, diſcourſing &amp;c. uſe ſome baths twice a month, and in the mornings this electuary.</p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:51143:42"/>
                  <p>Sweet almonds, piſtach nuts, white poppy ſeed, butter and ſugar, beat them up into the forme of an electuary: take thereof morning and evening the quantity of a walnut, it quickly fattens and gives a good complexion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> twelve or thirteen Lizards or outs cut off their heads and tailes, boile them and let the water ſtand to cool, take of the greaſe mix it with wheaten flower, feed a Hen therewith till ſhee be fat, then kil her and eat her; this often uſed will make you exceeding ſat, keep it for a rare and true ſecret.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> a young Capon, the fleſh of veal, four calves feet, white wine, faire water of both 3 <hi>quarts:</hi> boile all in an earthen veſſell, ſcumming of all the fat. Then put this broth into a new veſſell with a <hi>pound</hi> and a <hi>halfe</hi> of ſugar, cinnamon half an <hi>ounce,</hi> a <hi>dozen</hi> cloves, boile it gently againe, then adde thereto the whites of <hi>two</hi> egs, reboil it, and paſſe it through a ſtreiner, before it cool, mix a little musk, and amber, diſſolved in roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the flower of rice half a <hi>pound,</hi> diſſolve it in as much milke as is ſufficient,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:51143:43"/>adde thereto the fleſh of a young Capon boild tender, ſweet almonds 24. beat them well in a morter then mix them with the milke and rice, ſtreine all through a courſe cloth, putting thereto what quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of ſugar you pleaſe. Boile all over a ſoft fire till it coagulate into the forme of a gelly: when it begins to cool adde of amber and muske diſſolv'd in roſe water as much as will give it a gratefull odour, often take a ſmall quantity of it.</p>
                  <p>If one part fall away and be are no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the reſt of the body; you may bring it to even terms thus. <hi>Take</hi> oile of Foxes an <hi>ounce</hi> and <hi>a halfe,</hi> oile of lillies, the greace of Capons, and Geeſe of each two <hi>ounces,</hi> greek pitch, pine roſin, and turpentine of each two <hi>ounces,</hi> boile all theſe together in an earthen glazed veſſell, adding <hi>oile</hi> of elder one <hi>ounce,</hi> then take it from the fire and adde new wax, as much as will ſuffice to make it into a ſtiffe cerecloth, when it is almoſt cold ſpread it upon a ſtrong cloth, as much as will wrap up the member, then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it and leave it on all night; if you find any inconvenience in it uſe this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing bath.</p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:51143:43"/>
                  <p>Boile in claret wine halfe a <hi>handfull</hi> of roſes, wormwood, ſtoechas, calamint, ſquinanth, roſemary, ſage, cammomile, of each one <hi>handful;</hi> let a third part of the wine be conſum'd, while it is warme, bath the place where the cerecloth was applyed; this bath doth draw nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the part, and ſtrengthens its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive virtue. Thus much of what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the <hi>beautifying</hi> of the <hi>body in generall.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:51143:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>PART. II.</hi> Of the Head, Necke, and Breasts.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>E that intend, Ladies, to ſubdue hearts, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand with ſoveraignty in the mint-houſe of others Affections, muſt be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to keep in tune the harmony of theſe parts; remembring that they were intended for beauties glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Frontiſpiece, to allure Spectators eyes, and with a <hi>Phoebeau</hi> luſtre, make them its obſequious <hi>Heliotropes.</hi> By what means you are to preſerve their ſplendor, you may be inſtructed in this <hi>Second Part.</hi> Where you ſhall learn how to give the <hi>Face</hi> ſuch a commanding Beauty; that all who view it ſhall yield obedience, and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:51143:44"/>none rebel but thoſe who cannot ſee; how your <hi>Eyes</hi> may be made <hi>Cupids</hi> chryſtal burning glaſſes, to kindle devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in your Captives hearts; and your buſhy <hi>Hair Venus</hi>'s Grove, in whoſe twyning Maeanders a pleaſing impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall breed a diſlike of former Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: In a wotd, how to advance your Features to ſuch a pitch of dazeling glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that ſhall make Beauty it ſelf out of countenance, and put <hi>Cupid</hi> hardly to it, among ſo many fair ones, to know his Mother.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> To cure Redneſs and fiery Pimples in the Face.</head>
                  <p>AN <hi>inundation</hi> of crimſon'd <hi>blood</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>drowns</hi> the flowry <hi>Elyſium</hi> of a charming face; disfigoring it with ſuch a <hi>flaming</hi> hue, as if the juycie god had made it his vineyard, and planted it with <hi>rubie</hi> Grapes. To abate the fury of ſuch high colours, and fright them into a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:51143:45"/>paleneſs; call to your aſſiſtance the following Receipts.</p>
                  <p>As to the general cure, you are to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from wine, except it be very well qualified; as alſo from all meats which heat the blood, as thoſe which are ſharp or ſpicy: or are eaſie to be corrupted in the ſtomack, as milk, cheeſe, &amp;c. uſe in your broths lettuce, ſpinage, purſlain, ſorrel, and the like: Blood-letting is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, chiefly in the median vein, in both the arms, ſome dayes being inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; then in the vein of the forehead, afterwards in the neck; apply cupping-glaſſes to the ſhoulders and neck, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally under the chin, and ſometimes to the thighs and leggs; you may alſo apply leeches to the cheeks and chin to evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the blood that is amaſſed under the skin.</p>
                  <p>For more particular remedies, if the malady be inveterate, begin with Emoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, digeſtives, and things that do at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate, not only to rarifie the skin, but alſo to ſubtilize the humor. For if at firſt you uſe cold things and repercuſſives, you will condenſe the skin through which the humors ought to exhale and impact the humor into the ſubſtance of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:51143:45"/>the fleſh, and make it the more contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to be diſſolved; whereby the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion is made more black and ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</p>
                  <p>Prepare then a Decoction of figgs, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins of the Sun waſhed and ſton'd, oat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meal, ſoap, french barley, the leaves of pellitory of the wall, camomil, mallows, violets; receive the fume of this Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction up into the face, covering the face and neck with a napkin, to keep the fume from diſſipating: continue this <hi>three</hi> or <hi>four</hi> times that the face may be ſupple, and the skin fitted to receive the vertue of your medicines the better.</p>
                  <p>Inſtead of this Decoction, you may ſpread on the viſage the warm blood of a pigeon, pullet, or capon drawn newly from under their wings; let the blood lay on all night, in the morning waſh it off with warm water, or the decoction of ſoap, oat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meal, or the like. Or elſe in the place of theſe remedies, <hi>Take</hi> freſh fleſh of a neck of beef, veal, or mutton, cut <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three</hi> thin ſlices, lay them on the red places, and change them often, or elſe they will ſtink: And in caſe you have no freſh fleſh, you may take ſlices of ſtale, put them on the coals, and ſo apply them
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:51143:46"/>warm to the redneſs. The next morning waſh the face with fine rags dipt in the forementioned decoction.</p>
                  <p>When you find that thoſe remedies do ſomething mitigate the fiery colour of your face, and aſſwage the pimples, you may proceed to other medicines, that have vertue to repercuſs the thin and ſubtle blood, and bind the skin that it may not be ſo apt to receive ſuch noxious vapours, nor long retain them. Such are theſe that follow:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> a <hi>pint</hi> of roſe water, put it into a glaſſe, and ſteep therein camphire and ſulphure finely powdred, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> myrrhe and frankincenſe of each half an <hi>ounce,</hi> ſet it in the ſun twelve or fifteen dayes. Often waſh the face with water:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Brimſtone one <hi>ounce,</hi> ceruſe waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed two <hi>drams,</hi> juyce of limmons half a <hi>pint,</hi> juyce of onyons two ounces, cuttle bones and camphire, of each one <hi>dram:</hi> pound what is to be pounded, and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate your pouders with your juyces; anoint the face therewith going to bed, in the morning waſh it off with the deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of bran.</p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:51143:46"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the roots of the greater and leſſer ſerpentary of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> bruiſe them, &amp; boile them with as much water of plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, roſes, water lillies and vinegar, as will ſuffice to bring them to a maſh, then beat them in a mortar with oyle of roſes two <hi>ounces,</hi> adding the fineſt pouder of burnt oyſter ſhells one <hi>dram and a half,</hi> camfre one <hi>ſcruple, Venetian</hi> ceruſe two <hi>drams,</hi> ſalt, powdred brimſtone, of each one <hi>dram,</hi> juyce of citrons one <hi>ounce;</hi> make all theſe into a Liniment for your uſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> litharge of gold, ſulphure viue, of each half an <hi>ounce,</hi> powder and put them into a glaſſe with vinegar and roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water; moiſten a fine ragg in this water, apply it to the face all night, in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing waſh with bran and water.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> ſulphure vive one <hi>ounce,</hi> litharge and ceruſe, of each half an <hi>ounce,</hi> powder and incorporate them with two <hi>ounces</hi> of freſh lard, well waſht with the juyce of citrons, adding a little camphire, beat them ſometime in a mortar, then keep it ſtopt in a glaſſe for your uſe. Or, boyle ſtrong vinegar with bean and roſe water, ſoak white raggs therein, and apply them to the face.</p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:51143:47"/>
                  <p>If your red pimples yield to none of theſe external remedies, you muſt have recourſe to things more violent. Some uſe Veſicatories made of <hi>Cantharides</hi> and Soap mixt together. Others flea the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidermis,</hi> or ſuperficial skin of the face, with <hi>aqua fortis,</hi> and after skin it with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waters. But ſuch medicines are too offenſive to the face, by reaſon of infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, and greater redneſs that happen too often through ſuch tampring. It were better, if neceſſity compels you, to apply ſublimate and quickſilver, for they are much ſafer than Veſicatories, or <hi>aqua fortis,</hi> ſo they be prepared after that faſhion which I ſhall here deſcribe.</p>
                  <p>To prepare Quickſilver, chuſe that which is moſt clear, white, and fluid; ſtrein it through a ſheepskin, it will cleanſe it of all its droſs, (the oftner you ſtrein it, the purer 'twill be,) then boyle it in vinegar with ſage, roſemary, tyme, camo. mile, melilot, then ſtrein it again through a ſheepskin, at laſt mortifie it with juyce of limmons or faſting ſpittle. Being thus prepared, it may with little danger be mixt with ointments, plaiſters, or waters. Others ſteep quickſilver in ſtrong vinegar and ſalt, for ten or twelve dayes, changing
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:51143:47"/>the vinegar and ſalt every day, then they purifie it with the crum of hot white bread in an earthen pot three or four times, then they paſſe it nine or ten times thorow a ſheepskin, and at laſt mortifie it with juice of limmons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sublimate</hi> is prepared divers ways, the moſt aſſured preparation for our purpoſe is this following. <hi>Take</hi> Sublimate four <hi>ounces,</hi> bray it in a mortar with a wooden peſtle, till you make it ſo fine that it doe not grate betwixt your fingers, then moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten it with juice of limmons beating it all the while: then take quickſilver, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared carefully as you were taught be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, one <hi>ounce,</hi> worke it together with the ſublimate in the mortar (wherein you ſhould have firſt pounded half a <hi>dozen</hi> almonds, to make the mortar ſlippery and the ſublimate more eaſy to powder) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this work them well together with a wooden peſtle for the ſpace of 3 or 4 days without ceaſing, eſpecially the firſt day taking no reſt; when you have beat it one whole day, adde one <hi>pound</hi> of the whiteſt Salt calcind, the next two days work and incorporate them together, ſo that of black or grey it may become white as ſnow, and if at 3 days end it be
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:51143:48"/>not ſufficiently white, continue your tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turation till it be ſo: when this is done put it into a pot well glazed, powre there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſufficient quantity of ſpring water, ſtir it about with a wooden Spattula, then cover it and let it ſettle till the water be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come clear, change the water three or four times for the foure firſt days: then ſtirre and change the water once a day for nine days following, ſetting it all the while in ſome ſhadie and moiſt place. When this is done and the water cleare, draw it off by inclination, and put the Sublimate in ſome veſſell to dry in the Sun, ſtirring it up and down that it may dry the better, then keep it in a leaden pot.</p>
                  <p>The uſe of Quickſilver prepared as you were taught before is thus, <hi>Take</hi> lard often waſht in vineger two <hi>ounces,</hi> prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red quick ſilver two <hi>drams,</hi> allum, <hi>ſulphur vive</hi> of each half a <hi>dram</hi> beat them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a leaden mortar and make them into an Unguent.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Lillie roots, roaſted under the embers three <hi>ounces,</hi> pound and ſtreine them, freſh butter and lard waſht in vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of each one <hi>ounce, ſulphur vive</hi> three <hi>drams,</hi> juice of limmon ſix <hi>drams,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:51143:48"/>ſalt half an <hi>ounce,</hi> camfre one <hi>ſcruple,</hi> work altogether and make it into an oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>The moſt efficacious remedies for this diſtemper are made of Sublimate, the beſt ways of uſing it are theſe. <hi>Take <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum citrinum, pomatum</hi> waſht in juice of limmons of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> ſublimate well prepared half an <hi>ounce,</hi> ceruſe waſht in roſe water and borace, both finely powdred on a marble, of each <hi>two drams.</hi> camphre powdred half a <hi>dram,</hi> incorporate theſe together, then ſteep them 2 or 3 days in diſtil'd vinegar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> ſublimate prepared half an <hi>ounce,</hi> burnt borace two <hi>drams,</hi> grinde them on a marble, after make them into little bals with the whites of egs brought to a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which upon occaſion you may diſſolve in roſe water to waſh the face.</p>
                  <p>But ſince Sublimate and Mercury though never ſo well prepared often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure the teeth and cauſe a ſtinking breath, it will be good when you apply them to the face, to take ſomething that may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſuch inconveniences; as often as you uſe them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to waſh the mouth with oile of ſweet almonds, or elſe to keep a peece of gold in the mouth.</p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:51143:49"/>
                  <p>When you make any application of quickſilver or ſublimate conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the face be groſſe and corpulent, or leane and meager: if it be groſſe you muſt mix them with ſuch things as dry excedingly as borace, ceruſe, calcin'd tartar, <hi>unguentum citrinum;</hi> if it be lean, you muſt uſe them with oile of ſweet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, pomatum, mucilage of gourd ſeeds &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> How to free the face from freckles.</head>
                  <p>FReckles are the product of <hi>fuliginous</hi> vapours, and like <hi>ſmoke</hi> uſually moleſt thoſe moſt that have the <hi>faireſt skins:</hi> as if beauty jealous of being outvi'd by too cleare complexions, did beſtow that yellow livery on others which ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to weare her ſelfe, The beſt means to remove ſuch disfiguring ſpots are theſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Oile of tartar one <hi>dram,</hi> milke of the figtree, hony of each two <hi>drams,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate them well together, and bath the face therewith, Or take cummin ſeed
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:51143:49"/>beaten three <hi>ounces,</hi> ſalt two <hi>ounces,</hi> brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone one <hi>ounce,</hi> put them in a marble mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and beat altogether with the juice of celandine and urine, make it into an oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; waſh the face there with going to bed, in the morning waſh with fair water.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> roots of wild cucumbers, lillies, briony, borage, daffodill, dragonwort, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> date ſtones, bitter al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of each as <hi>much,</hi> white corall, meale of lupines and beans, chryſtall, cuttle bone, nitre, ſal gem, white marble burnt, ſarco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colla of each two <hi>ounces,</hi> ceruſe five <hi>ounces,</hi> beat all theſe into an exceeding fine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, make them into little bals with the juice of limmons, and dry them in the Sunne; when you would uſe them, take one or two and mix them with Oxe or Sheeps gall, and ſo anoint the face, let it lye on three or foure hours, then waſh it off with warme water.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> what quantity you pleaſe of juice of limmons, put it into a glaſſe bottle, adde thereto fine ſugar and borace poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſet it in the Sun eight days, ſhake it well together once a day: after uſe it. Or fill a thick &amp; ſtrong glaſs bottle with roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary flowers, bury it half a yeare in a dunghil, having ſtopt it cloſe; in that
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:51143:50"/>time the flowers will be turned to water, waſh the face therewith, it is exceeding good againſt the freckles.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> calcin'd tartar one <hi>pound,</hi> maſtick one <hi>ounce,</hi> camphre half an <hi>ounce,</hi> incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate them with the whites of eggs and apply it where it is needfull.</p>
                  <p>Beat radiſh ſeed and dragon roots to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, put them in <hi>aqua vitae,</hi> and ſet them in the Sun eight days together, then diſtil them in a Limbeck, and you ſhall draw a water admirable againſt all ſpots in the face.</p>
                  <p>Boile litharge in white wine vinegar till half be conſumed, then ſtreine the vinegar, take a little thereof, mix it with an equall quantity of oile of tartar, it will be as white as milk; bath the freckles therewith.</p>
                  <p>Waſh the face with ſope and warme water, then moiſten the freckles with oile of tartar, or oile of allum, continue this for ſome weeks.</p>
                  <p>Beate as much ſandarack with hony as will make it pretty thick, apply it to the freckles, &amp; keep it on ſo long till it ſcorch the skin: then diſſolve <hi>galbanum</hi> with a little nitre in vinegar, and bath therewith. And when any of theſe medicines offend
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:51143:50"/>the skin waſh it with warme water, or anoint with oile of roſes, or oile of ſweet almonds.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> To whiten a tan'd viſage and to keep the face from Sunburn.</head>
                  <p>AMber haird <hi>Hyperion</hi> ſpying faces to dawn with a world of dazeling fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that might rob him of his Perſian votives, or withdraw the <hi>Heliotrope</hi> from its wonted homage; to ſecure his bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from being eclips'd by ſuch teeming beauties, clouds them in the ſhadie cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of night, while he makes day to all the world beſide: but to make your beams of beauty break through ſuch ſable curtaines take theſe preſcriptions fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
                  <p>White bryony water two <hi>drams,</hi> roſe water one <hi>ounce,</hi> the white of one egge, oile of tartar two <hi>drams,</hi> verjuice one <hi>ounce,</hi> mix them and waſh the face there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, then dip a linnen cloth in it and lay it to the face all night.</p>
                  <p>Mix ceruſe with oile of mirtle and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:51143:51"/>white wine, bath the face therewith go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to bed. Or <hi>take</hi> roſe water two <hi>ounces,</hi> womans milke one <hi>ounce,</hi> pounded myrthe two <hi>drams,</hi> the white of an egge, beate them together, going to bed waſh the tann'd places with it.</p>
                  <p>Make pomatum with oile of ſweet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, wax and camfre. Elſe <hi>take</hi> the roots of Sowbread, ſcrape them &amp; preſſe out the juice, boile it to the conſiſtence of hony, then uſe it to anoint the face. Or mix the powder of burnt cuttle bones with hony, apply it in forme of an unguent to the face.</p>
                  <p>To keep the face from Sunburn, you had beſt waſh with water drawn from the whites of eggs, or juice of ſoure grapes; or annoint the viſage with a liniment made of powdred Maſtick, and oile om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phacine. Or <hi>take</hi> goats ſuet well waſhed in cleare water, beat it in a mortar with roſe water, ſtrein it through a thick cloth, then take oile of ſweet almonds one <hi>ounce,</hi> ſugar candy two <hi>drams,</hi> camfre half a <hi>dram,</hi> boile them all together, ſtirring them continually that they may be white, when it hath boiled a pretty while put it into a glaſs for your uſe. If you goe abroad in the Sun or Wind anoint the face with
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:51143:51"/>it, and 'twill preſerve your comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> pepper wort, roots of baſill, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentary the leſs of each three <hi>ounces,</hi> boile them in a quart of water, make a liniment to apply to the face for an houre; then take it off and waſh with warme water, it is exceeding good to cleare the face from Sunburn. Briony roots boiled in oile; or cuttle bones burnt and mixt with hony, if they are applyed have the ſame effects.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> To remove running Tettars, or ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Puſtules.</head>
                  <p>TEttars, which ſome call Ringworms, are the noxious <hi>vermine</hi> that great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly damage beauties <hi>paradiſe,</hi> and crap its faireſt <hi>flowers;</hi> defacing quite the <hi>lillies</hi> and <hi>roſes</hi> that uſe to <hi>flouriſh,</hi> with a lovely grace, in the fruitful <hi>ſoile</hi> of a comely cheek. To ſecure your faces flowry <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſium</hi> from ſuch waſteful inſects:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> vinegar of Squills two <hi>ounces,</hi> aloes powdred two <hi>drams,</hi> juyce of dock roots, oyle of tartar, of each half an <hi>ounce;</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:51143:52"/>them together in form of an oyntment, then apply it.</p>
                  <p>Make a Decoction of dock roots, mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, fengreek in ſtrong vinegar, and uſe it: then apply leeches; or make ſmall ſcarifications, that ſome quantity of blood may iſſue forth; then anoint the place with the oyle of tartar, or apply dock roots ſteept in vinegar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> ſublimate prepared three <hi>grains,</hi> put it to half a <hi>pint</hi> of water, put it in a glaſſe into a boyling pot, till the ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate diſſolve: Keep the water as a choice experiment for any ſpreading tettar or puſtule.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Tartar two <hi>drams,</hi> burnt allum three <hi>drams;</hi> powder and incorporate them with the whites of eggs for an ointment, Or, <hi>Take</hi> ſulphur vive two <hi>drams and a half,</hi> nettle ſeed one <hi>dram,</hi> camfre half a <hi>dram,</hi> freſh butter two <hi>ounces,</hi> make an ointment, waſh it in roſe water, then uſe it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> plantane water two <hi>ounces,</hi> white vitriol two <hi>drams and a half,</hi> burnt allum one <hi>dram;</hi> mix them to bath your tet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or pimples withal. Or elſe, <hi>Take</hi> grains of paradice half a <hi>dram,</hi> cloves, gum tragaganth, ginger, of each half an
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:51143:52"/>
                     <hi>ounce,</hi> brimſtone ſix <hi>drams;</hi> reduce all to a fine powder, to be workt well together with lard, to make an ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> How to help the Complexion when it is marr'd with blue and congealed blood, or black and blue, proceeding from a ſtroak or bruiſe.</head>
                  <p>THere often happens an effuſion of the blood betwixt the fleſh and the skin, where it ſtayes and is congeal'd, to the great diſadvantage of the face: The cauſe of this diſtemper may be either <hi>internal,</hi> as corrupted blood in the body; or <hi>external,</hi> as a cold, chilling air, ſtroak or fall.</p>
                  <p>If the cauſe be <hi>internal,</hi> powder ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barb, ſteep it ſome dayes in ſtrong vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and bath the face therewith: Or, <hi>chew</hi> in the morning faſting, cummin or muſtard ſeed, or <hi>calamus aromaticus,</hi> and anoint the face with it. Turneps boyld in honey; aloes mixt with honey; or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney incorporated with the aſhes of burnt
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:51143:53"/>garlick, are exceeding good in this caſe.</p>
                  <p>When this blewneſs of the viſage pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from cold, there is nothing better than to chafe the face often with the hand or a courſe cloth, or elſe, which is more effectual, you may uſe for a Fomentation <hi>aqua vitae</hi> warm'd.</p>
                  <p>If after a fall or bruiſe, the face, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other part remain blewiſh, it will be convenient to diſcuſſe the congeal'd blood, which may conveniently be done thus:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the roots of marſh mallows, of the great and leſſer ſerpentary, of white lillies, waſh them cleane, pound and boile them to a maſh in rain water, mix it with the oile of tartar and dears ſuet, adding a little camphre and make it into the forme of an unguent.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the kernels of peaches pounded foure <hi>ounces,</hi> goard ſeed two <hi>drams,</hi> mix and pound them together, then preſſe out the juice or rather oile; you ſhall find it exceeding good for any black and blew bruiſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> yellow arſnick, <hi>ſal ammoniacum</hi> one <hi>ſcruple</hi> and a <hi>half,</hi> mix them with the juice of coriander ſeed in quantity about
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:51143:53"/>three <hi>ounces,</hi> bathe the bruiſed places with it. <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> heated and applyed to the bruiſe preſently after the ſtroake with two ſpunges, changing them as faſt as they cool, will take away all ſignes of the bruiſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> To ſmooth the face disfigured with wrinckles.</head>
                  <p>THE ſmiling glories of beauties <hi>ſpring</hi> are often <hi>nipt</hi> with an early <hi>autumne;</hi> when ſharp ſith'd time cuts thoſe flowry graces down, and ſhrouds them in the <hi>furrows</hi> of a <hi>wrinkled</hi> face. Now to make your verdant features flowriſh in ſpight of envious time, or after their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay to ſmooth the face for a new plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> oile of bitter almonds two <hi>ounces,</hi> lilly roots finely powdred one <hi>ounce,</hi> make it into an ointment with the oile of roſes and a little wax, and ſo apply it to the faces</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> oile of S. <hi>Johns</hi> wort one <hi>ounce,</hi>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:51143:54"/>oile of mirtle, quinces, water lillies, jeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, maſtick, of each half an <hi>ounce,</hi> melt all together in an earthen veſſel, then take it, from the fire, adding a convenient quantity of roſe water, then let it cool and uſe it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> thin ſhavings of ivory, make a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction thereof in water, ſtreine it and keep the thickeſt, to mix with an equall part of incenſe and mouth glew, make it into an unguent, annoint the face there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with going to bed, in the morning waſh with faire warme water.</p>
                  <p>Waſh the wrinkled places with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction made with an equall quantity of bryony roots and figgs. Or <hi>take</hi> incenſe, the ſcum of ſilver of each half an <hi>ounce,</hi> white pepper an <hi>ounce,</hi> powder all apart, incorporate them with mouth glew, make them up into ſmall bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, diſſolve theſe in roſe water &amp; make a liniment for the face.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the juice of ſweet almonds drawn without fire, hony, the roots of lillies, roaſted under the embers and pounded, white wax waſht with roſe water, make it into the forme of a ſalve, ſoake a piece of linnen therein for a cerecloth, &amp; make a mask of it to lay over the face going to bed.</p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:51143:54"/>
                  <p>Boile pomegranate pils in white wine and whey, till the wine be conſumed and the whole remain like a liniment. Or dry in the Sun wild cucumer &amp; bryony roots, powder them and often waſh the face with the powder ſteept in wine, afterward waſh with cold water.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> How to cure chaps in the Face.</head>
                  <p>WHen the injurious <hi>violence</hi> of wind or weather hath rent your ſilken Skins, if you intend to unite the ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting parts, you will find theſe your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable <hi>cements.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Staggs ſuet and Goats ſuet of of each half an <hi>ounce,</hi> burnt borace two <hi>drams,</hi> new wax half an <hi>ounce,</hi> oile of ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes two <hi>drams,</hi> make it into an ointment and uſe it. Or elſe <hi>take</hi> Capons greaſe and camfre, mix them and anoint the chaps therewith every night, in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing waſh with bran and water. Some diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve mouth glew in warme roſe water, and anoint the face therewith.</p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:51143:55"/>
                  <p>Diſtil'd oile of turpentine is very good; ſo is freſh butter, if you take three <hi>ounces</hi> of it, and mix it with the mucilage of gum tragaganth, of fleawort ſeeds, and of quince ſeeds, of each an <hi>ounce</hi> and a <hi>half,</hi> and ſo make it into the faſhion of an ointment for your uſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> kids ſuet one <hi>ounce,</hi> oile of the whites of eggs, of ſweet almonds, and of preſt henbane ſeeds of each half an <hi>ounce,</hi> gooſe and hens fat of each as much, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharge of ſilver prepared, waſht ceruſe, prepared tuttie, red lead of each one <hi>dram,</hi> ſaffron one <hi>ſcruple,</hi> camfre halfe a <hi>ſcruple,</hi> mix them and with a ſufficient quantity of white wax make it into an ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Remedies for the Face when it is Burnt or Scalded.</head>
                  <p>IF the face that Magazin of Beauty be ſupprized by catching <hi>flames</hi> and <hi>blown</hi> up into <hi>bliſters,</hi> your ſecureſt way will be to allay the fury of that offenſive ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thus</p>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:51143:55"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> lead burnt and waſht two <hi>ounces,</hi> Goats ſuet, white wax, of each one <hi>ounce</hi> and a <hi>half;</hi> turpentine ſix <hi>drams,</hi> prepared <hi>lapis calaminaris,</hi> waſht ceruſe; of each two <hi>drams,</hi> mirrhe, maſtick, olibanum, of each one <hi>dram,</hi> aloes epat. camphre, nitre of each half a <hi>dram;</hi> mix them and make a plaiſter.</p>
                  <p>To draw out the fire and take away the inflammation take the whites of two eggs, oile of roſes and roſe water of each two <hi>ounces,</hi> work them together and then apply them. Or take two raw onions, ſalt, Venice ſope, bole armenick, of each an <hi>ounce,</hi> beat them together in a mortar, adding by degrees as much oile of roſes as as will ſuffice to make it into an oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>To hinder the riſing of bliſters and take away paine, you may uſe this, Hens dung, the whiteſt and freſheſt you can get three <hi>ounces,</hi> freſh butter ſix <hi>ounces,</hi> ſage leaves one <hi>handfull,</hi> plantaine leaves two <hi>hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls</hi> fry them a while over the fire, and annoint the affected part therewith ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times a day.</p>
                  <p>Or elſe you may take old lard, melt it with roſe water, then ſtreine it through a clean cloth, when it is cold waſh it 6 or 7
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:51143:56"/>times in plantane water, and to half a <hi>pound</hi> of this lard, add the yelks of 4 eggs; if the paine be vehement, you may mix a <hi>dram</hi> of <hi>opium</hi> with it.</p>
                  <p>In caſe the ulcer be ſordid and puru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, make application of this; <hi>Take</hi> the inner rind of green elder, oile of roſes of each half a <hi>pound,</hi> boile them with a gentle fire, ſtrein them and adde oile of the yelks of eggs two <hi>ounces,</hi> frankincenſe two <hi>drams,</hi> tuttie one <hi>dram,</hi> wax enough to make it into an ointment.</p>
                  <p>To make the cicatrice ſmooth and faire, waſh the ulcer after it is ſufficiently cleans'd with plantaine water having firſt diſſolv'd therein a little allum, being waſht, ſtrew thereon ſome metallique powder, either of tuttie, ceruſe, litharge burnt and waſht.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> To beautifie the Face howſoever disfigured.</head>
                  <p>THis chapter Ladies, makes you a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of univerſall remedies, that will fortifie your faces againſt any diſtemper,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:51143:56"/>and in ſpite of al the maladies that beauty is ſubject too, make them matchleſſe: the only inconvenience that I feare from them is, that ſome of ye when ye look in your glaſſes, may fall in love with your own ſhadows, and ſo linger away Martyrs to your ſelves.</p>
                  <p>The oile or water of Talque applyed to the face makes it as white as alablafter. The manner of preparing it is this, <hi>Take</hi> talque, the moſt tender &amp; tranſparent you can get, what quantity you pleaſe, ſlit it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thin ſlices, put them into a glaſs viol for the ſpace of ten or twelve days, with the juice of limmons, during the froſt in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; make a bag of the thickeſt cloth you can procure, put the former ſteeped Talque into the bag, with the hardeſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver flints, let the bag when cloſe tyed be rubbed together by two men, till the talque be exceeding finely powdred, then take it out and put it into a earthen pot that is not glaz'd, with a narrow mouth, ſtop the veſſel and biud it well about with ſtrong wire, then put it into a <hi>reverberatory</hi> for the ſpace of 12 houres, then take it from the fire by degrees, when it is cool powder it with as much ſpeed as you can (leaſt it draw and take in the aire,) on a
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:51143:57"/>marble, then put it into a bag, with a hook at bottome whereon to hang a veſſel to receive the liquor, then hang the bag with ſuch a veſſel in a deep well, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a fathome from the water, for the ſpace of 30 or 40 days, until the humidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty begins to drop: then take it up and put it in ſome moiſt place where neither aire nor wind comes, leave it hanging til all the moiſture be dreind a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, the liquor which you receive is the water of Talque: by the ſame meanes you may make oile of Talque, if you put that which remaines in the bag into a Retort giving fire to it by degrees till you draw all the oile forth: this is the moſt uſuall and experienc't way of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring water or oile of Talque. Others preſcribe this method, <hi>Take</hi> of the beſt talque what quantity you pleaſe, ſlice it into thin leaves, then calcine it thus, take ſulphur finely powdred, make one ſtrewing of it in a crucible, then put a laying of talque, after cover it with more ſulphur, uſing this method till you have put in what quantity you pleaſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring there be more talque then ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, and that it be alwaies in the middle of the ſulphur: cover the crucible, lute it
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:51143:57"/>well, and bind it about with wyre, ſet the crucible in a ſtrong fire, for ſix hours, afterward pound it and paſſe it through a ſearce, then waſh it well in hot water, till the water be freſh, then pour of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by inclination and leave the Talque to dry; when it is dry put it again into a crucible, and put it to the fire for other twelve hours. Next, <hi>Take</hi> one <hi>pound</hi> of this Talque, ſal armoniack two <hi>ounces,</hi> pouder them carefully together, put them in a moiſt place, and leave them there till they diſſolve into a water; when it is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, ſeparate the two waters by a gentle inclination, taking heed you do not mix the waters. The water which is clear and uppermoſt is the water of ſal armoniack; that which is at bottom, is the water of Talque, which is as white as pearl, filtre it and keep it carefully in a glaſs; it makes the face as white as ſnow, and may be uſed by a Princeſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> ſweet almonds blanched, four <hi>pound;</hi> ſandarach, maſtick, ceruſe, ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur vive, of each two <hi>ounces,</hi> gum tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaganth one <hi>ounce;</hi> whites of eggs three <hi>ounces;</hi> beat them together, and leave them to macerate ſeven or eight dayes, beating them together once a day, then
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:51143:58"/>heat them till they begin to ſmoke, after preſs them, and you ſhall have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n oyle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent good to beautifie the face. Or elſe going to bed chew five or ſix peel'd almonds, then put them in a linnen cloth and bath the face therewith. Or, <hi>Take</hi> oyle of tartar, mingle it with diſtilled vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar in the palm of the hand, adding a little camphre, and uſe it to bath the face.</p>
                  <p>Diſſolve in fair water Ceruſe one <hi>pound,</hi> ſtrein it through a thick cloth, leave that which is ſtreined in a veſſel one night till the Ceruſe be ſetled to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom; pour off the water, and dry the Ceruſe in the Sun, covering it with a cloth that it looſe not its whiteneſs; when it is dry, adde thereto a like quantity of ſtarch and gum dragant: keep the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and when you would uſe it, mix it with a little Womans or Aſſes milk, waſh your face therewith going to bed; in the morning waſh with water wherein wheat flower hath been boiled; continue this twelve or fifteen dayes. <hi>Ceruſe,</hi> ſince it is ſo excellent to whiten and clear the face, and ſeeing there are ſundry ſorts of it, I will here give a direction or two for their ſeveral preparations.</p>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:51143:58"/>
                  <p>Ceruſe of Wheat is made thus: <hi>Take</hi> what quantity you pleaſe of the fineſt french Wheat, ſteep it in fair water five or ſix dayes till it burſt, then ſtrein it and beat it a little; then ſtrein it again in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther clean water, then ſtrein it again tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a cloth; when it has ſtood a little, and the water is ſomething clear, pour off that water and pour on another, beat it together a long time, ſtrein the juyce in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to more water, then ſet it in the Sun till the water be clear, then pour off the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter gently, and to the ſediment which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in the bottom adde more water; do this, continuing the change of water morning and evening, for ſix dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, keeping the veſſel continually co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and in the day time ſetting it in the Sun; on the ſeventh day pour off the water by a gentle inclination, ſetting that which remains in the bottom to dry in the Sun; after it is dryed, pouder it fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and keep it cloſe ſtopt in a glaſs. This Ceruſe is of ſingular vertue to whiten, clear, and polliſh the skin; <hi>Tuke</hi> then one <hi>ounce</hi> of this Ceruſe, white Corral and Borace, of each half a <hi>dram;</hi> Nitre one <hi>ſcruple;</hi> reduce them all to a very fine pouder, and when you would uſe it, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:51143:59"/>one part thereof in roſewater with camphre and musk; bath your face with it going to bed, in the morning waſh with water and the crum of white bread.</p>
                  <p>The Ceruſe of the roots of either of the Serpentaries, is thus prepared; <hi>Take</hi> the roots in <hi>July</hi> or <hi>Auguſt,</hi> ſlit them into little round ſlices, put them on a ſtring ſome diſtance one from the other, and ſo dry them in the Sun, after pouder them as fine as poſſible, then ſift the pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and mingle it with fair water, ſtrein it through a fine cloth ſo often, till the whole ſubſtance of the root paſs through the ſtreiner; then ſet the thickned water in the Sun ten or twelve dayes, in which time you are to let it ſtand cover'd twelve hours without medling with it, that the root may ſettle to the bottom; then pour the water off gently and put in clear, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it up and down that the water and the pouder of the root may mix toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; change the water after the ſame manner twice a day, during the ſaid ten dayes, at laſt pour off the water without putting in more, and leave the Ceruſe to dry in the Sun; when it is dry, pouder and incorporate it with roſewater (cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorated and ſented with musk) as much
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:51143:59"/>as will ſuffice to make it into ſmall balls, which you moſt dry in the Sun and keep in a glaſs veſſel. When you would uſe them, diſſolve them in roſewater to waſh your face withal at night, the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning waſh with water of Lillies. This Ceruſe is exceeding good to take away all ſtains, ſpots and freckles from the face. After the ſame manner is made the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſe of the roots of Briony, wild Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumers, Water lillies. Thus much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the preparation of Ceruſes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> litharge of ſilver and gold of each one <hi>dram,</hi> put them into ſtrong white Wine vinegar, adding camfre and allum of each half a <hi>ſcruple,</hi> musk and cloves to ſent the Compoſition; boyle all in a little vinegar, then filtre and keep it; then boyle a little rock allum in water, keep it a part; for your uſe mingle theſe two waters together, and bath the face, neck, or breaſts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Camfre one <hi>dram,</hi> allum, borace two <hi>drams,</hi> oyle of tartar one <hi>ounce;</hi> all being finely poudred, boyle them in two <hi>quarts</hi> of roſewater, ſtrein and keep it; 'Tis excellent to whiten the face, neck, or breaſts.</p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:51143:60"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> bitter Almonds peeled one <hi>pound and a half,</hi> the whites of <hi>thirty</hi> eggs with their ſhells, the tender branch of a fig-tree cut into ſmall bits, incorporate them together, and diſtil them in a glaſs alem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick over a gentle fire; adde to the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which you draw, ſugar candy, borace, and camphre, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> olibanum two <hi>ounces;</hi> pounded all ſmall, then ſtill them again; and preſerve the water that you draw, as a ſecret to beautifie either the face or breaſts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> How to faſten the Hair, and keep it from falling off.</head>
                  <p>HAir (Ladies) is the ſilken <hi>fringe</hi> to Beauties <hi>bed;</hi> or if you will, the ſlender <hi>ſleaves</hi> that nature <hi>ſpins</hi> for <hi>Cupid,</hi> thereof to <hi>weave</hi> his heart-ſurpriſing nets; if once it fails, that amorous god looſes a conſiderable part of his artillery, and after never acts but weakly for ye: So that it concerns ye, who triumph over intangled Captive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, to tender its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:51143:60"/>You may keep that you already have, a faſt Friend to you, thus:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> myrtle berries, gals, emblick my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robalans, of each a <hi>like quantity</hi> boil them in oyle of roſes. It is a Receipt as old as <hi>Galen,</hi> but as good as moſt, if it doth not ſucceed, uſe the next.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> myrrhe, pine bark, myrtle leaves, maiden hair, pound them together very well, then adde a double quantity of <hi>labdanum</hi> pounded; put all into white Wine and oyle of Radiſh ſeed, anoint the head very well with it going to bed; next morning waſh it with this bath: Sorrel leaves, maiden hair, emblick my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robalans, boyle them in water, and adde a little pounded myrrhe; it very much faſtens the hair. Or elſe, <hi>Take</hi> the leaves of Willow, Plantane, rock Allum, boyle them in water, adding a little poudred Tutty and Myrrhe: make a bath and waſh therewith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the juyce of the youngeſt Myrtle leaves two <hi>ounces,</hi> juyce of wild Olives four <hi>ounces,</hi> red Roſes dryed two <hi>ounces,</hi> Roman Wormwood two <hi>drams,</hi> boyle all theſe in a <hi>quart</hi> of white Wine till <hi>half</hi> be conſumed, then ſtrein it, and adde a
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:51143:61"/>little poudred labdanum and uſe it to waſh the head.</p>
                  <p>The golden water drawn from hony in a glaſſe ſtill is much commended. Or <hi>take</hi> the leaves and roots of vervaine, put them into oile of green grapes, ſet them in the ſun many daies, then ſtreine it and keep it for your uſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> an equall quantity of labdanum, wormwood, juniper berries, nigella ſeeds, vervaine, bind them up in a linnen cloth and macerate them five daies in oile, there is nothing better to faſten the haire; or to make haire grow.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Remedies for the want of haire, how to make it grow on any bald place, or there where it never came before.</head>
                  <p>IF ſome diſaſter, Ladies, have trod too hard on your heads, &amp; kild thoſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant plants that uſe to flouriſh there; you may againe attire them with their native beauty and repaire all former ruines thus,</p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:51143:61"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> marſh mallow ſeed, boile it in ſallet oile 'til it become thick, with this oile anoint the head 6 or 7 times in an houre going to bed; when that is done take what quantitie you pleaſe of the ſame ſeed, boile it wel with water and waſh the head therewith; it makes the haire come exceeding thick, the ſame effects hath this which follows,</p>
                  <p>Boile in white wine oile of maſtick tree, mirtle and labdanum of each two <hi>ounces,</hi> maiden haire macerated two days in the ſame wine four <hi>ounces,</hi> ſet them over the fire til the wine be evaporated, after apply it as an ointment to the head.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nigella romana</hi> burnt &amp; incorporated with hony; Bees and Waſps burnt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated with oile; gals and the aſhes of haſel nuts mixt with hony; the kernels of peaches pounded and boiled in vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar; the cinders of cantharides, ſouthern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whod, maidenhaire, lilly roots, mixt with bears greace are exceeding good for thoſe that have but thin haire.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Euphorbium, laurell berries, rocket ſeed of each two <hi>drams,</hi> ſulphur vive, white hellebore burnt of each halfe a <hi>ſcruple,</hi> make a linement with wax diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:51143:62"/>in oile of laurel; if applyed it will ſoon ſupply you with haire.</p>
                  <p>If you would cauſe haire to grow on any bald place, do thus; Pound elme roots, boile them in water til there remaine a ſlimy ſcum on top, gather that for your uſe; then rub the bald place with a cloth til it look red, and after anoint it with that ſcum.</p>
                  <p>Or <hi>take</hi> pumice ſtone beaten exceeding fine, rub the skin therewith ſo long as you can endure it, then bath it with vinegar, mixt with an equall quantity of nitre, ſal armoniack, ſulphur vive; your own expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience will approve it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> barly bread and ſalt, role them up in parchment, burne them in a crucible and reduce them to a pouder, which make into an ointment with bears greaſe. It is a ſecret of nature. Or <hi>take</hi> canthari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, fling away the head and feet, rub them on the bald place and ſo leave them, bliſters will riſe firſt and then haire,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:51143:62"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> How to take away haire and keep it from growing againe.</head>
                  <p>WHen the Lillies and Roſes of your Faces Elyſium, are oretopt by the haſtie growth of ſuperfluous excreſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, you may ſecure the glorious hue of your beauties pride, and eradicate thoſe aſpiring weeds that diſturb you, by <hi>taking</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Quicke lime four <hi>ounces,</hi> auripigmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum one <hi>ounce</hi> and a <hi>half,</hi> Florentine iris root one <hi>ounce,</hi> ſulphur, nitre, of each half an <hi>ounce,</hi> lye made with the aſhes of bean ſtalks one <hi>quart;</hi> mix all together and boile it ſo long in a glaz'd earthen pot till putting a pen therein all the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers peel off, then add half an <hi>ounce</hi> of the oile of ſpike or any other perfume; and from what part of the body ſoever you are minded to take away the haire, anoint it with this unguent and in a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an hour you ſhall find the effects; but remember when the haire fals away to anoint with oile of roſes.</p>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:51143:63"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Orpiment and quick lime of each an <hi>ounce</hi> and a <hi>half,</hi> the ſeeds of fleawort and henbane of each half an <hi>ounce,</hi> ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate two <hi>drams,</hi> ivie gum one <hi>dram</hi> and a <hi>half,</hi> opium one <hi>ſcruple,</hi> pound all ſmall and ſteep them in as much common lye as may cover them four fingers, then boile them as the former.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> quick lime half a <hi>pound,</hi> ſteep it in common lye or urine, adde to it half an <hi>ounce</hi> of orpiment, boile it to the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence of a ſirrup. As for the uſe of the foregoing medicines, you are to foment the place with warme water a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you apply them; a quarter of an hour after waſh with hot water, and when the haire is taken away anoint the place with ſome cooling oile as <hi>oleum roſat,</hi> oile of henbane, the ointment of <hi>Rhaſis</hi> camphorated.</p>
                  <p>After that the haire is taken from any part, if you would keep it from growing againe, take the gall of a Hedghog, the aſhes of muſcle ſhels burnt, mix them with bats blood and uſe it as an ointment. Or elſe bats blood, the juice of ivy and radiſh roots, goats gall, mix and uſe them, or take opium and henbane finely beaten, mix them with vinegar ſo anoint there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with;
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:51143:63"/>any of theſe will keep the haire from ever growing: the ſame effects have theſe following.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the blood of Frogs, <hi>terra ſigillata,</hi> ſumach, roſes of each as much as ſhall be ſufficient, beat them together and ſteep them in the juice of nightſhade for four &amp; twenty hours, then diſtil them &amp; waſh with the water the depilated places.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> ivie gum, emmets eggs, orpiment, colophonie of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> leeches burnt half an <hi>ounce;</hi> grind and mingle them with frogs blood and make an oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> juice of henbane, <hi>ſanguis draconis,</hi> gum arab. frankincenſe of each three <hi>drams,</hi> juice of nightſhade as much as will ſuffice to make it into an ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> How to make the haire Curle.</head>
                  <p>TWining curls are now much the mode, and none thought paragons for Beauty, ſave thoſe whoſe gracefull locks do reach the breaſts and make ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:51143:64"/>think thoſe ivory globes of <hi>Venus</hi> are upheld by the freindly aid of their cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpie twirls. If any affect the faſhion they may ſerve themſelves with theſe directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſo advantagiously, that none ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be <hi>free</hi> that may have the glory to be <hi>fetter'd</hi> with their curled haire.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> gall nutts, filings of ſteel, cipreſſe leaves, quince ſeeds as much as you pleaſe; quick lime half as much as either of the firſt, ſteep them in water wherein rye hath been boiled, let it ſtand one day, then boile it to the thickneſs of hony, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the haire therewith and curle it up going to bed.</p>
                  <p>Boile ſalt in water, gather the ſcum thereof &amp; mix it with myrrhe, it is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous in curling the haire.</p>
                  <p>Some to make their haire curle wind it up going to bed upon a hot Tabacco pipe or iron. Others diſſolve gum arabick or mouth glew in water, moiſtning the haire, with it, afterward they let it dry. Some in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof uſe the white of an egge or elſe beare or ale. But to give you farther &amp; better directions, firſt rub the haire well with lye or urine, that ſo it may be waſht very clean: then take 20 oak gals, mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den haire two <hi>ounces,</hi> and as much ſalt
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:51143:64"/>water boiled to the conſiſtence of hony, worke them all well together, and for two days anoint the haire therewith, on the third waſh it with this following Bath.</p>
                  <p>Boile firn roots, beet leaves of each a like quantity ſo long in water, till a third part of the water be conſum'd, then take it from the fire, put in a little gum arabick and when it is cool uſe it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> oile of fenugreek, oile of white henbane, mix therewith mirrh and gum arabick, and uſe it for an ointment. Or <hi>take</hi> beets and mirtle a like quantity, dry them in the ſhade, powder them, then mingle one <hi>ounce</hi> of the powder with two <hi>ounces</hi> of oile olive, and uſe it as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> mallow roots, ſeeds of flax and pſyllium, boile them a long time together, ſtrein it and waſh the haire therewith. Or make lye with oake aſhes, boile there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in nutgals, roots of dane wort, maiden haire, afterwards diſſolve therein a little litharge, bole armeniake, gum dragant, waſh the haire with it, when it is dryed in, anoint with oile of mirtle.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:51143:65"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> To make the Haire Lank and flag.</head>
                  <p>THE buſhie <hi>forreſt</hi> of the head is ſometimes <hi>labarinth'd</hi> with mazie and rude <hi>maeanders;</hi> while the locks them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves retreat in ſuch recoiling twirls, as if they rook the breaſts for a paire of ſnowie mountaines, and were afraid their tender tops ſhould touch them: they may be forc'd to extend themſelves to a pleaſing length if you follow theſe preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> oile of lillies, oile of roſes, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> oile of violets two <hi>ounces,</hi> green marſh mallows finely beaten three <hi>ounces:</hi> boile them altogether, anoint the haire throughly therewith, combing it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward very well.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> borage, mallows, beat them ſmall and work them well together with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon oile, let them ſtand together in a warme place a day &amp; a night; next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put them in an alimbeck, &amp; diſtil them
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:51143:65"/>ore a gentle fire the water that you draw from them, keeps the haire from frisling and makes it flag and ſmooth,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> oile of roſes four <hi>ounces,</hi> worke it well together in a great bottle with an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall quantity of faire ſpring water, then anoint the haire, twice a day therewith.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> To lengthen the Haire.</head>
                  <p>HAire though an excrement, is yet carefully cheriſht as a plant of value: for moſt fancye it to be the microcoſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>flax</hi> whereof <hi>Cupid</hi> twiſts his <hi>bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrings.</hi> To ſee it (I confeſſe) in the female ſex, of a more then uſual length is a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſpectacle, and if therebe any Lady that deſire it, ſhe may by theſe means ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffect her wiſhes.</p>
                  <p>Uſe firſt this unguent, <hi>take</hi> a wild gourd, hollow it within, fill it with oile of laurel, orpiment, henbane leaves, boile it over the fire and anoint therewith: then uſe once a week this bath following.</p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:51143:66"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> agrimony, elm bark, vervaine, boile all in a ſufficient quantity of water, till the third part of the water be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd and waſh therewith while it is warme.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the hardeſt and ſtiffeſt hony, boile it for ſome while over the fire, into three <hi>pound</hi> of this hony, while it is over the fire, breake 20 eggs, take them out when they are hard and put in ſo many more; at laſt take onely the yolks of the eggs and beat them with the hony into a paſt, then put them into an alembick, and with a gentle heat, draw from thence a liquor to waſh the haire withall, if you would increaſe its length.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> lavender, white ſaunders, carda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moms, coſtus of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> in the ſpring time ſteep all theſe for 24 houres in a <hi>pint</hi> and a half of the beſt white wine, then ſet it on the fire that you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the vapour of the decoction up into the haire, afterward waſh the head with it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> old white lard three <hi>pound,</hi> mince and beat it ſmall till it come to a paſt, then diſtill it in a limbick, and keep the water that ariſes from it to anoint the haire; it will make the hair of a faire length &amp; ſoft.</p>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:51143:66"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> willow peel, wormwood and ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thernwood, dryed roſes of each two <hi>ounces</hi> ſteep them in a <hi>quart</hi> of faire water for a night or two, then ſet it over the fire till a third part of the water be eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated, keep it and often waſh the haire with it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the aſhes of maidenhaire, politrik, reed roots, flax ſeed; make a lye of all theſe aſhes, wherein diſſolve a little myrrhe, adding thereto a third part of whitewine and then uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> To ſoften the Haire when too harſh and ſtiffe.</head>
                  <p>THE Haire on ſome hangs like thatch on a country Cottage, and ſerves more for uſe then ornament; to ſecure them from the impetuous injuries of wind and weather, rather then with its ſoft and tender ſleaves, to delight admiring eyes. Such ſtiff <hi>briſtles</hi> are uſual attendants to churliſh <hi>Corydons,</hi> who are repreſented by nothing better then the parallel
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:51143:67"/>emblem of ſurly <hi>ſwine.</hi> Thoſe then who deſire a more graceful covering, and and would alter the harſh conceit that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are apt to entertaine of their <hi>hoggiſh</hi> natures, may to their great advantage uſe theſe directions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the roots of galingale, fig leaves, camomile, melilot, mirtle berries what quantity you pleaſe, make thereof a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction wherein diſſolve ſalt nitre, and rock allum of each two <hi>drams</hi> adding the like quantity of pumice ſtones and cuttle bones; ſet all over a gentle fire, and while it is warme, bath the head there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with before the fire or elſe in the Sun.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the roots of white and black hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebore, briony, birthwort round and long, wake Robin, dry, and then powder them, afterward rub the haire well therewith. Or elſe make a lye of vine twig aſhes, wherein boile the meale of beans, vetches, barly and lupines, ſtreine the lye and adde thereto a little white wine; then uſe it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Emets eggs, henbane ſeed, rock allum, <hi>pſyllium</hi> and <hi>opium,</hi> of each a like quantity, boile them in diſtilled water of vinegar, bathe the haire wel therewith, when you have done this, make this
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:51143:67"/>pouder, <hi>Take</hi> ſalt Nitre, four <hi>ounces,</hi> Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mice ſtone poudred two <hi>ounces,</hi> Lilly roots and Cuttle bone, of each two <hi>drams;</hi> beat them all very fine and rub the hair with it. After you have done this, uſe again the former Decoction.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> white Saunders and Rhodium, of each two <hi>ounces,</hi> Myrrhe and white Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, of each two <hi>drams,</hi> Gentian roots one <hi>dram;</hi> pouder theſe, and uſe it: If it be for any perſon of quality, you may adde two or three <hi>grains</hi> of Musk. This Pouder is excellent good for the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> Remedies for the Hair when it ſplits.</head>
                  <p>VVHen Nature hath <hi>ſpun</hi> the ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hair to its utmoſt length, if it be not carefully kept, 'twill be <hi>fray'd</hi> and <hi>ravel'd</hi> at ends by ſundry accidents, which ſeem to envy that work they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not better. Your beſt proviſion againſt ſuch injuries, are theſe;</p>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:51143:68"/>
                  <p>When you go to bed, <hi>Take</hi> Oyle and Water a <hi>like quantity,</hi> put them into a bottle and incorporate them well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, anoint the hair well with it going to bed, next morning waſh it with this following; <hi>Take</hi> marſh mallows, fleabane, willow bark, boyle them in ſpring water, and uſe it to waſh the head. This will keep the hair from ſplitting, but if it be ſplit already, you muſt uſe this:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Myrtle and Willow leaves of each two <hi>ounces,</hi> poudred labdanum ſix <hi>ſcruples,</hi> emblick myrobalans poudred half a <hi>dram,</hi> oyle of Myrtle four <hi>ounces,</hi> white wine two <hi>ounces;</hi> boyle all theſe over a gentle fire to a conſumption of the <hi>third part,</hi> then uſe it to anoint the extremities of the hair therewith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the juyce of Willow leaves and Myrtle leaves, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> boyle and evaporate <hi>half</hi> a way, after adde poudred labdanum one <hi>ounce,</hi> then mix all with oyle of myrtle; keep it for your hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:51143:68"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> To make the Hair of what colour you pleaſe.</head>
                  <p>YEllow Hair was much in requeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the antients, whence the Poet <hi>Forma placet nivenſque color flavique ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilli.</hi> Yet now this colour is loaded with obloquies; for 'tis a fancy generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that the locks can never <hi>ſparkle</hi> with golden <hi>flames</hi> without, except there be ſome cheriſhing <hi>heat</hi> of luſt within: ſo that of late Black is more the faſhion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lookt upon as a quality congregating not the ſight only, but hearts and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons too.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make the Hair yellow.</head>
                     <p>If any Lady be in love with this colour, ſhe may order her hair thus; <hi>Take</hi> ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings of Box, ſtechas, cedar, liquorice roots ſcraped and bruiſed, coltsfoot roots, maiden hair, of each two <hi>ounces,</hi> and a <hi>little</hi> ſaffron; ſet all theſe over the fire till <hi>two parts</hi> of the water be conſumed,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:51143:69"/>then ſtrein it, and waſh the hair there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
                     <p>Or, <hi>Take</hi> rock Allum, Sandarach, of each three <hi>ounces,</hi> Saffron one <hi>ounce,</hi> Madder four <hi>ounces,</hi> Vine twigge aſhes <hi>two drams;</hi> beat the aſhes very ſmall with the Madder, boyle the mixture in water till <hi>half</hi> be conſumed, then take it from the fire and ſtrein it; afterward adde the Saffron, Sandarack, and Allum: keep it cloſe in a bottle; when you would uſe it, firſt comb the hair very well, then take a ſpunge and bath it with this Compoſition. When it is dry, waſh it with water where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Fengreek, Barly, Cumin and Soap have been boyled.</p>
                     <p>Make Lye with the aſhes of Ivy bark, wherein boyle over a gentle fire Madder roots, Gentian, Celendine, ſhaving of Box, yellow Saunders, Liquorice clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from its outward bark, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> Orange peele, and the inner rinde of Barberry tree, of each half an <hi>ounce,</hi> green Lupines pounded two <hi>ounces,</hi> Broom flowers, yellow Stoechas, moth Mullein a ſufficient quantity of each; bath the hair with a ſpunge dipt in this Decoction, then dry it gently in with warm cloaths evening and morning: uſe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:51143:69"/>likewiſe a Combe ſteeped in this Decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it gives a graceful colour to young peoples hair.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take</hi> the firſt buds of the black Poplar, pound them with freſh butter, ſet them in the Sun for <hi>five</hi> days, then ſtrein them and preſſe out the butter, waſh it with lye made of the aſhes of Box tree, then uſe it to anoint the hair.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make the Hair or Beard black, though before grey.</head>
                     <p>The hair, either of head or beard, will be as black as Jet, if you <hi>Take</hi> the ſhells of green Walnuts, bark of Oak roots, of each three <hi>ounces,</hi> the oldeſt and deepeſt coloured red Wine, eight <hi>ounces;</hi> boyle them to the conſumption of <hi>half,</hi> then ſtrein the juyce and preſs it hard; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto adde one <hi>pound and a half</hi> of oyle of Myrtle, ſet in ſix dayes in the Sun in a leaden Mortar, and ſtir it with a leaden Peſtle, then uſe it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take</hi> burnt Lead three <hi>ounces,</hi> Nutgals, Walnut ſhells, of each four <hi>ounces, terra ſigillata</hi> the like quantity, Roman vitriol ſix <hi>ounces,</hi> ſal gem. one <hi>ounce and a half,</hi> Nutmegs, Cloves, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> ſal
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:51143:70"/>amoniac, aloes, of each half an <hi>ounces</hi> pouder and ſteep them three dayes in ſharp vinegar, then diſtil it in an Alem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick, and afterward keep it for uſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take</hi> quick Lime one <hi>ounce,</hi> of both the litharges half an <hi>ounce;</hi> make a maſs with the Decoction of Nutgalls and Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nut ſhells; oyle of Camomile two <hi>ounces.</hi> Or, <hi>Take</hi> litharge of gold two <hi>ounces,</hi> aſhes of calcined Tartar half an <hi>ounce,</hi> quick Lime an <hi>ounce and a half;</hi> diſſolve all in mans urine, till it come to be as thick as an ointment, then uſe it for the hair.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take</hi> Privet and Vitriol, what quantity you pleaſe, put them in oyl &amp; ſet it over the fire till it begin to boyle, anoint the hair therewith, having a care that it doth not touch the skin, for 'twill make it very black. Dogs urine kept in glaſſe four or five dayes, if you anoint your hair there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, will dye it of dark black co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Take</hi> Litharge of Silver, quick Lime, burnt Lead, crude Antimony, of each one <hi>ounce;</hi> pound and infuſe them in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled water of Walnuts. Or, <hi>Take</hi> Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, Vitriol, Nutgals, quick Lime, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharge, of each two <hi>drams;</hi> pouder them fine, and incorporate them with running
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:51143:70"/>water to make a maſs, wherewith rub the hair going to bed, in the morning waſh it off with warm water and white wine.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> How to cleanſe the Hair of Scurffe or Dandruffe.</head>
                  <p>DAndruffe or Scurffe is a mealy duſt, that over-clouds the hair of the Head, Brows, and Beard: It proceeds from corrupted ſerous humors, which by reaſon of their acrimony, corrode the cuticle from the ſubjacent skin, and fret it into little pieces like bran. Thoſe who are ſubject to this diſtemper, if they would eaſe themſelves, muſt uſe this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod.</p>
                  <p>If the body abound with ill humors, firſt purge it with ſome convenient medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, afterward waſh the head, or other part affected, with this Lye; <hi>Take</hi> the aſhes of the roots of Beets and Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worts, make a lixivium therewith, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in boyl Lupins and Beans, a <hi>ſufficient</hi> quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity; then ſtrein the Decoction, and add
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:51143:71"/>a <hi>ſixth part</hi> of Honey. When the Head hath been well waſht with this, dry it carefully with a warm courſe cloth, then anoint it with this Unguent:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> bitter Almonds lightly heated in an oven, old Walnuts, of each ſix <hi>ounces,</hi> Sulphur half an <hi>ounce,</hi> Vitriol two <hi>drams,</hi> Honey of Squills two <hi>ounces,</hi> the dregs of old Wine three <hi>ounces;</hi> make it into a Liniment for your uſe with red Wax.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the aſhes of Figtree, boyl them in water and vinegar till the <hi>third part</hi> be conſumed; then adde Lupines and Beans, boyle them again till a <hi>third part</hi> be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, take it from the fire, ſtrein and uſe it. Or boyle the roots of wild Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumers in vinegar, to the conſiſtence of honey, anoint the Head with it all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Ox gall and ſalt, temper them with the juyce of Beets, anoint there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with two or three dayes; Then waſh with this following Lye: <hi>Take</hi> the ſtrongeſt vinegar and fair water, two <hi>pound;</hi> ſet it over the fire, and when it begins to boyle, put in a little Salt and flowers of Camomile, waſh the head of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten therewith.</p>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:51143:71"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> oyle of Rue one <hi>pound,</hi> Sope one <hi>ounce,</hi> Salt finely beaten half an <hi>ounce;</hi> work them together into one maſs; then waſh with this following:</p>
                  <p>Boyle Beets, Fengreek, Briony roots, Bean meale, in fair ſpring water, ſet all together over the fire till <hi>half</hi> be boyled away; then take it off, and when it is coole uſe it to bath the head withal.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> How to beautifie the Forehead.</head>
                  <p>THE Forehead is the Ivory <hi>throne</hi> where Beauty ſits in <hi>ſtate,</hi> it muſt therefore be <hi>ſmooth,</hi> and raiſed to a decent <hi>height;</hi> for if it be too <hi>low,</hi> 'tis much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the grandure of her commanding majeſty; and if furrowed with <hi>wrinkles,</hi> it will put her too much in mind of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane frailty, to let her take a pleaſing recreation there.</p>
                  <p>To make the Forehead <hi>high,</hi> eradicate the hairs which incroach too much upon its bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nds, thus, <hi>Take</hi> as much Maſtick as you ſhall have occaſion to uſe, ſteep it in
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:51143:72"/>warm water till it be ſo ſoft, that you can ſpread it upon a filler, then bind that fillet to the Forchead all night, and in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning twitch it off. So you may take hair from any part of the body. And when they are thus pul'd away, that they grow not again, uſe theſe medicines:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> a <hi>pretty quantity</hi> of Henbane ſeed, wrap it in a Colewort leaſe, and roaſt it under the cinders; then beat it in a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar and preſs out the liquor; adde to it a little Orpiment poudred, and make thereof a Liniment to apply to the part.</p>
                  <p>Or elſe, <hi>Take</hi> the gall of an Eele, mix it with oyle of Roſes, or the blood of a Bat, and uſe it. Or, <hi>Take</hi> quick Lime, Lizards dung, boyl them in an <hi>equal quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity</hi> of vinegar and oyle of Henbane, till the vinegar be conſumed, make it into an Unguent for your uſe.</p>
                  <p>To <hi>ſmooth</hi> and polliſh the Forehead when it is wrinkled, <hi>Take</hi> the ſhavings of Hartshorn, boyl them in water till there come a kind of oylineſs on top, with the ſcum of the water, and Bean meal, make a paſte, which you muſt make into ſmall balls. Keep the water wherein you did boyl the Hartshorn, and when you have
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:51143:72"/>occaſion to uſe it, diſſolve ſo many little balls in a <hi>ſmall</hi> quantity of the water, as will make it into the thickneſs of a Cear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth; apply it to the Forehead all night, and in the morning when you take it off, waſh with warm water. Uſe this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod often.</p>
                  <p>Or elſe, <hi>Take</hi> your whiteſt Mutton ſuet, waſh it half a ſcore times in cold water, mix it with the froth of whites of eggs made in a mortar, beating them together with a Peſtle and a little butter; then add a little Maſtick and Frankincenſe beaten to pouder, and anoint the face often therewith.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> How to beautifie, and adorne the Brows.</head>
                  <p>THe <hi>two Brows</hi> are <hi>Cupids groves</hi> of pleaſure, where he ſhelters himſelf from the too violent <hi>heat</hi> of the inflaming eyes. Or rather as a controuling <hi>Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> made ſuperintendant to the Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal <hi>Sphares</hi> below him, he keeps his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:51143:73"/>there, that he might with the more facility direct their beamy <hi>influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> when and whither he pleaſes. You may, Ladies, by theſe means make them beautiful.</p>
                  <p>If the hairs on the <hi>brows</hi> grow too thick, or irregular, you may pull them up by the rootr with a pair of mullets, and afterward uſe thoſe means which we have formerly deſcribed to keep the hair from growing.</p>
                  <p>If the <hi>brows</hi> themſelves fall too low o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the eyes, You muſt work a little Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick together with the joyce of Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worts; and going to bed, put the <hi>brow</hi> up into its place, and apply the Maſtick to it all night in form of a Plaiſter.</p>
                  <p>When the hair ſheds from the <hi>brows,</hi> the uſe of thoſe things is good which we have already given you to faſten the hair. Or elſe, <hi>Take</hi> the ſmall filings of Lead, and incorporate them with Gooſe greaſe to anoint the <hi>brows</hi> withal. Or if ye pleaſe, <hi>Take</hi> black Henbane ſeed two <hi>drams,</hi> Maiden hair one <hi>dram, unguentum irinum</hi> three <hi>ſpoonfuls,</hi> bruiſe what is to be bruiſed, afterward make it up with oyle into the form of an Unguent to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the <hi>brows</hi> withal, after you have firſt
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:51143:73"/>bathed them with water wherein Myrtle berries have been boyled.</p>
                  <p>The hair that is fallen from the <hi>brows,</hi> may be made to come again, if you burn Bees or Waſps, and mix them with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; but have a care you touch no other place, for whereſoever it lights, it makes the hair grow.</p>
                  <p>If the <hi>Eyebrows</hi> are of a reddiſh or white colour, you may make them of a lovely black by theſe means:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> red Filberds, what quantity you pleaſe, calcine them thoroughly in an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then veſſel, or crucible, work them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Goats greaſe, anoint the hair therewith, and if it foul the skin, waſh it off with warm water: This will make the <hi>brows</hi> very black. The ſame effect hath this which follows:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Maiden hair poudred one <hi>ounce,</hi> Labdanum two <hi>ounces;</hi> beat them well together with Bears greaſe, and rub the <hi>brows</hi> therewith. Many uſe black Lead only to rub the <hi>brows</hi> withal, and if ye do it without ſoyling the skin, 'twill give them a very pleaſing dark colour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:51143:74"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> Remedies for Inflammation, Bloodſhot, or Spots in the Eyes, and yellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Eye-lids.</head>
                  <p>SParkling eyes are the <hi>ſtarry</hi> jewels of a <hi>Heavenly</hi> face, which with their active influence, and amorous motions rule the reſtleſs fate of every Lover: When once thoſe twinkling twins make break of day through their incloſing lids, their piercing beams of glory amuze ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators, and make them pay a tributary devotion to thoſe Chryſtal Orbs from whence they flow. The beauty of the eyes is much impaird by <hi>inflammations, bloodſhot, duskie ſpots,</hi> which much ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe and cloud their ſplendour. Such vices may thus be remedied:</p>
                  <p>If the eyes be <hi>inflamed,</hi> you are firſt to begin with a good dyet, and never eat or drink any thing that may ſend fumet to the head; then you muſt be careful either to evacuate or divert that humour which cauſeth the malady, by purging, blood-letting, drawing bliſters in the neck, In the next place, apply them that
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:51143:74"/>may alter and digeſt the humour, if it be <hi>hot.</hi> it is to be done with cold things; as Fndive, Purſlaine, Nightſhade, Roſewater, Womans milk. If it be a <hi>cold rhume</hi> that falls into the eye, boyle Laurel leaves in white Wine, bind them in form of a Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to the eye, or make a Pultice of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>londine with white Wine, apply it to the eye, it both eaſeth the pain, and takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way inflammation. Or, <hi>Take</hi> Rue and Fennel roots, beat them well in a mortar; then boyle them in white Wine and bath the eyes with the Decoction.</p>
                  <p>If the pain and pricking be extream, <hi>Take</hi> the white of an egge, beat it toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſome Poppy water. You may make a very good Plaiſter for all inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations thus, <hi>Take</hi> an equal quantity of Saffron, Myrrhe, Opium, gum Arabick; pouder and diſſolve them in Roſewater, make a Plaiſter and dry it, and when you have occaſion, ſoften it with Roſewater or the white of an Egge.</p>
                  <p>When the <hi>pupil</hi> or <hi>ſight</hi> of the eye is covered with any ſpot, after you have purged the body, bath the eyes with Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor preſſed from Sowes or Wood lice, being bruiſed in a mortar, and in leſſe then thirty dayes, it will be taken away.
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:51143:75"/>Or, apply to the eye a bag full of cummin ſeed ſteep in warme white wine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> prepared tuttie, ſugar candie, ginger of each one <hi>dram,</hi> ſarcocol, white tartar of each two <hi>drams,</hi> muske half a <hi>ſcruple;</hi> powder, ſift and mix them altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and put now and then a little of it in the eye.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the ſeeds of fennel, parſly, wild parſnip, aniſe, carroway, roots of celen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, ſorrell, betony, leaves of agrimony, tormentil, rue, vervaine of each a like quantity, pound them all, and the firſt day ſteep them in white wine, the ſecond in womans milk, on the third diſtil them: keep the liquor cloſe ſtopt in a veſſel, and put two drops of it into the eye every day, it will take away all ſpots whatever.</p>
                  <p>To help the eyes when they are <hi>blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot,</hi> take green wormwood pound and mix it with the white of an egge, bind it warm to the eye; the ſecond time that it is applyed it will core you. Mix the crum of warm white bread, with the yolke of an egge, ſhut the eye and lay it upon it. Or ſoake unwaſht wool in an equal quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of oile of violets, whites of egs, juice of rue and apply it to the eye.</p>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:51143:75"/>
                  <p>If the lower lid of the eye in the cavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of it be of a tawny ſwarthy colour, you may by theſe meanes remedie it. Firſt let the Phyſitian remove the principall cauſe, then take oile of fenugreek and anoint the diſcoloured places with all. Or elſe anoint them with the oile of Cedar, which is exceeding good to take away ſuch ill colours. <hi>Take</hi> ſome Pomegranate peels and preſſe them, anoint the lids with the juice, and twill make them returne to their former colour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> To alter the ill colour of the eyes and how to make them bigger or leſſe.</head>
                  <p>ALL colours do not equally grace the eyes: they are <hi>Cupids</hi> torches, that ſhould ſhine with a ſplendent <hi>flame,</hi> and never <hi>burne</hi> too <hi>blew;</hi> which is a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour lookt upon as fatal, and never more aptly plac'd then in <hi>Bellonas</hi> (<hi>Mars's</hi> grim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lookt ſiſters) eye. Neither againe do all dimenſions ſuit with their office; they are
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:51143:76"/>
                     <hi>Cupids</hi> chryſtall quivers, and muſt not be too big for that litle archer, nor yet ſo ſmall as not to containe his magazeen of ſhafts. Thoſe that have eyes of an ill co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, if they would have them black let them <hi>take</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Antimony waſh'd and dryed five <hi>ounces, lapis lazuli</hi> one <hi>ounce,</hi> musk, camfre of each three <hi>graines,</hi> wood of aloes two <hi>ounces,</hi> frankincenſe three <hi>ounces,</hi> ſaffron halfe an <hi>ounce:</hi> make a very fine powder of all theſe, at night when you goe to bed put a little of it into the eyes, in the morning they wil be black as if they had been ſo naturally.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gioranni Marienallo</hi> an Italian, ſaith he hath often made proof of this which was communicated to him by an Armenian. <hi>Take</hi> acacia, gals of each an equal quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, powder them exceeding ſmall, then mix them with the juice of anemonie or wind flower, making it up in the thickneſs of hony, then paſſe it through a ſtreiner and keep it for your uſe in a glaſs.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Author exceedingly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends this following. <hi>Take</hi> henbane flowers, dry them in the ſhade and keep them: when you have occaſion to uſe them put them into white wine and bath
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:51143:76"/>the eyes therewith, it will make them black.</p>
                  <p>If the eyes be too little through the waſting of the whole body or any other diſtemper, have reſpect to the humour which cauſeth it and purge that, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bath them frequently with a ſpunge dipt in warme water or in womans milk newly come from the breſt.</p>
                  <p>If they are too big and beare too large a proportion to other parts, make an iſſue behind in the neck, purge the head and body, drink water, and abſtaine as much as can be from meats that are ſtrongly nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing. After this <hi>take</hi> cotton, anoint it with hony mixt together with ſaffron, bind it over the eyes going to bed, and often waſh them with cold water and ſalt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXIV.</hi> To make the Lips ruddie.</head>
                  <p>PAleneſs when once it affects the lips, makes the world believe, that thoſe rubie <hi>portals</hi> of the mouth, have loſt their
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:51143:77"/>varniſh by being too much <hi>knockt</hi> at<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thoſe Ladies whoſe lips lye under ſuch a ſuſpicion, may beutifie them witha corall complexion, thus</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the juice of briony, wild cucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, reeds, roſe water of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> clarified hony four <hi>ounces,</hi> boile all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſtrein it and keep it in a glaſſe: it is exceeding good to anoint the lips and gives them a ruddie and vermilion hue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the ſhavings of your deepeſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured braſil three <hi>ounces,</hi> make them into a very fine powder, ſteep it three daies in three <hi>pints</hi> of faire ſpring water, then adde fix <hi>drams</hi> of <hi>icthyocolla</hi> or fiſh glew bruiſed and minc'd, let it ſtand til it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſoft and diſſolves, then ſet it over the fire againe and adde <hi>grana tinctoria</hi> (<hi>chermes</hi> berries) foure <hi>ounces,</hi> rock allum one <hi>ounce,</hi> borace three <hi>drams,</hi> boile all theſe til half be conſumed, ſtreine it and in a glaſſe veſſel keep it cloſe ſtopt eight daies, before you uſe it. It gives a very ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able redneſs to pale or blue parts, whether lips or cheeks, that which you put on at one time will laſt 8 daies, in which time it will not be done off either by ſweat or water.</p>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:51143:77"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> fine filings of brazil two <hi>ounces,</hi> madder one <hi>ounce,</hi> Chermes berries half an <hi>ounce,</hi> infuſe them in ſtrong white wine the ſpace of four dayes then adde half an <hi>ounce</hi> of rock allum and boile al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to a conſumption of half, filtre it and keep it for your uſe. It is of very great efficacy to vermilionize either the lips or cheeks. Of the like virtue is that which follows</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> rock allum, fiſh glue of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> ſhavings of braſil two <hi>ounces,</hi> ſteep all three daies in faire water, then boile them, ſtrein them and put them in a glaſs to uſe at your pleaſure. It will make any pale or blewiſh part, to be very faire and lively ruddie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> How to ſmooth the Lips when they are rough and chapt.</head>
                  <p>WHen thoſe pretty ſiſter Rubies, have been kiſt too hard, either by a chilly and cold mouth'd <hi>Boreas,</hi> or a ſcorching and hot lipt <hi>Sol;</hi> to repaire the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:51143:78"/>breaches ſuch rude embraces make on their cherrie Skins, uſe theſe things fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Ladies, they will make them ſeem ſuch ſmooth and bluſhing wax, as <hi>Cupid</hi> will think himſelf honourd to imprint his kiſſes on.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Stags ſuet two <hi>pound,</hi> freſh lard ſix <hi>ounces,</hi> waſh them often in white wine, then worke them well together till all the white wine be preſſed out, then put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an earthen glazed veſſel. adding <hi>nardus Indicus</hi> three <hi>graines,</hi> cloves half an <hi>ounce,</hi> nutmegs two <hi>drams,</hi> ſeven or eight pippins pard, cord and ſlic'd, ſteep all theſe one whole day in a ſufficient quantity of roſe water, then keeping it covered, ſet it over a gentle fire, ſtirring it up and down with a woden ſpatula till all the roſe water be evaporated, ſtrein it through a thick cloth into a clean veſſel half full of roſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; let it ſtand till the ſuet be cold, and ſwim on the top of the water, then put it againe into an earthen pot, adding oile of ſweet almonds ſix <hi>ounces,</hi> Virgins wax four <hi>ounces,</hi> melt all theſe over the fire, ſtrein it againe into roſe water through a thick cloth, let it as before ſtand till it is cold, then take that off which ſwims on the top of the roſe water
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:51143:78"/>and waſh it well in ſome ſented water till it be as white as ſnow; then keep it for your uſe in a dry place that it do not mould. Some adde to this pomatum, coral finely powdred to make it the more drying; others adde juice of alkanet to give it a vermilion colour; there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better then this for any chaps what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
                  <p>Make an ointment of oile of roſes and a little wax anoint the lips therewith, or champ a little gum tragagant in your mouth and afterward moiſten your lips with your tongue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> oile of violets, mucilage of quince ſeeds, hens fat of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> litharge and gum dragant of each one <hi>dram,</hi> make them into an ointment and apply it to the lips. All fats and marrows are very good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the mucilage of quince ſeeds, oile of maſtick of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> gooſe fat, beef marrow of each half an <hi>ounce,</hi> a little new white wine, make theſe up into an ointment with as much wax as ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Or take a fine linnen ragg dip it in the juice of housleek, and apply it to the lips. <hi>Michael Noſtredame</hi> a Frenchman much commends cotton dipt in common oile
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:51143:79"/>and laid to the navel going to bed. It is an eaſie thing and ſoon tryed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> Remedies for ſuch vices as are incident to the Noſe.</head>
                  <p>BEauty is a nice &amp; cleanly Dame, that loves to have the noſe (though but the ſink to convey filth from the braine) kept neat and handſome, as well as the other parts which are deſignd for more honourable uſes.</p>
                  <p>Stanch and ſnivell do very much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire the credit of this patt. The ſtanch of the noſtrils proceeds ſometimes from a fool ſtomack; for if the <hi>kitchin</hi> be naſtie the <hi>chimny</hi> ſeldome ſinels well, if this be the cauſe, you muſt have recourſe to the Phyſitian. But ſometimes the fault is in the noſe it ſelf, as when it is affected with ſome fore or ulcer, then you may follow this method.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take Calamus Aromaticus,</hi> damask roſes, galingale, lavender, reduce all into a fine powder, then ſift it and ſnuff it up into the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:51143:79"/>noſtrils. Or <hi>take</hi> one <hi>ſcruple</hi> of London Theriacle, diſſolve it in white wine and draw it ſeverall mornings up into the noſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Roſes, Cloves, <hi>lignum aloes</hi> of each two <hi>drams,</hi> Spicknard one <hi>dram,</hi> Musk two <hi>graines,</hi> pouder what is to be pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and make them all into a paſt, with the beſt white wine, and ſo make them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to little pils; when you would uſe them, diſſolve one in a little roſe water and drop it into the noſtrils, but firſt waſh the noſe well with white wine, wherein roſes and lavander have been boiled; this will both cure the diſtemper &amp; cauſe a ſweet breath.</p>
                  <p>If the noſe be to much charged with ſnivell; the frequent uſe of gentle clyſters and vomits is very good. Or elſe anoint the head with ſome heating oile, if it be a cold diſtillation; and with a cooling oile, if it be a hot. When you go to bed, rub the feet with pitch diſſolv'd in oile, and waſh the noſe in wine, wherein put a little poudred myrrhe; By the uſe of theſe things you may ſufficiently purge the dregs, which diſtil from the beake of your dropping Alembick.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:51143:80"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXVII.</hi> How to faſten, cleanſe, and preſerve the Teeth.</head>
                  <p>LEaſt the Microcoſme might be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized by any treacherous <hi>invader,</hi> the teeth are ſet as ivory <hi>Portcullis's</hi> to guard its entrance. Or rather Nature hath made the <hi>ſharpſet</hi> teeth as ſo many mincing <hi>knives</hi> to belong to her <hi>kitchin,</hi> the Stomack: If they happen through a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſchance to be <hi>ruſted</hi> over, the beſt way to <hi>ſcour</hi> them, will be every morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to rub the teeth with poudred Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, after waſh them with white Wine, if it be in the <hi>ſpring;</hi> or with cold water if it be in the <hi>ſummer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> rock Allum, Salt, Nitre, of each four <hi>ounces,</hi> pound and diſſolve them in Vinegar, then diſtil them: to one <hi>ounce</hi> of this water adde juyce of limmons three <hi>ounces,</hi> and rub the teeth therewith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> rock Allum burnt, poudred coral, <hi>Sanguis draconis,</hi> Pumice ſtone, pouder them all pretty fine, and rub the teeth
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:51143:80"/>therewith. Or, <hi>Take</hi> white Coral, Cuttle bone, white Tartar, dryed roots of Florentine iris, of each a <hi>like quantity,</hi> a little burnt Allum: Make of them all a fine pouder, and keep it dry to rub the teeth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> calein'd Salt three <hi>drams,</hi> Galin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale two <hi>drams,</hi> Hartshorne burnt four <hi>drams,</hi> flowers of Schoenanthum and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes dryed, one <hi>dram;</hi> make them into a Pouder to rub the teeth with. If the teeth be very black, you may touch them ſlightly with oyle of Sulphure or Vitriol, but not too often.</p>
                  <p>When the teeth are looſe, your beſt way to faſten them, will be to <hi>Take</hi> Galls, Pomegranate flowers, Cyperus, Roſes, Sumach, a <hi>like quantity</hi> of each; <hi>Take half the quantity</hi> of theſe in rock Allum, pouder all, and rub the teeth and gums therewith.</p>
                  <p>Or elſe, <hi>Take</hi> Galls one <hi>ounce,</hi> Myrrhe half an <hi>ounce,</hi> Pomegranate bark one <hi>ſcruple;</hi> boyle them in vinegar, and make a Gargariſme to waſh the mouth. Some diſſolve Allum in vinegar to waſh the mouth withal.</p>
                  <p>To keep the teeth from rotting, <hi>Take</hi> calcin'd Hartshorne, cypreſs leaves, of each
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:51143:81"/>one <hi>dram,</hi> Cinkfoyle roots two <hi>drams,</hi> Maiden hair burnt one <hi>dram,</hi> Roſe leaves a <hi>dram and a half;</hi> bring all into a pouder and uſe it as a Dentifrice to rub the teeth with. It makes them white, and keeps them ſound. If the teeth are already rotten and corroded, <hi>Take</hi> Opium, Myrrhe, Storax, of each one <hi>dram,</hi> white Pepper, Galbanum, Saffron, of each half a <hi>dram,</hi> beat them together and apply them to the corroded tooth.</p>
                  <p>Or, <hi>Take</hi> Pepper, Pellitory of Spain, juyce of Spurge, Galbanum, of each <hi>a like;</hi> mix altogether, and put it into the rotten tooth.</p>
                  <p>Boyle Sage leaves in wine, waſh the teeth well therewith; then, <hi>Take</hi> black Hellebore, mix it with Honey, and put it into the hollow tooth. Others only put burnt Allum into it, and find much good by it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:51143:81"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXVIII.</hi> To Sweeten the Breath.</head>
                  <p>WHen your breath, Ladies, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of exulcerated Lungs or rotten Teeth, ſends forth a ſtanch more noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome then old <hi>Saturns</hi> ſweaty ſocks, make your application to theſe following medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, and you ſhall embalm the air with ſo rare a ſent, that all the <hi>aromatick fumes</hi> of <hi>Flora's garden,</hi> ſhall never enrich it with a more delicious ſweetneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Cloves, Nutmegs, Cinnamon, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> Mace, ſweet Saunders, of both half an <hi>ounce,</hi> Wood of Aloes an <hi>ounce and a half,</hi> Musk half a <hi>dram;</hi> after you have poudred theſe, make them up (with Roſewater, Sugar, and gum Tragant) into ſmall bullets, to hold in the mouth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> wood of Aloes, Galingale, Myrtle leaves, three ſorts of Myrabolans prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Cinnamon, Mace, Pepper, Ginger, Nutmegs, Cardamoms, Laurel berries, of each two <hi>drams,</hi> Musk, Amber, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre, of each half a <hi>dram,</hi> Sugar two <hi>ounces;</hi> make all into a pouder, and take
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:51143:82"/>one <hi>dram</hi> thereof in a morning; it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding good to ſtrengthen the Stomack, and ſweeten the breath.</p>
                  <p>Or elſe, <hi>Take</hi> gum Tragant one <hi>ounce, Sanguis Draconis</hi> two <hi>drams;</hi> ſleep them two dayes in Roſewater, then put them into a mortar, adding an <hi>ounce</hi> of Sugar, Starch half an <hi>ounce,</hi> Musk diſſolved in Roſewater one <hi>ſcruple;</hi> pound them well, then mix them together with a Spatula, and make them up into little pellets as big as barley corns, dry them, and after that they are thoroughly dryed, put one now and then into your mouth, and let it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Cinnamon half an <hi>ounce,</hi> cloves two <hi>drams,</hi> nutmegs, mace, citron pill, of each one <hi>dram,</hi> Florentine iris, the leſſer galingale, of each half a <hi>dram,</hi> yellow Saunders, wood of Aloes, of each one <hi>ſcruple,</hi> ambergreece, musk, of each half a <hi>ſcruple;</hi> ſteep them when they are pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in a <hi>quart</hi> of the beſt Malmſey Wine ten or twelve dayes, then ſtrein it through a woollen cloth, afterward put it into a Bottle, and keep it cloſe ſtopt for your uſe. <hi>Take</hi> a <hi>ſpoonful</hi> or <hi>two</hi> of it in the morning faſting; it ſweetens the breath
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:51143:82"/>exceedingly, and ſtrengthens the heart and ſtomack.</p>
                  <p>If the breath be infected by rotten teeth, <hi>Take</hi> the beſt Styrax two <hi>drams,</hi> ſweet <hi>Aſa</hi> one <hi>dram,</hi> the beſt iris root half a <hi>dram, gallia moſchata,</hi> yellow ſaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, of each one <hi>ſcruple:</hi> Diſtil'd oyle of Roſes <hi>half a ſcruple,</hi> mix them; and with a little gum tragant, diſſolved in cinnamon water, make a maſs; out of which you may form little long pills to put into the hollow teeth.</p>
                  <p>When the breath ſmells of Garlick, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyons, or any thing elſe that is eaten, <hi>Take</hi> coriander ſeeds, or zedoary, chew them in the mouth, and drink a good draught of Wine after, it will take away the ſent of any thing that was eaten before. The ſame effect hath Mint if it be chewed in the mouth. Fennel ſeeds, or Galingale champt after the drinking of Wine, takes away the ſmell of the Wine; ſo do ſour Apples and Quinces.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:51143:83"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXIX.</hi> How to beautifie the Neck.</head>
                  <p>NOthing more commends the Neck for comely, than to be white and ſmooth; for 'tis a part uſually expoſed to ſight, and ought to repreſent a <hi>Pillar</hi> of polliſht ivory, that <hi>ſupports</hi> the head with a luſtre becoming that place where the <hi>underſtanding</hi> ſeats his <hi>throne.</hi> It is uſually impaird by <hi>Kernels, Kings evil, hard Tumours,</hi> and <hi>Swellings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For <hi>Kernels</hi> (which uſually breed in thoſe places where the emunctuaries of the nobler parts are) if they come in the neck, (after the body hath been purged, and the Cephalicke veine opened in the arm) apply mollifying and diſcuſſive Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations, with ſpunges dipt in ſtrong vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, then apply a Plaiſter of <hi>Oxycroce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> adding a little gum <hi>ammoniac,</hi> bdelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, ſagapenum, opoponax, pouder of euphorbium.</p>
                  <p>For the Cure of the <hi>Kings evil,</hi> the pouder of Sarſaparilla, drunk to the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of half a <hi>dram,</hi> for forty dayes, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and evening, in white Wine, availes
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:51143:83"/>marvellouſly. The like operation have all your nitrous and vitriolick waters; for an external Plaiſter, you may uſe <hi>Empla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum divinum.</hi> In <hi>Autumne, Take</hi> the root of Scrofulary, beat it together with freſh butter, put it into an earthen veſſel well covered in a moiſt place, leave it ſo fifteen dayes, then melt the butter over a gentle fire, ſtrein it and uſe it to anoint the place. <hi>Take</hi> a live Mole skin'd, three or four Serpents skins, the roots of Scro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulary, Solomons ſeal, Briony, wild Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumers, of each three <hi>ounces,</hi> boyl them together in an <hi>equal part</hi> of wine and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſo long till the liquor be evaporated; adde at laſt, a little white VVine vinegar; firſt anoint the place with two ſpunges dipt in ſtrong vinegar, and applyed as hot as you can endure: then make uſe of the ointment.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>ſwellings and tumours</hi> of the Neck, (I mean thoſe which ariſe betwixt the skin and the <hi>aſpera arteria</hi>) are thus to be ordered.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, purge the body with Cephalick Pills: uſe a drying and temperate dyet: Then, <hi>Take</hi> ſal gem. amber, allum burnt, cuttle bone, nutgalls, long and black pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, cinnamon, ginger, pellitory of Spain,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:51143:84"/>of each <hi>half an ounce;</hi> pouder all very fine, and adde four <hi>ounces</hi> of Roſewater. <hi>Take</hi> every morning, in the <hi>waine</hi> of the <hi>Moon,</hi> a <hi>ſpoonful</hi> of this pouder, and ſo continue uſing it with your meat: when it is gone, make it again and uſe it.</p>
                  <p>Foment the place with the Decoction of Briony, wild Cucomers, Beets, Sage, Camomile, Melilot. Or put them all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a bag, and apply them as hot as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient can endure; then put on the part af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected a plaiſter of <hi>diachylum,</hi> to which you may adde <hi>euphorbium,</hi> ſulphur, verdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greece.</p>
                  <p>If the beauty of the Neck be any whit impaired by Freckles, Spots, Wrinkles, or Leanneſſe; you may uſe the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies which we have before preſcribed for theſe Maladies, in the <hi>Tenth</hi> and <hi>Twelfth Chapters</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Part;</hi> and the <hi>Second</hi> and <hi>Sixt</hi> in this <hi>Second Part.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:51143:84"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXX.</hi> How to keep the Breaſts from growing too big, and to make them plumpe and round.</head>
                  <p>YOur care, Ladies, to preſerve the the Beauty of theſe parts, muſt not be inferiour to that, wherewith you cheriſh any: for the Breaſt muſt be made remarkable with an outvying ſplendour, that ſo the graceful riſing of thoſe ſnowy hills, might like a pair of ſtately <hi>promon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories,</hi> tempt wandring Lovers, and make them take your Microcoſms for the only <hi>fortunate Iſlands.</hi> If ye ſear they will grow too big, ye may be theſe means keep them within their bounds.</p>
                  <p>Put as much pounded Cummin ſeed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to water as will ſuffice to make it into the conſiſtence of a plaiſter; bind it when you are young, ſomewhat ſtreight to the paps, with a fillet dipt in water and vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, letting it remain three dayes, then take away the Cummin, and apply the roots of white Lillies, incorporated with water, bind it likewiſe to the breaſt pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:51143:85"/>ſtreight, and keep it on other three dayes. Uſe this plaiſter often.</p>
                  <p>Bath the paps with Roſewater and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, whereto you may adde a little Camfre and Tutty. Or, pouder rock Allum, mix it with oyle of Roſes, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the paps with it. Or with oyle of Myrtle, and juyce of Henbane mixt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Some uſe to drink in their beer, half a ſcore <hi>grains</hi> of Hares dung to keep the breaſts from growing too big.</p>
                  <p>If the Breaſts have already exceeded their dimenſions, the dyet that you uſe, muſt be more ſparing and drying, that there be not too great plenty of blood; care muſt likewiſe be had, to draw the blood downwards from the breaſts. Ye may apply this, to hinder the breaſts from receiving too much blood,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the juyce of Hemlock, with the water of Myrtle &amp; Prunella, a <hi>ſmall quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity</hi> of Vinegar and Allum, dip a linnen cloth therein, and apply it to the breaſts.</p>
                  <p>When the Breaſts are flaccid, and hang down too low, you may make them round and plump thus; <hi>Take</hi> Quinces, green Grapes a <hi>like quantity,</hi> beat them well together; adde a little bole,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:51143:85"/>ſeed of Plantane, Annis, Fennel, Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min; with the juyce of Plantane and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar mixt; ſpread it upon the breaſts in form of a Plaiſter. The ſame effects have dryed Figs, incorporated well with Cummin and a little vinegar. You may likewiſe diſſolve Pitch, mix it together with oyle, and apply it to the breaſts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XXXI.</hi> Remedies for Inflammations or Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Breaſts, and chaps in the Nipples.</head>
                  <p>WHEN ſome inteſtine heat impairs the radiant whiteneſs of thoſe ſnowy hills; or curdles the milky nectar of the breaſts, into ſuch a hard and compacted thickneſs, that not being able to get forth, it muſt of neceſſity lye and generate ſharp corroding ſtreams, which fret the tender out-lets of <hi>Cupids</hi> fountains: Ye may, Ladies, in this <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> furniſh your ſelves with recuring re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies.</p>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:51143:86"/>
                  <p>For your Breaſts, when they are firſt Inflamed, <hi>Take</hi> the green leaves of Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, Mallows, of each four <hi>handfuls,</hi> Earth-worms newly prepared, ſix <hi>hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls,</hi> oyle of Roſes three <hi>ounces,</hi> oyle of Camomile and Mellilot, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> Barley meale three <hi>ounces,</hi> boyle all theſe together; and with a ſufficient <hi>quantity</hi> of this Decoction, adding <hi>Bdellium</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in vinegar, two <hi>drams;</hi> make a Plaiſter, and apply it to the breaſts. Or elſe,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the crum of white bread, Barley meal, of each one <hi>ounce and a half,</hi> the meal of Beans and fengreek, of each half an <hi>ounce,</hi> Roſes, and the flowers of Camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile poudred, of each two <hi>drams;</hi> boyle them, then adde roſe vinegar one <hi>ounce,</hi> oyle of Camomile and Roſes, of each one <hi>ounce;</hi> make it into a Pultiſs, and apply it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the leaves of Lettuce, Purſlane, of each one <hi>handful,</hi> red Roſes half a <hi>handful;</hi> boyle them in water, and adde to the Decoction, two <hi>ounces</hi> of vinegar; dip cloths therein, and apply them to the breaſts: If great pain doth accompany the Inflammation, you may uſe this as a ſingular remedy, <hi>Take Album Graecum,</hi>
                     <pb n="155" facs="tcp:51143:86"/>powder it very fine, make it into a plaiſter with white wine, or vinegar, and apply it warme to the breaſts.</p>
                  <p>Sometimes there is hardneſſe in the breaſts which accompanies the inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in ſuch a caſe <hi>take</hi> bean &amp; barly meal of each one <hi>handful,</hi> the meale of the ſeed of flax &amp; fenugreek of each half a <hi>handful,</hi> the oile of roſes three <hi>ounces,</hi> ſaffron one <hi>ſcruple,</hi> mix them together and make an ointment.</p>
                  <p>If after this, the paps remaine hard, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply ſome repercuſſive medicines, that the breaſts may not draw more blood then they can digeſt: anoint the breaſts and under the armpits with this medicine, <hi>take</hi> bole arm. one <hi>ounce,</hi> with a ſufficient quantity of oile of roſes, of myrtle, and vinegar make an unguent. To the paps apply this diſcuſſive cataplaſme; take dry mint two <hi>handfuls,</hi> worme wood one <hi>hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> boile them to marſh, ſtrein them, add the meal of beanes, lupines, of each half an <hi>ounce,</hi> make a pultis with the oile of lillies and apply it. If the blood be curd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, diſſolve it with this, <hi>take</hi> ſmallage four <hi>ounces,</hi> oxymel two <hi>ounces,</hi> meal of red vetches &amp; lupins of each two <hi>ounces,</hi> make them into a cataplaſme.</p>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:51143:87"/>
                  <p>When the paps are ſubject to chaps and clefts uſe things mollifying and atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating; before the milke come to the breaſts: wherefore it will be good for married Ladies before they lye in, to uſe ſome mollifying poultiſes, or to anoint the paps with wax workt well together with oile or freſh lard. Or elſe <hi>take</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Bole arm. myrrh of each half a <hi>dram,</hi> ceruſe two <hi>ſcruples,</hi> with a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Ducks fat, make an unguent for the paps. Or elſe you may anoint them with oile of ſweet almonds. The pomatum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the 25 chap. of this Part is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding good in this caſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:51143:87"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>PART. III.</hi> How to Beautifie the Arms, Hands, Leggs and Feet.</head>
               <p>A Mongſt thoſe beſt meanes that ye have Ladies, to get your ſelves in Fames immortalizing Calendar, canoniz'd for Beauties; it is one, to ſtudie the ornament of theſe parts, which though they ſeem the outbranches onely of rationall trees, yet conduce much to the ſplendour of beauties Paradiſe.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:51143:88"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> To remedie ſweating of the Armpits, and other inconveniences pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding thence.</head>
                  <p>SOmething is ſeems of miracle, that Ladies armes ſhould keep thoſe they once <hi>incircle</hi> ſuch faſt priſoners, that few of them are ever known to regaine their former freedome. Nothing inferiour to <hi>Cupids</hi> magick <hi>ſpels,</hi> they never <hi>ſurround</hi> any, but by their inchantments work on them ſo ſtrange a <hi>metamorphoſis,</hi> that they leave them nothing may ſpeak them men, but humane ſhape. If any Ladie find that her embraces have no ſuch powerfull <hi>charms,</hi> ſhe may juſtly ſuſpect there is ſomething that frights the amarous <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> from the <hi>bait,</hi> before they have leiſure to be intoxicated. Such ſents are thus remov'd.</p>
                  <p>After the body hath been purged, uſe a bath made with bawme, mirtle, laven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and other herbs of a good ſent in wine or water, wherewith bath the places af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. or elſe bath them with wine and roſe water wherein you have boiled
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:51143:88"/>allum, myrrhe, <hi>calamus aromaticus, lignum aloes,</hi> cloves.</p>
                  <p>If you bath the armpits with any ſort of allum diſſolv'd in water, it will condenſe the pores, and hinder the ſweat from ſtreining through the skin. Or elſe you may often waſh the arm pits with white wine wherein nutmegs or mace have been boiled, or wherein three <hi>graines</hi> of musk have been diſſolved; it hinders the tranſpiration of ſweat and gives a pleaſing odour to the body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Monſieur Liebault</hi> a French man ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth to keep this pomander under the armpits. <hi>Take</hi> Styrax calamite, ladanum, benjamin of each half a <hi>dram,</hi> cloves, mace, lignum aloes, lavender flowers of each half a <hi>ſcruple,</hi> musk one <hi>graine,</hi> with gum tragagant diſſolvd in roſe water and a little turpentine make them up for uſe.</p>
                  <p>As for internall remedies to alter the ill conſtitution of your bodies, I would commend this to ye; <hi>Take</hi> the beſt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malade of quinces two <hi>ounces,</hi> candid gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger one <hi>ounce,</hi> green <hi>calamus aromaticus</hi> preſerved, half an <hi>ounce,</hi> nutmegs, <hi>caſſia lignea,</hi> the leſſer galingale, mace, of each one <hi>dram,</hi> the ſeeds of coriander prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, of biſhops weed of each half a <hi>dram,</hi>
                     <pb n="160" facs="tcp:51143:89"/>oile of Cloves and Cinnamon of each one <hi>ſcruple,</hi> the whiteſt ſugar diſſolv'd in cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon water one <hi>pound,</hi> mix all theſe, and according to art make them into pectoral lozenges; a <hi>dram</hi> whereof taken in a morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doth wonderfully ſtrengthen a cold ſtomack, repair a decayed complexion, and utterly take away all foetid fumes that uſe to exhale from the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> For Chaps and Warts in the Arms or Hands.</head>
                  <p>YOur Alabaſter Armes and Hands Ladies, are the fleſhie <hi>altars</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> Inamorato's offer to you, as female Deities the <hi>firſt fruits</hi> of their devotion in zealous kiſſes. Your care ſhould be to keep them in ſuch a ſoul-inchanting ſymmetrie, that might confirm your Idolizing lovers in the opinion they have conceived, that you are more then mortal.</p>
                  <p>If the hands or armes are chapt, in the morning as ſoon as you are up, bath the chaps with ſpittle, then anoint them
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:51143:89"/>with Capon or Duck greaſe well waſht with roſe water. Or elſe <hi>take</hi> a little ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick finely powdred, incorporate it with oile of roſes and white wax; you may likewiſe mix poudred maſtick with the white of an egg, and anoint the chapt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with it. Or <hi>take</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Olibanum, maſtick, of each two <hi>drams,</hi> oile of roſes, new wax and Capons greaſe, of each half an <hi>ounce,</hi> make them into an unguent and uſe it. If the chaps proceed from heat, <hi>take</hi> hens greaſe and camfre, mix them to anoint the chaps withall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very night, in the morning waſh with bran and water: if the hands are chapt with cold uſe this, Litharge of ſilver, mirrhe, ginger powdred, a like quantity of each; mix them with oile of roſes and new wax, make an unguent, firſt bath the chaps with ſpittle, then anoint with this oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let it lye on all night, in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing waſh with warme water, it heals the chaps and makes the skin faire and cleare.</p>
                  <p>To free your ſelf from warts, apply to them a plaiſter of Cantharides, but let it touch no part elſe, and it will eat them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by little and little. Or bath them often with the milke that iſſues from the figtree.</p>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:51143:90"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Litharge one <hi>pound,</hi> quick Lime <hi>half a pound, ſal Armoniac half an ounce,</hi> common Vitriol three <hi>drams;</hi> boyle all in water to the conſumption of <hi>three parts</hi> of the water, then ſtrein it, and bath the Warts therewith.</p>
                  <p>The beſt way is to touch them with oyle of Vitriol, very ſlightly; for if you lay on any great quantity, it will quickly eat to the bone. Warts, when they come firſt, and are tender, may be removed with black Soap, mixt with burnt Salt, ſalt of Nitre, milk of Spurge, juyce of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>londine, juyce of wild Cucumers, pouder of Cantharides. Some rub them with a piece of raw Beef, and afterwards bury it. Others uſe Marigold leaves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> How to make the Hands fair and white, and to leſſen the Veins when they appear too big.</head>
                  <p>IF any Lady be already the <hi>Cynoſure</hi> to neighbouring eyes, and would be <hi>elevated</hi> to the higheſt <hi>altitude</hi> in peoples aeſtimation, beſides the attractive lure of
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:51143:90"/>a pleaſing face, ſhe ought to have hands, whoſe radiant whiteneſs might dazle ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators eyes, that ſo they might go on blindfolded in the fond humour of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her. And then I dare ſecure her, men will be ſuch cloſe captives to her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious tyranny, that ſhe need never fear being diſdain'd by any apoſtate Lover. The beſt means to bring the hands to ſuch a lillied ſplendour, follow here:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the preſſings of ſweet and bitter Almonds, which remain after the Oyle is drawn from them, of each four <hi>ounces,</hi> Bean meal two <hi>ounces,</hi> your fineſt <hi>French</hi> Barley, ground and ſifted, meal of Lupins, of each an <hi>ounce and an half,</hi> pouder of Florentine iris one <hi>ounce,</hi> red Roſes dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Benjamin, of each ſix <hi>drams,</hi> ſalt of white Tartar, the whiteſt Chalk waſht and prepared, burnt ivory, freſh <hi>ſperma coeti,</hi> of each half an <hi>ounce,</hi> oyle of Rhodium one <hi>ſcruple,</hi> oyle of Cloves and Lavander, of each <hi>half a ſcruple;</hi> mix them all well together, and with a little of the mixture often rub and waſh the hands: it is of an excellent ſent, and makes the hands ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding white, ſmooth, and ſoft.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Venice Soap diſſolved in juyce of Limmons one <hi>pound,</hi> white virgin Honey
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:51143:91"/>four <hi>ounces,</hi> prepared Sublimate, white Sugar candy, the roots of Florentine iris, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> ſalt of white Tartar, whiteſt <hi>ſperma coeti,</hi> Sugar, allum, Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an borace, of each <hi>half an ounce,</hi> true ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Balſame of <hi>Peru</hi> two <hi>drams, gallia moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chata</hi> one <hi>dram,</hi> oyle of Rhodium, Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, Cloves, of each one <hi>ſcruple.</hi> Uſe the mixture to waſh and rub the hands withal. It is of the ſame efficacy with the former.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Venice Soap, what quantity you pleaſe, cut it in ſmall pleces, ſet them ſo long to dry in the Sun, that you may bring them into a pouder. Afterward, <hi>Take</hi> one <hi>pound</hi> of this pouder, iris root, and Saunders poudred, of each four <hi>ounces,</hi> ſtarch ſix <hi>ounces;</hi> beat them altogether in a mortar, adding liquid ſtorax, and oyl of benjamin, what quantity you pleaſe; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the hands with this Compoſition, and it will marvelouſly whiten, ſmooth, and ſent them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take half a pound</hi> of Figs, as many Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins of the Sun ſton'd, and a <hi>like quantity</hi> of bitter Almonds, beat them all ſeveral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a mortar, as ſmall as you can, then mix them together, adding two Limmons par'd and minc'd, and two good <hi>handfuls</hi>
                     <pb n="165" facs="tcp:51143:91"/>of Bean meal, boyle all theſe in a <hi>pinte</hi> of white Wine vinegar, ſtirring them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually; when it hath boyled ſo long that it ſticks no more to the Poſnet, then put it forth into a <hi>gally pot,</hi> and keep it; uſe ſome quantity of it to ſcour your hands every time you waſh.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Labdanum four <hi>ounces, Styrax ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam.</hi> three <hi>ounces,</hi> Benjamin two <hi>ounces,</hi> put them into a brazen mortar heated, work them together with a hot Peſtle till they are pretty ſoft, adde poudred Soap two <hi>pound,</hi> then ſtrew thereon liquid Storax two <hi>ounces,</hi> make it into a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition with a little Roſewater, and keep it to ſcour your hands.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Starch, meale of Beans, Lupins, Rice, iris roots, of each <hi>four ounces;</hi> pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them very ſmall, ſearce them, and then mix them together; when you waſh your hands, take a <hi>little</hi> of this pouder and moiſten, to rub them withal.</p>
                  <p>If you like an Ointment, do thus; <hi>Take</hi> oyle of ſweet Almonds <hi>four ounces, take</hi> a <hi>little</hi> white Wax and put to it, boyl it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the fire, adde one <hi>dram</hi> of Camfre, and make it into an Unguent: it will both keep the hands from ſun-burn, and make them exceeding white.</p>
                  <pb n="166" facs="tcp:51143:92"/>
                  <p>When the milky whiteneſs of the hands is eclyps'd by the azure veins that ſwell too big, chaff them well with water wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in allum hath been diſſolved; then waſh them in warm water, preſently after an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint them with an unguent made of Ceruſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> wax an <hi>ounce</hi> and a <hi>halfe,</hi> turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine three <hi>ounces,</hi> frankincenſe, fenugreek, maſtick of each two <hi>ounces</hi> &amp; a <hi>half,</hi> three graines of musk, diſſolve the wax and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, in a new pipkin, then add half a <hi>pound</hi> of common oile; when it begins to boyl, ſtrew in the maſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ick, frankincenſe, ſenugreek, all being powdred, incorporate them together and make an ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> For the Hands when they are ſwoln and look red or blew with cold.</head>
                  <p>IF your hands like the flowry fields, <hi>diſmantle</hi> themſelves of their richeſt <hi>livery</hi> at the approach of the crabbed winter, &amp; laying aſide their youthful love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, do ſhelter themſelves under ſome more <hi>ſerious</hi> colour, that may better ſuit
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:51143:92"/>with the humour of that <hi>grave</hi> decrepit ſeaſon: Ye may I adies reapparell them with their native whiteneſs, by the help of theſe directions following.</p>
                  <p>Often bath your hands in wine where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you have boiled, nettles, roſemary, time, rue, penny royall; the frequent uſe of this decoction will keep them from ſwelling. As ſoon as they begin to ſwell and riſe into knobs apply a repercuſſive plaiſter made of barly meale and juice of limmons; or <hi>take</hi> litharge, oile of roſes and vinegar work them wel together into a liniment to anoint the affected places. If the ſwellings do not yeild to theſe medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the yolks of five eggs, calcine them, and mix them well with barrows greaſe, anoint the hands well therewith going to bed, draw on a paire of ſmooth gloves and ſo lye all night.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> turpentine, mix it with half its quantity of ſalt, ſtir them well together, till they are pretty thick, then apply it to the ſwoln hands.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> oyl of dil, &amp; oyl of ſweet almonds, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> mucilage of gum traga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganth made with pennyroyal water, three <hi>drams,</hi> powdred ſtarch eight <hi>drams,</hi> mix
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:51143:93"/>and make them into an ointment; it takes away the cold ſwellings of the hands and reduces them to their former Colour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Remedies for thoſe vices which are incident to the nails.</head>
                  <p>THE nails are pearlie <hi>helmets</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with prudent nature hath <hi>arm'd</hi> the active fingers, to which (if they are neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly burniſht) they give a commanding com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs; and may at a preſſing exigencie be fit materials to <hi>head Cupids</hi> piercing ſhafts: their oriental beautie is thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
                  <p>When the nails are ſpotted remove the ſpots with theſe medicaments; Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate myrrhe with a ſufficient quantity of turpentine and apply it. Or elſe <hi>take</hi> ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur vive work it together with a conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient quantity of pitch and tarre, uſe it as a plaiſter; you may if you pleaſe add a little vinegar. Mix flax ſeed beaten with hony and wax, put it to the naile that is ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
                  <p>If the naile be bruiſed and becomes
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:51143:93"/>black by reaſon of the blood that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geals underneath, apply a cerecloth that is made of capons greaſe &amp; ſheeps greaſe with oile of cammomile or dil: afterward to diſſolve the ſetled blood uſe goats dung tempered with ſulphur. Or incorporate cummin ſeed with <hi>diachylum ireatum</hi> and oile of camomile in forme of an unguent. Ducks greaſe mixt with Euphorbium is ſingular good to diſcuſſe the condenſed blood.</p>
                  <p>By ſome miſchance or other the top of the finger is oftentimes ſo bruiſed, that the naile comes off; to make it come again foment the part with wine wherein dates have been ſteeped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Flaxſeed one <hi>ounce,</hi> cardamoms three <hi>drams,</hi> as much hony as will make it into a plaiſter: this will make a naile that is cleft or rotted to come away: the ſame effect hath the juice of ſtinking orach. When the naile by theſe means is fallen off, to make it grow againe you may uſe that which was before preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</p>
                  <p>If the fleſh or skin grows too much o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the nails, milk of ſpurge dropt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is very good. Or <hi>take</hi> ſalt, barly meal and coſtus poudred; mix them with ſo
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:51143:94"/>hony, as will make them into a plaiſter and apply it to the fleſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Remedies for the galling, fretting and ſweating of the feet.</head>
                  <p>THE Body, that fleſhie pallace of a deathleſſe gueſt, would ſink beneath its own magnificence, were it not upheld by the feet, thoſe beauteous pedeſtals to the ſiſter columns that more immediately ſupport the ſtructure: If they are once fretted, or ſtand on too moiſt a foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they may chance to ſlip, and ſo the whole aedefice of beauty hazard it ſelf by catching a fall. Your wiſeſt way will be to ſecure them thus,</p>
                  <p>When the feet are galled take <hi>empla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum diachalcit,</hi> diſſolve it in oile of mirtle and uſe it to anoint the feet. Oile of eggs made by expreſſion, or elſe oyl preſt from wheat betwixt two iron plates is very good. You may likewiſe uſe thoſe things which have been formerly commended to take away chaps. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum album,</hi> or <hi>diapomphol,</hi> are not applyed without good
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:51143:94"/>ſucceſſe, the like might be ſaid of the oile of flax, freſh butter &amp; the yolk of an egg made into an unguent.</p>
                  <p>The feet if they are often ſubject to troubleſome ſweatings may thus be orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, bath them in warm water wherein allum hath been diſſolved; or elſe waſh your feet in water wherein the flowers and berries of myrtles, the leaves of cypreſſe, tamarisk, mint, marjoram; and after you have waſht them well, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint them with litharge powdered and mixt with hony.</p>
                  <p>There is yet another diſtemper inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the feet, which I had almoſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got, they are often apt to be numb'd with a kind of pinching chilneſs. You may Ladies, free your ſelves from this diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per thus. Make a decoction of the roots of enula campana, angelica, flowers of camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile, melilot, and once or twice a week bath your feet in it. You may likewiſe boile mint, marjoram, ſage, laurel, pepper wort, in white wine and uſe it as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:51143:95"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Remedies whereby to be freed from Kibes and Cornes.</head>
                  <p>THE <hi>ſervile</hi> feet, though they vaile bonnet to all the nobler parts, and are leveld with that, below which they cannot well feare a fall; yet ſeem to have ſomething of <hi>pride,</hi> while they often <hi>ſwell</hi> into tumours, and to thoſe dimenſions they cannot reach themſelves, they arive in needleſs excreſſencies: You may check this their petty ambition, and ſecurely trample upon them, if your hands will take but the paines to walke to your feet and apply theſe medicines.</p>
                  <p>For the kibes or thoſe red, hard, itch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tumours that are troubleſome to the feet in froſtie weather, bath them well till they are very ſoft in warme water wherein mallows or ſenugreek have been boiled, or in hot graines or oats boiled in <hi>aqua vitae;</hi> then apply to them an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent made of oile of maſtick, oile of ſpike, and wax of each a like quantity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the powder of gum tragaganth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate it with oile of maſtick and uſe it for a liniment, Or <hi>take</hi> goats ſuet one
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:51143:95"/>
                     <hi>pound,</hi> Galls powdred one <hi>ounce,</hi> melt and ſtrein the ſuet, then add the gals: uſe it as an unguent. Or <hi>take</hi> neats foot oile two <hi>ounces,</hi> galbanum half an <hi>ounce,</hi> boile them till they are pretty thick, then anoint the kibes therewith, having firſt well bathd them. Boile half an <hi>ounce</hi> of litharge in oile, ſtirring it continually then adde three <hi>drams</hi> of galbanum and make it into an ointment. <hi>Take</hi> ammoniack half an <hi>ounce,</hi> roſin one <hi>ounce,</hi> maſtick, frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe of each one <hi>dram,</hi> meal of fenugreek half an <hi>ounce,</hi> wax and oile as much as ſhall be ſufficient, diſſolve the gum ammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niac and the roſine over hot embers, then add the wax and the oile, when it is all melted add the meale of fenugreek and the frankincenſe powdred, make it into an unguent.</p>
                  <p>Beares greaſe, ſea water, the decoction of leeks, frankincenſe incorporated with lard, pomegranate peels boiled in wine, all theſe if they are applyed are very good. But if the kibes are broken and exulcera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, anoint them, with <hi>unguen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum,</hi> ſtrewing thereon powder of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, incenſe, myrrhe, then bind up the part affected with a fillet, ſteept in hot white wine, and cover it with a warme cloth.</p>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:51143:96"/>
                  <p>Corns in the toes or feet, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved by the ſame means which we have preſcribed for warts. Or <hi>take</hi> pure galbanum, new wax, ſoften them with your breath, and work them together, apply them as cloſe to the corne as you can. Firſt ſoften the corne with ſome fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, then apply a cautery; ſome uſe leaven, others the powder of the root of reſt harrow.</p>
                  <p>Waſh the feet, and apply to the corns the milk of fig leaves; then ſhave them with a razor to the quick, and if there happen any inflammation, anoint them with <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guentum roſatum.</hi> Bruiſe the leaves of rue and bind them to the corns: quick lime likewiſe kils them. Or <hi>take</hi> water of tartar three <hi>ounces,</hi> black ſope one <hi>ounce,</hi> quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver half an <hi>ounce,</hi> boile theſe nine times, &amp; every time when they begin to boile, make it ceaſe by powring in cold water, then waſh the cornes with this water morning and evening, then ſhave them to the quick, then waſh them againe as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, then ſhave them and they will be quite taken away. Some apply ox gall, changing it every day till the cornes fall away.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:51143:96"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>PART. IV.</hi> Sents and Perfumes fitted for ſeverall occaſions.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>E have heard Ladies how to furniſh your ſelves with a Beauty, ſo tranſcendent, that ſhall puzzle Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick to ſtudie Hyperbolies to expreſs it by; ſo cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivating, that none ſhall dare ſtile himſelf a Platonick; or at moſt, he onely whom your divine features ſhall make believe that ye are more than mortal. The former receipts ſhall furniſh each of ye with love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs enough for your whole Sex, &amp; make ye <hi>Pearls</hi> in beholders eyes; theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall make ye walking <hi>gardens,</hi> ſo that ye ſhal lead your ſervants by the <hi>noſes</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ye; they ſhal all turn Camoeleons and live on that aire which ye perfume.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:51143:97"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Perfumed Pomanders for Bracelets.</head>
                  <p>QUeſtion not, Madams, but <hi>Pomander Bracelets</hi> conduce much to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of your Captives numerous; though they <hi>bind</hi> only your arms, yet they take men your <hi>priſoners:</hi> for none can have the courage to reſiſt, that once ſee how much <hi>bracelets</hi> make ye Women of your hands. The beſt directions for making them, are ſuch.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> two <hi>ounces</hi> of the beſt damask roſe buds, the whites being cut off; musk, ambergreece, of each <hi>forty grains,</hi> civet <hi>twenty grains;</hi> let your roſes be beaten fine, as is uſual for Conſerves; then adde the former things with a <hi>little Labdanum;</hi> beat them well together, and make them up with gum tragaganth diſſolved in roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Styrax Calamite, <hi>Labdanum,</hi> of each a <hi>dram and a half,</hi> Benjamin one <hi>dram,</hi> Cloves, Mace, wood of Aloes, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender flowers, of each <hi>half a ſcruple,</hi> musk, ambergreece, of each <hi>four grains,</hi> a <hi>little</hi> turpentine, gum traganth diſſolved
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:51143:97"/>in roſewater, as much as will ſuffice; mix them well together in a warm mortar, and make all into a Pomander, according to art.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Florentine iris roots, Cloves, Mace, Cinnamon, of each <hi>half an ounce;</hi> yellow Saunders, Styrax calam. ſweet Aſa, of each two <hi>drams,</hi> Ambergreece one <hi>dram,</hi> Musk of <hi>Alexandria</hi> half a <hi>dram,</hi> ſweet Balſame of <hi>Peru,</hi> oyle of <hi>Rhodium,</hi> of each one <hi>ſcruple;</hi> mix all well together, and adde two <hi>drams</hi> of Civet. This Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition will be dear, but ye may make it in <hi>leſs quantity;</hi> taking either <hi>half,</hi> or a <hi>quarter</hi> of the doſes. Beſide, the exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pleaſant ſmell, it is good in Peſtilential times, and in Fits of the Mother.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the ſhavings of the greeneſt Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs wood one <hi>ounce,</hi> Florentine iris ſix <hi>ounces,</hi> Cloves three <hi>ounces,</hi> Calamus aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticus three <hi>drams,</hi> wood of Aloes fix <hi>drams;</hi> pound them altogether in a ſtill place. <hi>Take three</hi> or <hi>four hundred</hi> red damask Roſes clean pickt, beat them in a mortar with a wooden Peſtle; when they are half beaten, ;put in the former pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, then pound them again, moiſtning them with a little damask Roſe water; and when they are well mixt, make them
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:51143:98"/>up into ſmall Trochicks, and dry them in the ſhade. Of this Compoſition ye may make musk ſoaps, ſweet pouders, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders; and to make the Compoſition more excellent, ye may put what musk &amp; ambergreece ye pleaſe, ſo that ye pouder the musk, and diſſolve both that and the ambergreece in roſe water, then mix them with the former Compoſition.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> of the former Trochisks of roſes <hi>half an ounce,</hi> the beſt <hi>labdanum</hi> two <hi>oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Styrax Calam.</hi> Benjamin, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> violets poudred one <hi>ounce,</hi> amber and musk, of each <hi>half a dram;</hi> pouder what is to be poudred, and work them well together into a paſte; out of which ye may make Pomanders of an excellent and durable ſent.</p>
                  <p>If ye like a perfumed Compoſition to carry about with ye in a ſilver box, ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have a better than this, <hi>Take</hi> your true Jaſmine butter <hi>half an ounce,</hi> eſſence of orange flowers, eſſence of cinnamon, oyle of orange peel, oyle of nutmegs, eſſence of roſes, of each <hi>half a ſcruple,</hi> flowers of benjamin one <hi>ſcruple,</hi> eſſence of musk, amber, and civet, of each <hi>half a ſcruple;</hi> all theſe ye muſt work well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:51143:98"/>in a cold and ſmall marble mortar, then put it into your box.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Pouders for the Hair, Linnen, and Sweet Baggs.</head>
                  <p>IF after ye have uſed all hitherto com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, ye meet with any that defies your charms, and is obſtinate; do not yet deſpair, Ladies, for this <hi>Chapter</hi> teaches ye, how ye ſhall tickle his noſe, and fetch him about with a pouder, which will give ye ſo rich a ſent, that the roſes and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets in all your cheeks, ſhall not make ye half ſo ſweet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Florentine iris roots, finely pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred one <hi>pound,</hi> Benjamin four <hi>ounces,</hi> Cloves the <hi>like quantity,</hi> Storax two <hi>oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi> pouder them all very fine, and mix them together. This ye may uſe to ſent your hair-pouder withal, adding about three <hi>ounces</hi> of this pouder to a <hi>pound</hi> of Starch, ſifted and pounded; or elſe, to a <hi>like quantity</hi> of Rice, pouder of Poſt, or French Beans, being firſt pounded and then ſifted.</p>
                  <pb n="180" facs="tcp:51143:99"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Iris roots ſix <hi>ounces,</hi> red Roſe leaves poudred four <hi>ounces,</hi> Cyperus <hi>half a dram,</hi> Marjoram, Cloves, and Storax, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> Benjamin, yellow Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, of each <hi>half an ounce,</hi> Violets three <hi>drams,</hi> Musk one <hi>dram.</hi> If ye pouder them gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſly, they may ſerve to put in ſweet bags to lay amongſt linnen; but if ye pouder them ſmall, and ſeirce them through a ſeive, ye may keep the groſſer part for the former uſe, and with the more fine, ye may perfume your hair-pouders. This ye may obſerve in your other pouders.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Iris roots three <hi>pound,</hi> Cyperus roots, Benjamin, yellow Saunders, <hi>lignum Rhodium,</hi> Citron peel, Storax Calam. Cloves, Cinnamon, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re <hi>Labdanum,</hi> of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> ſweet Marjoram <hi>twelve hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls,</hi> flowers of Roman Camomile, and Roſemary, leaves of ſweet Musk, Tyme, and Savory, of each two <hi>handfuls and a half,</hi> the beſt Musk a quarter of an <hi>ounce,</hi> Civet <hi>half</hi> ſo much, Ambergreece <hi>half a dram;</hi> let all be driven into a groſſe pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, except the Amber, Civet, and Musk, which muſt be finely poudred, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward mixed. This is an excellent pouder for Linnen, and Bags; it will endure ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years exceeding ſtrong, and is as
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:51143:99"/>good a Compoſition as any where you can meet with. If ye mix a <hi>leſſe</hi> propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Zibet, Musk, and Amber, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be expected to be ſo pleaſant, nor laſting.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> from the Apothecaries common Iris roots poudred one <hi>pound, calamus aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticus</hi> two <hi>ounces,</hi> roſes four <hi>ounces,</hi> cori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander ſeeds two <hi>ounces, lignum Aloe</hi> one <hi>ounce,</hi> marjoram, orange peels, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> ſtorax calam. ten <hi>drams, Labda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> ſix <hi>drams,</hi> Trochisks of Roſes two <hi>ounces,</hi> Lavender four <hi>ounces,</hi> Cloves two <hi>ounces,</hi> Bay leaves <hi>half a dram,</hi> galingale two <hi>drams;</hi> mix all theſe and pouder them fine, then adde musk and amber, of each <hi>half a dram.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> yellow Saunders one <hi>ounce, cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus aromaticus</hi> a <hi>like</hi> quantity, marjoram three <hi>drams,</hi> the leaves of damask Roſes and Violets poudred, of each two <hi>drams,</hi> Nutmegs and Cloves, of each one <hi>dram,</hi> musk <hi>half a dram;</hi> all muſt be beaten into a groſſe pouder, then put it into ſilken bags to lay amongſt Linnen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the roots of Florentine Iris four <hi>ounces,</hi> Violet flowers newly d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yed one <hi>ounce,</hi> the root of round Cyperus two <hi>drams,</hi> the true diſtilled oyle of Roſes a
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:51143:100"/>
                     <hi>dram and a half;</hi> reduce all theſe into a very fine pouder. This gives a very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful and pleaſing ſmell, and is compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for their ſakes who do not affect thoſe ſtrong Perfumes that are made with musk and Zibet. Ye may put it in ſilken taffity bags to lay amongſt linnen, or elſe it may ſerve to ſtrew on the hair, or cloaths.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the preſſings (that which remains after the oyle is drawn forth) of ſweet and bitter Almonds, of each four <hi>ounces,</hi> the flower of French Barley and Lupins, of each two <hi>ounces,</hi> the roots of the beſt Iris pounded one <hi>ounce,</hi> white Roſes dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Benjamin ſix <hi>drams,</hi> ſalt of white Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, whiteſt Chalk poudred, <hi>Sperma Coeti,</hi> of each <hi>half an ounce,</hi> oyle of <hi>Rhodium</hi> one <hi>ſcruple,</hi> of Cloves and Lavender <hi>half a ſcruple;</hi> mix and make them into a pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, it gives the hands and skin an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent odour, makes them white and ſmooth if ye often rub it on them, or uſe it to waſh withal.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="183" facs="tcp:51143:100"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Sweet Waters, Oils and Eſſences.</head>
                  <p>SUch Ladies is the efficacie of theſe liquors that they'l cheriſh rather then extinguiſh the flames of <hi>love,</hi> they'l put ye in ſo <hi>ſweet</hi> a <hi>pickle,</hi> that will make ye dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhall <hi>ſharpen</hi> the <hi>appetite</hi> of thoſe that have no <hi>flomack</hi> to fall on a Ladie. In a word the Pope and all his Conclave ſhall never do ſo many wonders with their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly water as you may do with theſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> three <hi>pints</hi> of damask roſe water, malmſey <hi>half</hi> a <hi>pint,</hi> the flowers of laven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and ſpike of each two <hi>ounces,</hi> Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine flower de Luis roots two <hi>drams,</hi> nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, ſtyrax Calam of each half a <hi>drum.</hi> Infuſe altogether for a fortnight in a cloſe ſtopt bottle, then diſtill them in a glaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lembick, putting into the noſe of it a <hi>ſcruple</hi> of musk &amp; as much amber greece. Ye may mix this water with ordinary water for your hands, or put ſome of it on a chafing diſh of coals, it will recreate the ſences with a pleaſing vapour. An e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall quantity of roſe water and vinegar ſet on the coals does the ſame.</p>
                  <pb n="184" facs="tcp:51143:101"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> roſe water four <hi>ounces,</hi> cinnamon <hi>half</hi> an <hi>ounce,</hi> yellow ſaunders poudred, wood of aloes, citron peel, cloves of each <hi>half</hi> a <hi>ſcruple,</hi> musk two <hi>grains,</hi> mix them, and they will make an excellent ſented water.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> oiles of musk one <hi>dram,</hi> of cloves ſix <hi>graines,</hi> of lillies of the vally three <hi>graines,</hi> a little Virgin wax, mix them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther according to art, and you ſhall have an odoriferous balſam that comforts the brain and revives the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irits, if ye anoint the noſtrils with a little of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> cloves, cinnamon, lavender, nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs of each two <hi>drams,</hi> oiles of cloves, angelica, ſpike, lavender, of each <hi>half</hi> a <hi>ſcruple,</hi> wax four <hi>drams,</hi> musk and amber of each three <hi>graines,</hi> make them into a Balſame which will be of the ſame virtues with the former.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> musk finely powdred a <hi>dram</hi> and a <hi>half,</hi> put it into a glaſſe alembick, poure thereon two <hi>quarts'</hi> of roſe water, diſtil this over a gentle fire in B. M. keep the water that ye draw from thence in a glaſs cloſe ſtopped, it may be ſerviceable to Queens and Empreſſes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> roſe water three <hi>quarts, aſſa dulcis</hi> poudred one <hi>ounce,</hi> ſtorax, cloves, wood
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:51143:101"/>of aloes, camfre of each one <hi>dram,</hi> musk and civet, of each one <hi>ſcruple,</hi> put all theſe into a glaſſe bottle, cloſe ſtopped, which boile for the ſpace of four houres in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then take the veſſel wherein the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is and let it cool by degrees; when it is cold ſtreine it through a thick cloth, then put it into another glaſſe veſſel with fifteen <hi>graines</hi> of musk, ſtop it cloſe and ſet it in the Sun five dayes. This perfume is ſo ſtrong, that if you mix one part thereof with twelve of water, twil be exceeding ſweet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Lavender flowers ſeven <hi>handfuls,</hi> roſemary flowers, clove July flowers, orange peel of each three <hi>handfuls,</hi> mint, ſage, bay leaves, elder flowers, pennyroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of each one <hi>handful,</hi> cloves four <hi>ounces,</hi> galingale, nutmegs, <hi>calamus aromaticus,</hi> ginger, cinnamon, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> the beſt ſented white wine three <hi>quarts,</hi> pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all the ſpices and ſteep them in white wine, put all into a glaſſe veſſel ſtopped, ſet it in the Sun eight dayes, then put it into a glaſſe alembick with musk and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill all in B. M. Whether it be diſtilled or not, it is a very ſweet water, excellent to waſh the hands if ye mix one drop of it with a hundred of common water, if it be
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:51143:102"/>applyed to the face it will free it from ſpots and freckles.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> twenty <hi>graines</hi> of musk, nutmegs, cloves, galingale, ſpikenard, grains of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, mace, cinnamon, of each one <hi>ounce,</hi> powder all very ſmall, and put them all into a <hi>pinte</hi> bottle of roſe water, let them ſteep four daies, then pour on more roſe water and after diſtil them in <hi>B. M.</hi> Or tye in a very fine rag, musk and civet of each one <hi>dram,</hi> put the bag into a three <hi>quart</hi> bottle fild with roſe water, expoſe it ſome days to the ſun, and ye ſhall have a rich ſented water.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> the pureſt Benzoin twelve <hi>ounces,</hi> powder it very fine, then take liquid ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax as much as will ſuffice to make it into a paſt, when it is well mixt put it into a glaſſe alembick with a glaſſe head; which ye muſt ſet in aſhes or ſifted ſand, and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a receiver to the noſe of the alem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick, with potters clay and the whites of egs very cloſe, that the vapours may have no vent forth; (which if they have they'l be ſo ſtrong that to moſt they'l ſeem a ſtink rather then a perfume, and to ſome perſons may be very prejudicial) when things are thus fitted kindle fire under it by degrees, afterwards make the fire
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:51143:102"/>ſtronger; at firſt ye ſhall draw a yellow water in a ſmall quantity and worth little, but preſently after there will ariſe a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour white as ſnow, that will ſtick to the alembick; when ye perceive that this ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes no more then make the fire ſtronger, but not too violent, then will an oile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend that is ſweeter then the former: and according to the colour of your oiles, remember to change your receivers; your laſt oile wil be an excellent Balſame. But to make an exact perfume, <hi>take</hi> an <hi>ounce</hi> and a half of the white ſnow, oile of ſweet almonds newly drawn four <hi>ounces,</hi> melt both over a gentle fire, ſtirring it continually with a ſpattula till the ſnowie part be diſſolv'd, and to give it a reddiſh colour put in a ſmall piece of the root of alkanet; ſo ye may have a perfume of an excellent ſent. Iſ you would have this oyl of a richer odour, ye may diſſolve therein one <hi>ſcruple</hi> of amber greece. The black oile that remains at the bottome of your alembick, is of a very ſtrong ſmel, but mixt with liquid ſtyrax will make excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently ſented pomanders: if ye keep it by it ſelf, ye were beſt to keep it open that ſo the ſtrong ſent may evaporate.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="188" facs="tcp:51143:103"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Sweet Candles, and Perfumes to burn.</head>
                  <p>YE are much beholding, Ladies, to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary <hi>Candles;</hi> for when the ſooty night would be-friend your Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maids, and make them ſeem as handſome as your ſelves, that which diſcovers the cheat, and makes ye be prefer'd before them, is the friendly <hi>light</hi> thoſe <hi>Candles</hi> lend; they ſhew the difference betwixt a <hi>beauty</hi> and the <hi>foiles</hi> that uſually attend her. But if thoſe <hi>common ones</hi> do ye much ſervice, <hi>theſe</hi> will more; for if ye can once procure theſe <hi>ignes fatui</hi> to lead them, ye may be ſure to make <hi>fools</hi> of men; and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fear but ye ſhall have ſervants, after ye have got ſuch enamouring <hi>flames.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take Labdanum</hi> two <hi>ounces,</hi> Storax one <hi>ounce,</hi> Benjamin and Cloves, of each <hi>half an ounce,</hi> Mace a quarter of an <hi>ounce;</hi> beat all to a pouder in a braſen mortar, and when they are finely poudred, ſet the mortar over a gentle fire, and work them well together; then take roſewater <hi>eight ſpoonfuls,</hi> diſſolve therein musk and civet, of each three <hi>grains;</hi> afterward, put it with the reſt of the ingredients, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:51143:103"/>the mortar; when ye have mixed all throughly together, make the whole maſs into ſmall long roles; when they are dry, you may put them into a ſilken bag, and lay them amongſt linnen, or burn them in your chamber, or any where elſe at your pleaſure. They are a pleaſing Perfume, and will laſt good ſeven years.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take Labdanum</hi> two <hi>drams,</hi> Styrax <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam.</hi> a <hi>dram and a half,</hi> benjamin, fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincenſe, white amber, wood of aloes, red roſes, wood of cypreſs, cinnamon, cloves, of each two <hi>ſcruples,</hi> amber, musk, of each five <hi>grains;</hi> make them up into ſmall cakes with gum tragaganth diſſolved in ſpirit of roſes, one whereof caſt upon the coals, ſents your chamber with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful vapour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take Labdanum</hi> one <hi>ounce and a half,</hi> dryed charcoal made of willow one <hi>ounce,</hi> myrrhe, wood of aloes, ſtyrax <hi>calam.</hi> of each one <hi>ounce and a half,</hi> amber, musk, of each ſeven <hi>grains;</hi> diſſolve half an <hi>ounce</hi> of gum tragant in roſewater with a <hi>little</hi> ſpirit of wine, and make them up into roles like ſmall candles.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> gum ſtyrax <hi>calam.</hi> benjamin, of each <hi>equal quantities,</hi> diſſolve them in the beſt roſewater; as ſoon as they are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:51143:104"/>ſtrein them hard thorough a thick cloth: afterwards dry them, and pouder them, and keep the pouder for your uſe. <hi>Take</hi> of this pouder thus prepared one <hi>ounce,</hi> the weightieſt wood of aloes pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, two <hi>drams,</hi> red roſes dryed, amber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greece, of each one <hi>dram,</hi> zibet, musk, of each <hi>half a dram,</hi> ſweet balſame of <hi>Per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> oyle of <hi>Rhodium,</hi> of each one <hi>ſcruple,</hi> ivory burnt till it be black, as much as will ſuffice: powder what is to be pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, then mix all with roſe water, and work them together into a kind of black paſte &amp; make it into ſmall bals, which you muſt wrap in roſe leaves and dry them in the ſhade, then keep them well ſtopt in glaſſes. This is a perfume for Perſons of quality. One or two of them caſt upon coals or put into a quantity of roſe water that is ſet over the coals, will fill the room with a raviſhing and coeleſtiall vapour, that refreſhes the braine and vitall ſpirits and corrects the malignity of any contagious aire.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take</hi> Styrax calam, prepared as before, benzoin, of each <hi>half</hi> an <hi>ounce,</hi> your beſt wood of aloes two <hi>drams,</hi> Zibet that is not adulterate one <hi>dram, Gallia moſcata</hi> one <hi>ſcruple,</hi> oile of roſes, and of cloves, of
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:51143:104"/>each <hi>half</hi> a <hi>ſcruple,</hi> mix them according to art, and with damask roſe water make them into little bals. They are of the ſame virtue with the former and uſed in the ſame manner.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> How to perfume Gloves.</head>
                  <p>TO adde the <hi>roſes</hi> ſweetneſs, to the <hi>lillied</hi> lovelineſs of your ſnowie hands, ſent your gloves with theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes: and they who take ye by the hand, ſhall find all pleaſures graſpt in a handfull, wherein all raviſhing objects are, that can convey thoſe charming delights to the admiring fancy, that both pleaſe the ſight and feaſt the other ſenſes too.</p>
                  <p>Firſt then perfume your gloves thus, <hi>Take</hi> a pair of ſmooth new Cordavan gloves, waſh them well for two or three daies (once a day) in good white wine; preſſing them well and ſmoothing them, after every waſhing; after the laſt waſhing, when they are almoſt dry waſh them in roſe water, wherein musk hath been
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:51143:105"/>diſſolved; let them lye in that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for one day; then pull one of the gloves on your hand, and with your other hand ſmooth and dry it, then do the ſame to the other glove. When this is done, ſteep in water for four or five daies four <hi>ounces</hi> of gum tragagant, the whiteſt you can get; musk, amber, dryed marjo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram of each one <hi>ſcruple;</hi> boil them gently altogether, and in the boiling add <hi>half</hi> a <hi>ſcruple</hi> of Zibet, put theſe into a coverd veſſel till they are cold, then chaff and rub it well into the gloves, afterward lay them in ſome place to dry.</p>
                  <p>Or waſh thoſe gloves ye intend to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume, firſt well in white wine, then dry them in the ſhade, after waſh them in a <hi>pint</hi> of roſe water, ſented with oile of cloves, jaſmine, nutmegs, labdanum of each <hi>half</hi> a <hi>ſcruple,</hi> then take musk, zibet, ambergreece of each five <hi>graines,</hi> beat them together in a mortar with a little oile of ſpike, and mucilage of gum traga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant diſſolv'd in roſe water, chaff this compoſition into the waſht gloves, before the fire.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51143:105"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
